<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>JWST arXiv Feed (author)</title><link>https://github.com/gbrammer/arxiv-to-rss</link><description>Custom arXiv Query of JWST articles</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2024 17:43:52 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.1.1</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>The JWST UNCOVER Treasury survey: Ultradeep NIRSpec and NIRCam  ObserVations before the Epoch of Reionization</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.04026v3</link><description>Rachel Bezanson, Ivo Labbe, Katherine E. Whitaker, Joel Leja, Sedona H. Price, Marijn Franx, Gabe Brammer, Danilo Marchesini, Adi Zitrin, Bingjie Wang, John R. Weaver, Lukas J. Furtak, Hakim Atek, Dan Coe, Sam E. Cutler, Pratika Dayal, Pieter van Dokkum, Robert Feldmann, Natascha Forster Schreiber, Seiji Fujimoto, Marla Geha, Karl Glazebrook, Anna de Graaff, Jenny E. Greene, Stephanie Juneau, Susan Kassin, Mariska Kriek, Gourav Khullar, Michael Maseda, Lamiya A. Mowla, Adam Muzzin, Themiya Nanayakkara, Erica J. Nelson, Pascal A. Oesch, Camilla Pacifici, Richard Pan, Casey Papovich, David Setton, Alice E. Shapley, Renske Smit, Mauro Stefanon, Edward N. Taylor, Christina C. Williams
    &lt;p&gt;
    In this paper we describe the survey design for the Ultradeep NIRSpec andNIRCam ObserVations before the Epoch of Reionization (UNCOVER) Cycle 1 \JWSTTreasury program, which executed its early imaging component in November 2022.The UNCOVER survey includes ultradeep ($\sim29-30\mathrm{AB}$) imaging of$\sim$45 arcmin$^2$ on and around the well-studied Abell 2744 galaxy cluster at$z=0.308$ and will follow-up ${\sim}500$ galaxies with extremely deeplow-resolution spectroscopy with the NIRSpec/PRISM during the summer of 2023,with repeat visits in summer 2024. We describe the science goals, surveydesign, target selection, and planned data releases. We also present andcharacterize the depths of the first NIRCam imaging mosaic, highlightingpreviously unparalleled resolved and ultradeep 2-4 micron imaging of knownobjects in the field. The UNCOVER primary NIRCam mosaic spans 28.8 arcmin$^2$in seven filters (F115W, F150W, F200W, F277W, F356W, F410M, F444W) and 16.8arcmin$^2$ in our NIRISS parallel (F115W, F150W, F200W, F356W, and F444W). Tomaximize early community use of the Treasury data set, we publicly release fullreduced mosaics of public JWST imaging including 45 arcmin$^2$ NIRCam and 17arcmin$^2$ NIRISS mosaics on and around the Abell 2744 cluster, including theHubble Frontier Field primary and parallel footprints.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 19 pages, 8 figures, 4 tables, Accepted for publication in ApJ
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.04026v3" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.04026v3 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Rachel Bezanson</author><pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2022 01:47:01 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.04026v3</guid></item><item><title>A strong He II $λ$1640 emitter with extremely blue UV spectral  slope at $z=8.16$: presence of Pop III stars?</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.04476v2</link><description>Xin Wang, Cheng Cheng, Junqiang Ge, Xiao-Lei Meng, Emanuele Daddi, Haojing Yan, Zhiyuan Ji, Yifei Jin, Tucker Jones, Matthew A. Malkan, Pablo Arrabal Haro, Gabriel Brammer, Masamune Oguri, Meicun Hou, Shiwu Zhang
    &lt;p&gt;
    Cosmic hydrogen reionization and cosmic production of first metals are majorphase transitions of the universe occurring during the first billion yearsafter the Big Bang, however these are still underexplored observationally.Using the JWST NIRSpec prism spectroscopy, we report the discovery of asub-$L_\ast$ galaxy at $z_{\rm spec}=8.1623\pm0.0007$, dubbed RXJ2129-z8HeII,via the detection of a series of strong rest-frame UV/optical nebular emissionlines and the clear Lyman break. RXJ2129-z8HeII shows a pronounced UV continuumwith an extremely steep (i.e. blue) spectral slope of$\beta=-2.53_{-0.07}^{+0.06}$, the steepest amongst all spectroscopicallyconfirmed galaxies at $z_{\rm spec}\gtrsim7$, in support of its very hardionizing spectrum that could lead to a significant leakage of its ionizingflux. Therefore, RXJ2129-z8HeII is representative of the key galaxy populationdriving the cosmic reionization. More importantly, we detect a strong He II$\lambda$1640 emission line in its spectrum, one of the highest redshifts atwhich such a line is robustly detected. Its high rest-frame equivalent width(${\rm EW}=21\pm4$ Angstrom) and extreme flux ratios with respect to UV metaland Balmer lines raise the possibility that part of RXJ2129-z8HeII's stellarpopulations could be Pop III-like. Through careful photoionization modeling, weshow that the physically calibrated phenomenological models of the ionizingspectra of Pop III stars with strong mass loss can successfully reproduce theemission line flux ratios observed in RXJ2129-z8HeII. Assuming the Eddingtonlimit, the total mass of the Pop III stars within this system is estimated tobe $7.8\pm1.4\times10^5 M_\odot$. To date, this galaxy presents the mostcompelling case in the early universe where trace Pop III stars might coexistwith metal-enriched populations.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Accepted to ApJL. 24 pages, 12 figures, and 5 tables
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.04476v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.04476v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Xin Wang</author><pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2022 18:51:10 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.04476v2</guid></item><item><title>JWST and ALMA Multiple-Line Study in and around a Galaxy at $z=8.496$:  Optical to FIR Line Ratios and the Onset of an Outflow Promoting Ionizing  Photon Escape</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.06863v3</link><description>Seiji Fujimoto, Masami Ouchi, Kimihiko Nakajima, Yuichi Harikane, Yuki Isobe, Gabriel Brammer, Masamune Oguri, Clara Giménez-Arteaga, Kasper E. Heintz, Vasily Kokorev, Franz E. Bauer, Andrea Ferrara, Takashi Kojima, Claudia del P. Lagos, Sommovigo Laura, Daniel Schaerer, Kazuhiro Shimasaku, Bunyo Hatsukade, Kotaro Kohno, Fengwu Sun, Francesco Valentino, Darach Watson, Yoshinobu Fudamoto, Akio K. Inoue, Jorge González-López, Anton M. Koekemoer, Kirsten Knudsen, Minju M. Lee, Georgios E. Magdis, Johan Richard, Victoria B. Strait, Yuma Sugahara, Yoichi Tamura, Sune Toft, Hideki Umehata, Gregory Walth
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present ALMA deep spectroscopy for a lensed galaxy at $z_{\rm spec}=8.496$with $\log(M_{\rm star}/M_{\odot})\sim7.8$ whose optical nebular lines andstellar continuum are detected by JWST/NIRSpec and NIRCam Early ReleaseObservations in SMACS0723. Our ALMA spectrum shows [OIII]88$\mu$m and[CII]158$\mu$m line detections at $4.0\sigma$ and $4.5\sigma$, respectively.The redshift and position of the [OIII] line coincide with those of the JWSTsource, while the [CII] line is blue-shifted by 90 km s$^{-1}$ with a spatialoffset of $0.''5$ ($\approx0.5$ kpc in source plane) from the JWST source. TheNIRCam F444W image, including [OIII]$\lambda$5007 and H$\beta$ line emission,spatially extends beyond the stellar components by a factor of $&gt;8$. Thisindicates that the $z=8.5$ galaxy has already experienced strong outflows whoseoxygen and carbon produce the extended [OIII]$\lambda$5007 and the offset [CII]emission, which would promote ionizing photon escape and facilitatereionization. With careful slit-loss corrections and removals of emissionspatially outside the galaxy, we evaluate the [OIII]88$\mu$m/$\lambda$5007 lineratio, and derive the electron density $n_{\rm e}$ by photoionization modelingto be $220^{+170}_{-100}$ cm$^{-3}$, which is comparable with those of$z\sim2-3$ galaxies. We estimate an [OIII]88$\mu$m/[CII]158$\mu$m line ratio inthe galaxy of $&gt;4$, as high as those of known $z\sim6-9$ galaxies. This high[OIII]88$\mu$m/[CII]158$\mu$m line ratio is generally explained by the high$n_{\rm e}$ as well as the low metallicity ($Z_{\rmgas}/Z_{\odot}=0.04^{+0.02}_{-0.02}$), high ionization parameter ($\log U &gt;-2.27$), and low carbon-to-oxygen abundance ratio ($\log$(C/O)$=[-0.52:-0.24]$) obtained from the JWST/NIRSpec data; further [CII] follow-upobservations will constrain the covering fraction of photodissociation regions.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 27 pages, 11 figures, 5 tables. ApJ in press
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.06863v3" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.06863v3 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Seiji Fujimoto</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2022 19:09:59 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.06863v3</guid></item><item><title>A population of faint, old, and massive quiescent galaxies at 3 &lt; z &lt; 4  revealed by JWST NIRSpec Spectroscopy</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.11638v3</link><description>Themiya Nanayakkara, Karl Glazebrook, Colin Jacobs, Lalitwadee Kawinwanichakij, Corentin Schreiber, Gabriel Brammer, James Esdaile, Glenn G. Kacprzak, Ivo Labbe, Claudia Lagos, Danilo Marchesini, Z. Cemile Marsan, Pascal A. Oesch, Casey Papovich, Rhea-Silvia Remus, Kim-Vy H. Tran
    &lt;p&gt;
    Here we present a sample of 12 massive quiescent galaxy candidates at z~3-4observed with the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) Near Infrared Spectrograph(NIRSpec). These galaxies were pre-selected from the Hubble Space Telescopeimaging and 10 of our sources were unable to be spectroscopically confirmed byground based spectroscopy. By combining spectroscopic data from NIRSpec withmulti-wavelength imaging data from the JWST Near Infrared Camera (NIRCam), weanalyse their stellar populations and their formation histories. We find thatall of our galaxies classify as quiescent based on the reconstruction of theirstar formation histories but show a variety of quenching timescales and ages.All our galaxies are massive ($\sim0.1-1.2 \times 10^{11} M\odot$), with massescomparable to massive galaxies in the local Universe. We find that the oldestgalaxy in our sample formed $\sim1.0\times10^{11} M\odot$ of mass within thefirst few hundred million years of the Universe and has been quenched for morethan a billion years by the time of observation at z$\sim$3.2 ($\sim$2 billionyears after the Big Bang). Our results point to very early formation of massivegalaxies requiring a high conversion rate of baryons to stars in the earlyUniverse.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Published in Nature Scientific Reports
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.11638v3" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.11638v3 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Themiya Nanayakkara</author><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 12:08:33 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.11638v3</guid></item><item><title>JWST NIRSpec spectroscopy of the triply-lensed $z = 10.17$ galaxy  MACS0647$-$JD</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.03042v3</link><description>Tiger Yu-Yang Hsiao, Abdurro'uf, Dan Coe, Rebecca L. Larson, Intae Jung, Matilde Mingozzi, Pratika Dayal, Nimisha Kumari, Vasily Kokorev, Anton Vikaeus, Gabriel Brammer, Lukas J. Furtak, Angela Adamo, Felipe Andrade-Santos, Jacqueline Antwi-Danso, Marusa Bradac, Larry D. Bradley, Tom Broadhurst, Adam C. Carnall, Christopher J. Conselice, Jose M. Diego, Megan Donahue, Jan J. Eldridge, Seiji Fujimoto, Alaina Henry, Svea Hernandez, Taylor A. Hutchison, Bethan L. James, Colin Norman, Hyunbae Park, Norbert Pirzkal, Marc Postman, Massimo Ricotti, Jane R. Rigby, Eros Vanzella, Brian Welch, Stephen M. Wilkins, Rogier A. Windhorst, Xinfeng Xu, Erik Zackrisson, Adi Zitrin
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present JWST/NIRSpec prism spectroscopy of MACS0647-JD, the triply-lensed$z \sim 11$ candidate discovered in HST imaging and spatially resolved by JWSTimaging into two components A and B. Spectroscopy of component A yields aspectroscopic redshift $z=10.17$ based on 7 detected emission lines: CIII]$\lambda\lambda$1907,1909, [OII] $\lambda$3727, [NeIII] $\lambda$3869, [NeIII]$\lambda$3968, H$\delta$ $\lambda$4101, H$\gamma$ $\lambda$4340, and [OIII]$\lambda$4363. These are the second-most distant detections of these emissionlines to date, in a galaxy observed just 460 million years after the Big Bang.Based on observed and extrapolated line flux ratios we derive a gas-phasemetallicity $Z =$ log(O/H) = $7.5 - 8.0$, or $(0.06 - 0.2)$ $Z_\odot$,ionization parameter log($U$) $\sim -1.9\pm0.2$, and an ionizing photonproduction efficiency ${\rm log}(\xi_{\rm ion})=25.2\pm0.2\,$erg$^{-1}$ Hz. Thespectrum has a softened Lyman-$\alpha$ break, evidence for a strong Ly$\alpha$damping wing, suggesting that MACS0647-JD was unable to ionize its surroundingsbeyond its immediate vicinity ($R_{\text{HII}} \ll 1$ pMpc). The Ly$\alpha$damping wing also suppresses the F150W photometry, explaining the slightlyoverestimated photometric redshift $z = 10.6 \pm 0.3$. MACS0647-JD has astellar mass log($M/M_\odot$) = $8.1 \pm 0.3$, including $\sim$ 6$\times 10^7M_\odot$ in component A, most of which formed recently (within $\sim$ 20 Myr)with a star formation rate $2\pm1 M_\odot$ / yr, all within an effective radius$70\pm24\,$pc. The smaller component B ($r \sim 20$) pc is likely older($\sim$100 Myr) with more dust ($A_V \sim 0.1$ mag), as found previously.Spectroscopy of a fainter companion galaxy C separated by a distance of \about\3$\,$kpc reveals a Lyman break consistent with $z = 10.17$. MACS0647-JD islikely the most distant galaxy merger known.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 22 pages, 6 figures, accepted for publication in ApJ
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2305.03042v3" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2305.03042v3 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Tiger Yu-Yang Hsiao</author><pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2023 17:58:30 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.03042v3</guid></item><item><title>Little Red Dots: an abundant population of faint AGN at z~5 revealed by  the EIGER and FRESCO JWST surveys</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.05448v3</link><description>Jorryt Matthee, Rohan P. Naidu, Gabriel Brammer, John Chisholm, Anna-Christina Eilers, Andy Goulding, Jenny Greene, Daichi Kashino, Ivo Labbe, Simon J. Lilly, Ruari Mackenzie, Pascal A. Oesch, Andrea Weibel, Stijn Wuyts, Mengyuan Xiao, Rongmon Bordoloi, Rychard Bouwens, Pieter van Dokkum, Garth Illingworth, Ivan Kramarenko, Michael V. Maseda, Charlotte Mason, Romain A. Meyer, Erica J. Nelson, Naveen A. Reddy, Irene Shivaei, Robert A. Simcoe, Minghao Yue
    &lt;p&gt;
    Characterising the prevalence and properties of faint active galactic nuclei(AGN) in the early Universe is key for understanding the formation ofsupermassive black holes (SMBHs) and determining their role in cosmicreionization. We perform a spectroscopic search for broad H$\alpha$ emitters at$z\approx4-6$ using deep JWST/NIRCam imaging and wide field slitlessspectroscopy from the EIGER and FRESCO surveys. We identify 20 H$\alpha$ linesat $z=4.2-5.5$ that have broad components with line widths from $\sim1200-3700$km s$^{-1}$, contributing $\sim30-90$ % of the total line flux. We interpretthese broad components as being powered by accretion onto SMBHs with impliedmasses $\sim10^{7-8}$ M$_{\odot}$. In the UV luminosity range M$_{\rm UV}=-21$to $-18$, we measure number densities of $\approx10^{-5}$ cMpc$^{-3}$. This isan order of magnitude higher than expected from extrapolating quasar UVluminosity functions. Yet, such AGN are found in only $&lt;1$ % of star-forminggalaxies at $z\sim5$. The SMBH mass function agrees with large cosmologicalsimulations. In two objects we detect narrow red- and blue-shifted H$\alpha$absorption indicative, respectively, of dense gas fueling SMBH growth andoutflows. We may be witnessing early AGN feedback that will clear dust-freepathways through which more massive blue quasars are seen. We uncover a strongcorrelation between reddening and the fraction of total galaxy luminosityarising from faint AGN. This implies that early SMBH growth is highly obscuredand that faint AGN are only minor contributors to cosmic reionization.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 26 pages, 20 figures. Accepted for publication in ApJ. Various  improvements and updated citations. Main additions: colours (Fig 11), broad  Halpha LF (Fig 18, Sect 5.2), comparisons to simulations (Sect 5.3)
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2306.05448v3" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2306.05448v3 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Jorryt Matthee</author><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2023 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2306.05448v3</guid></item><item><title>Size - Stellar Mass Relation and Morphology of Quiescent Galaxies at  $z\geq3$ in Public $JWST$ Fields</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2307.06994v2</link><description>Kei Ito, Francesco Valentino, Gabriel Brammer, Andreas L. Faisst, Steven Gillman, Carlos Gomez-Guijarro, Katriona M. L. Gould, Kasper E. Heintz, Olivier Ilbert, Christian Kragh Jespersen, Vasily Kokorev, Mariko Kubo, Georgios E. Magdis, Conor McPartland, Masato Onodera, Francesca Rizzo, Masayuki Tanaka, Sune Toft, Aswin P. Vijayan, John R. Weaver, Katherine E. Whitaker, Lillian Wright
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present the results of a systematic study of the rest-frame opticalmorphology of quiescent galaxies at $z \geq 3$ using the Near-Infrared Camera(NIRCam) onboard $JWST$. Based on a sample selected by $UVJ$ color or $NUVUVJ$color, we focus on 26 quiescent galaxies with$9.8&lt;\log{(M_\star/M_\odot)}&lt;11.4$ at $2.8&lt;z_{\rm phot}&lt;4.6$ with publiclyavailable $JWST$ data. Their sizes are constrained by fitting the S\'ersicprofile to all available NIRCam images. We see a negative correlation betweenthe observed wavelength and the size in our sample and derive their size at therest-frame $0.5\, {\rm \mu m}$ taking into account this trend. Our quiescentgalaxies show a significant correlation between the rest-frame $0.5\, {\rm \mum}$ size and the stellar mass at $z\geq3$. The analytical fit for them at$\log{(M_\star/M_\odot)}&gt;10.3$ implies that our size - stellar mass relationsare below those at lower redshifts, with the amplitude of $\sim0.6\, {\rm kpc}$at $M_\star = 5\times 10^{10}\, M_\odot$. This value agrees with theextrapolation from the size evolution of quiescent galaxies at $z&lt;3$ in theliterature, implying that the size of quiescent galaxies increasesmonotonically from $z\sim3-5$. Our sample is mainly composed of galaxies withbulge-like structures according to their median S\'ersic index and axis ratioof $n\sim3-4$ and $q\sim0.6-0.8$, respectively. On the other hand, there is atrend of increasing fraction of galaxies with low S\'ersic index, suggesting$3&lt;z&lt;5$ might be the epoch of onset of morphological transformation with afraction of very notable disky quenched galaxies.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 25 pages, 17 figures, 3 tables; accepted for publication in ApJ
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2307.06994v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2307.06994v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Kei Ito</author><pubDate>Thu, 13 Jul 2023 18:00:03 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2307.06994v2</guid></item><item><title>A massive galaxy that formed its stars at $z \sim 11$</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2308.05606v3</link><description>Karl Glazebrook, Themiya Nanayakkara, Corentin Schreiber, Claudia Lagos, Lalitwadee Kawinwanichakij, Colin Jacobs, Harry Chittenden, Gabriel Brammer, Glenn G. Kacprzak, Ivo Labbe, Danilo Marchesini, Z. Cemile Marsan, Pascal A. Oesch, Casey Papovich, Rhea-Silvia Remus, Kim-Vy H. Tran, James Esdaile, Angel Chandro Gomez
    &lt;p&gt;
    The formation of galaxies by gradual hierarchical co-assembly of baryons andcold dark matter halos is a fundamental paradigm underpinning modernastrophysics and predicts a strong decline in the number of massive galaxies atearly cosmic times. Extremely massive quiescent galaxies (stellar masses$&gt;10^{11}$ M$_\odot$) have now been observed as early as 1-2 billions yearsafter the Big Bang; these are extremely constraining on theoretical models asthey form 300-500 Myr earlier and only some models can form massive galaxiesthis early. Here we report on the spectroscopic observations with the JamesWebb Space Telescope of a massive quiescent galaxy ZF-UDS-7329 at redshift3.205 $\pm$ 0.005 that eluded deep ground-based spectrscopy, is significantlyredder than typical and whose spectrum reveals features typical of much olderstellar populations. Detailed modelling shows the stellar population formedaround 1.5 billion years earlier in time (z ~ 11) at an epoch when dark matterhalos of sufficient hosting mass have not yet assembled in the standardscenario. This observation may point to the presence of undetected populationsof early galaxies and the possibility of significant gaps in our understandingof early stellar populations, galaxy formation and/or the nature of darkmatter.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 21 pages, 6 figures, updated to reflect accepted version. v3 with  figure caption clarified
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2308.05606v3" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2308.05606v3 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Karl Glazebrook</author><pubDate>Thu, 10 Aug 2023 14:35:37 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2308.05606v3</guid></item><item><title>A high black hole to host mass ratio in a lensed AGN in the early  Universe</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2308.05735v2</link><description>Lukas J. Furtak, Ivo Labbé, Adi Zitrin, Jenny E. Greene, Pratika Dayal, Iryna Chemerynska, Vasily Kokorev, Tim B. Miller, Andy D. Goulding, Anna de Graaff, Rachel Bezanson, Gabriel B. Brammer, Sam E. Cutler, Joel Leja, Richard Pan, Sedona H. Price, Bingjie Wang, John R. Weaver, Katherine E. Whitaker, Hakim Atek, Ákos Bogdán, Stéphane Charlot, Emma Curtis-Lake, Pieter van Dokkum, Ryan Endsley, Yoshinobu Fudamoto, Seiji Fujimoto, Karl Glazebrook, Stéphanie Juneau, Danilo Marchesini, Michael V. Maseda, Erica Nelson, Pascal A. Oesch, Adèle Plat, David J. Setton, Daniel P. Stark, Christina C. Williams
    &lt;p&gt;
    Early JWST observations have uncovered a new population of red sources thatmight represent a previously overlooked phase of supermassive black hole growth(Kocevski et al. 2023; Matthee et al. 2023, Labb\'e et al. 2023). One of themost intriguing examples is an extremely red, point-like object that was foundto be triply-imaged by the strong lensing (SL) cluster Abell 2744 (Furtak etal. 2023). Here we present deep JWST/NIRSpec observations of this object,Abell2744-QSO1. The spectroscopy confirms that the three images are of the sameobject, and that it is a highly reddened ($A_V\simeq3$) broad emission-lineActive Galactic Nucleus (AGN) at a redshift of$z_{\mathrm{spec}}=7.0451\pm0.0005$. From the width of H$\beta$($\mathrm{FWHM}=2800\pm250\,\frac{\mathrm{km}}{\mathrm{s}}$) we derive a blackhole mass of $M_{\mathrm{BH}}=4_{-1}^{+2}\times10^7\,\mathrm{M}_{\odot}$. Weinfer a very high ratio of black hole to galaxy mass of at least 3%, an orderof magnitude more than is seen in local galaxies (Bennert et al. 2011), andpossibly as high as 100%. The lack of strong metal lines in the spectrumtogether with the high bolometric luminosity($L_{\mathrm{bol}}=(1.1\pm0.3)\times10^{45}\,\frac{\mathrm{erg}}{\mathrm{s}}$)indicate that we are seeing the black hole in a phase of rapid growth,accreting at 30% of the Eddington limit. The rapid growth and high black holeto galaxy mass ratio of A2744-QSO1 suggest that it may represent the missinglink between black hole seeds (Volonteri et al. 2021) and the first luminousquasars (Fan et al. 2022).
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Published in Nature. Updated to the accepted version
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2308.05735v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2308.05735v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Lukas J. Furtak</author><pubDate>Thu, 10 Aug 2023 17:56:31 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2308.05735v2</guid></item><item><title>UNCOVER: JWST Spectroscopy of Three Cold Brown Dwarfs at  Kiloparsec-scale Distances</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2308.12107v2</link><description>Adam J. Burgasser, Rachel Bezanson, Ivo Labbe, Gabriel Brammer, Sam E. Cutler, Lukas J. Furtak, Jenny E. Greene, Roman Gerasimov, Joel Leja, Richard Pan, Sedona H. Price, Bingjie Wang, John R. Weaver, Katherine E. Whitaker, Seiji Fujimoto, Vasily Kokorev, Pratika Dayal, Themiya Nanayakkara, Christina C. Williams, Danilo Marchesini, Adi Zitrin, Pieter van Dokkum
    &lt;p&gt;
    We report JWST/NIRSpec spectra of three distant T-type brown dwarfsidentified in the Ultradeep NIRSpec and NIRCam ObserVations before the Epoch ofReionization (UNCOVER) survey of the Abell 2744 lensing field. One source waspreviously reported as a candidate T dwarf on the basis of NIRCam photometry,while two sources were initially identified as candidate active galacticnuclei. Low-resolution 1--5 $\mu$m spectra confirm the presence of molecularfeatures consistent with T dwarf atmospheres, and comparison to spectralstandards infers classifications of sdT1, T6, and T8--T9. The warmest source,UNCOVER-BD-1, shows evidence of subsolar metallicity, and atmosphere model fitsindicates T$_{eff}$ = 1300 K and [M/H] $\sim$ $-$1.0, making this one of thefew spectroscopically-confirmed T subdwarfs known. The coldest source,UNCOVER-BD-3, is near the T/Y dwarf boundary with T$_{eff}$ = 550 K, and ouranalysis indicates the presence of PH$_3$ in the 3--5~$\mu$m region, favoredover CO$_2$ and a possible indicator of subsolar metallicity. We estimatedistances of 0.9--4.5 kpc from the Galactic midplane, making these the mostdistant brown dwarfs with spectroscopic confirmation. Population simulationsindicate high probabilities of membership in the Galactic thick disk for two ofthese brown dwarfs, and potential halo membership for UNCOVER-BD-1. Oursimulations indicate that there are approximately 5 T dwarfs and 1--2 L dwarfsin the Abell 2744 field down to F444W = 30 AB mag, roughly one-third of whichare thick disk members. These results highlight the utility of deepJWST/NIRSpec spectroscopy for identifying and characterizing the oldestmetal-poor brown dwarfs in the Milky Way.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: revised, accepted by ApJ 22 Nov 2023
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2308.12107v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2308.12107v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Adam J. Burgasser</author><pubDate>Tue, 22 Aug 2023 17:46:06 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2308.12107v2</guid></item><item><title>CECILIA: The Faint Emission Line Spectrum of z~2-3 Star-forming Galaxies</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2308.13508v2</link><description>Allison L. Strom, Gwen C. Rudie, Ryan F. Trainor, Gabriel B. Brammer, Michael V. Maseda, Menelaos Raptis, Noah S. J. Rogers, Charles C. Steidel, Yuguang Chen, David R. Law
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present the first results from CECILIA, a Cycle 1 JWST NIRSpec/MSA programthat uses ultra-deep ~30 hour G235M/F170LP observations to target multipleelectron temperature-sensitive auroral lines in the spectra of 33 galaxies atz~1-3. Using a subset of 23 galaxies, we construct two ~600 object-hourcomposite spectra, both with and without the stellar continuum, and use theseto investigate the characteristic rest-optical (5700-8500 Angstrom) spectrum ofstar-forming galaxies at the peak epoch of cosmic star formation. Emissionlines of eight different elements (H, He, N, O, Si, S, Ar, and Ni) aredetected, with most of these features observed to be &lt;3% the strength ofH-alpha. We report the characteristic strength of three auroral lines([NII]5756, [SIII]6313, and [OII]7322,7332), as well as other semi-strong andfaint emission lines, including forbidden [NiII]7380,7414 and the OI 8449recombination line, some of which have never before been observed outside ofthe local universe. Using these measurements, we find T_e[NII]=13630+/-2540 K,representing the first measurement of electron temperature using [NII] in thehigh-redshift universe. We also see evidence for broad line emission with aFWHM of ~536 km/s; the broad component of H-alpha is 6.01-28.31% the strengthof the narrow component and likely arises from star-formation driven outflows.Finally, we briefly comment on the feasibility of obtaining large samples offaint emission lines using JWST in the future.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Published in ApJL in November 2023
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2308.13508v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2308.13508v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Allison L. Strom</author><pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2023 17:38:31 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2308.13508v2</guid></item><item><title>Accelerated Formation of Ultra-Massive Galaxies in the First Billion  Years</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2309.02492v2</link><description>Mengyuan Xiao, Pascal Oesch, David Elbaz, Longji Bing, Erica Nelson, Andrea Weibel, Garth Illingworth, Pieter van Dokkum, Rohan Naidu, Emanuele Daddi, Rychard Bouwens, Jorryt Matthee, Stijn Wuyts, John Chisholm, Gabriel Brammer, Mark Dickinson, Benjamin Magnelli, Lucas Leroy, Daniel Schaerer, Thomas Herard-Demanche, Seunghwan Lim, Laia Barrufet, Ryan Endsley, Yoshinobu Fudamoto, Carlos Gómez-Guijarro, Rashmi Gottumukkala, Ivo Labbe, Daniel Magee, Danilo Marchesini, Michael Maseda, Yuxiang Qin, Naveen Reddy, Alice Shapley, Irene Shivaei, Marko Shuntov, Mauro Stefanon, Katherine Whitaker, J. Stuart Wyithe
    &lt;p&gt;
    Recent JWST observations have revealed an unexpected abundance of massivegalaxy candidates in the early Universe, extending further in redshift and tolower luminosity than what had previously been found by sub-millimeter surveys.These JWST candidates have been interpreted as challenging the $\Lambda$CDMcosmology, but, so far, they have mostly relied only on rest-frame ultravioletdata and lacked spectroscopic confirmation of their redshifts. Here we report asystematic study of 36 massive dust-obscured galaxies with spectroscopicredshifts between $z_{\rm spec}=5-9$ from the JWST FRESCO survey. We find notension with the $\Lambda$CDM model in our sample. However, three ultra-massivegalaxies (log$M_{\star}/M_{\odot}$ $\gtrsim11.0$) require an exceptionalfraction of 50% of baryons converted into stars -- two to three times higherthan even the most efficient galaxies at later epochs. The contribution from anactive nucleus is unlikely because of their extended emission. Ultra-massivegalaxies account for as much as 17% of the total cosmic star formation ratedensity at $z\sim5-6$.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Nature in press. Updated to the accepted version. 24 pages, 4 main  figures, 7 supplementary figures, 3 supplementary tables
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2309.02492v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2309.02492v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Mengyuan Xiao</author><pubDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2023 18:00:01 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2309.02492v2</guid></item><item><title>The UNCOVER Survey: A First-look HST+JWST Catalog of Galaxy Redshifts  and Stellar Population Properties Spanning $0.2 \lesssim z \lesssim 15$</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2310.01276v3</link><description>Bingjie Wang, Joel Leja, Ivo Labbé, Rachel Bezanson, Katherine E. Whitaker, Gabriel Brammer, Lukas J. Furtak, John R. Weaver, Sedona H. Price, Adi Zitrin, Hakim Atek, Dan Coe, Sam E. Cutler, Pratika Dayal, Pieter van Dokkum, Robert Feldmann, Danilo Marchesini, Marijn Franx, Natascha Förster Schreiber, Seiji Fujimoto, Marla Geha, Karl Glazebrook, Anna de Graaff, Jenny E. Greene, Stéphanie Juneau, Susan Kassin, Mariska Kriek, Gourav Khullar, Michael Maseda, Lamiya A. Mowla, Adam Muzzin, Themiya Nanayakkara, Erica J. Nelson, Pascal A. Oesch, Camilla Pacifici, Richard Pan, Casey Papovich, David J. Setton, Alice E. Shapley, Renske Smit, Mauro Stefanon, Katherine A. Suess, Edward N. Taylor, Christina C. Williams
    &lt;p&gt;
    The recent UNCOVER survey with the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) exploitsthe nearby cluster Abell 2744 to create the deepest view of our universe todate by leveraging strong gravitational lensing. In this work, we performphotometric fitting of more than 50,000 robustly detected sources out to $z\sim 15$. We show the redshift evolution of stellar ages, star formation rates,and rest-frame colors across the full range of $0.2 \lesssim z \lesssim 15$.The galaxy properties are inferred using the Prospector Bayesian inferenceframework using informative Prospector-$\beta$ priors on masses and starformation histories to produce joint redshift and stellar populationposteriors, and additionally lensing magnification is performed on-the-fly toensure consistency with the scale-dependent priors. We show that this approachproduces excellent photometric redshifts with $\sigma_{\rm NMAD} \sim 0.03$, ofa similar quality to the established photometric redshift code EAzY. In linewith the open-source scientific objective of the Treasury survey, we publiclyrelease the stellar population catalog with this paper, derived from thephotometric catalog adapting aperture sizes based on source profiles. Thisrelease includes posterior moments, maximum-likelihood spectra, star-formationhistories, and full posterior distributions, offering a rich data set toexplore the processes governing galaxy formation and evolution over a parameterspace now accessible by JWST.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Corrected typos: Eq.1 should've been (1-kappa)^2, and the lens maps  are normalized to D_ds/D_s=1. These errors were only in the writing; no data  products or results were affected. The SPS catalogs are accessible via the  UNCOVER survey webpage: https://jwst-uncover.github.io/DR2.html#SPSCatalogs,  with a copy deposited to Zenodo: https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8401181
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2310.01276v3" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2310.01276v3 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Bingjie Wang</author><pubDate>Mon, 02 Oct 2023 15:25:56 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2310.01276v3</guid></item><item><title>Bursty star formation and galaxy-galaxy interactions in low-mass  galaxies 1 Gyr after the Big Bang</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2310.02314v2</link><description>Yoshihisa Asada, Marcin Sawicki, Roberto Abraham, Maruša Bradač, Gabriel Brammer, Guillaume Desprez, Vince Estrada-Carpenter, Kartheik Iyer, Nicholas Martis, Jasleen Matharu, Lamiya Mowla, Adam Muzzin, Gaël Noirot, Ghassan T. E. Sarrouh, Victoria Strait, Chris J. Willott, Anishya Harshan
    &lt;p&gt;
    We use CANUCS JWST/NIRCam imaging of galaxies behind thegravitationally-lensing cluster MACS J0417.5-1154 to investigate star formationburstiness in low-mass ($M_\star\sim10^8\ M_\odot$) galaxies at $z\sim4.7-6.5$.Our sample of 123 galaxies is selected using the Lyman break selection andphotometric emission-line excess methods. Sixty per cent of the 123 galaxies inthis sample have H$\alpha$-to-UV flux ratios that deviate significantly fromthe range of $\eta_{1500}$ values consistent with smooth and steady starformation histories. This large fraction indicates that the majority oflow-mass galaxies is experiencing bursty star formation histories at highredshift. We also searched for interacting galaxies in our sample and foundthat they are remarkably common ($\sim40$ per cent of the sample). Compared tonon-interacting galaxies, interacting galaxies are more likely to have very lowH$\alpha$-to-UV ratios, suggesting that galaxy-galaxy interactions enhance starformation burstiness and enable faster quenching (with timescales of$\lesssim100$ Myr) that follows the rapid rise of star formation activity.Given the high frequency of galaxy-galaxy interactions and the rapid SFRfluctuations they appear to cause, we conclude that galaxy-galaxy interactionscould be a leading cause of bursty star formation in low-mass, high-$z$galaxies. They could thus play a significant role in the evolution of thegalaxy population at early cosmological times.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 20 pages, 15 figures, and 1 table. Accepted for publication in MNRAS
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2310.02314v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2310.02314v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Yoshihisa Asada</author><pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 18:00:03 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2310.02314v2</guid></item><item><title>$Λ$CDM not dead yet: massive high-z Balmer break galaxies are less  common than previously reported</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2310.03063v3</link><description>Guillaume Desprez, Nicholas S. Martis, Yoshihisa Asada, Marcin Sawicki, Chris J. Willott, Adam Muzzin, Roberto G. Abraham, Maruša Bradač, Gabe Brammer, Vicente Estrada-Carpenter, Kartheik G. Iyer, Jasleen Matharu, Lamiya Mowla, Gaël Noirot, Ghassan T. E. Sarrouh, Victoria Strait, Rachel Gledhill, Gregor Rihtaršič
    &lt;p&gt;
    Early JWST observations that targeted so-called double-break sources(attributed to Lyman and Balmer breaks at $z&gt;7$), reported a previously unknownpopulation of very massive, evolved high-redshift galaxies. This surprisingdiscovery led to a flurry of attempts to explain these objects' unexpectedexistence including invoking alternatives to the standard $\Lambda$CDMcosmological paradigm. To test these early results, we adopted the samedouble-break candidate galaxy selection criteria to search for such objects inthe JWST images of the CAnadian NIRISS Unbiased Cluster Survey (CANUCS), andfound a sample of 19 sources over five independent CANUCS fields that cover atotal effective area of $\sim60\,$arcmin$^2$ at $z\sim8$. However, (1) our SEDfits do not yield exceptionally high stellar masses for our candidates, while(2) spectroscopy of five of the candidates shows that while all five are athigh redshifts, their red colours are due to high-EW emission lines instar-forming galaxies rather than Balmer breaks in massive, evolved systems.Additionally, (3) field-to-field variance leads to differences of $\sim 1.5$dex in the maximum stellar masses measured in the different fields, suggestingthat the early single-field JWST observations may have suffered from cosmicvariance and/or sample bias. Finally, (4) we show that the presence of even asingle massive outlier can dominate conclusions from small samples such asthose in early JWST observations. In conclusion, we find that the double-breaksources in CANUCS are not sufficiently massive or numerous to warrantquestioning the standard $\Lambda$CDM paradigm.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: V3 Accepted for publication in MNRAS, 13 pages (+5 in Appendix), 7  figures (+4), 1 table (+2)
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2310.03063v3" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2310.03063v3 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Guillaume Desprez</author><pubDate>Wed, 04 Oct 2023 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2310.03063v3</guid></item><item><title>Unveiling the hidden universe with JWST: The contribution of  dust-obscured galaxies to the stellar mass function at $z\sim3-8$</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2310.03787v2</link><description>R. Gottumukkala, L. Barrufet, P. A. Oesch, A. Weibel, N. Allen, B. Alcalde Pampliega, E. J. Nelson, C. C. Williams, G. Brammer, Y. Fudamoto, V. González, K. E. Heintz, G. Illingworth, D. Magee, R. P. Naidu, M. Shuntov, M. Stefanon, S. Toft, F. Valentino, M. Xiao
    &lt;p&gt;
    With the advent of JWST, we can probe the rest-frame optical emission ofgalaxies at $z&gt;3$ with high sensitivity and spatial resolution, making itpossible to accurately characterise red, optically-faint galaxies and thus movetowards a more complete census of the galaxy population at high redshifts. Tothis end, we present a sample of 148 massive, dusty galaxies from theJWST/CEERS survey, colour-selected using solely JWST bands. With deepJWST/NIRCam data from 1.15$\mu$m to 4.44$\mu$m and ancillary HST/ACS and WFC3data, we determine the physical properties of our sample using spectral energydistribution fitting with BAGPIPES. We demonstrate that our selection methodefficiently identifies massive ($\mathrm{\langle \log M_\star/M_\odot \rangle\sim 10}$) and dusty ($\mathrm{\langle A_V\rangle \sim 2.7\ mag}$) sources,with a majority at $z&gt;3$ and predominantly lying on the galaxy main-sequence.The main results of this work are the stellar mass functions (SMF) of red,optically-faint galaxies from redshifts between $3&lt;z&lt;8$: these galaxies make upa significant relative fraction of the pre-JWST total SMF at $3&lt;z&lt;4$ and$4&lt;z&lt;6$, and dominate the high-mass end of the pre-JWST SMF at $6&lt;z&lt;8$,suggesting that our census of the galaxy population needs amendment at theseepochs. While larger areas need to be surveyed in the future, our resultssuggest already that the integrated stellar mass density at $\mathrm{\logM_\star/M_\odot\geq9.25}$ may have been underestimated in pre-JWST studies byup to $\sim$15-20\% at $z\sim3-6$, and up to $\sim$45\% at $z\sim6-8$,indicating the rapid onset of obscured stellar mass assembly in the earlyuniverse.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 19 pages, 10 figures, published in MNRAS; view published article at  https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/530/1/966/7630203
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2310.03787v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2310.03787v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>R. Gottumukkala</author><pubDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2023 18:00:01 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2310.03787v2</guid></item><item><title>Quantifying the Effects of Known Unknowns on Inferred High-redshift  Galaxy Properties: Burstiness, the IMF, and Nebular Physics</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2310.06781v2</link><description>Bingjie Wang, Joel Leja, Hakim Atek, Ivo Labbe, Yijia Li, Rachel Bezanson, Gabriel Brammer, Sam E. Cutler, Pratika Dayal, Lukas J. Furtak, Jenny E. Greene, Vasily Kokorev, Richard Pan, Sedona H. Price, Katherine A. Suess, John R. Weaver, Katherine E. Whitaker, Christina C. Williams
    &lt;p&gt;
    The era of the James Webb Space Telescope ushers stellar population modelsinto uncharted territories, particularly at the high-redshift frontier. In acompanion paper, we apply the \texttt{Prospector} Bayesian framework to jointlyinfer galaxy redshifts and stellar population properties from broad-bandphotometry as part of the UNCOVER survey. Here we present a comprehensive errorbudget in spectral energy distribution (SED) modeling. Using a sample selectedto have photometric redshifts higher than 9, we quantify the systematic shiftsstemming from various model choices in inferred stellar mass, star formationrate (SFR), and age. These choices encompass different timescales for changesin the star formation history (SFH), non-universal stellar initial massfunctions (IMF), and the inclusion of variable nebular abundances, gas densityand ionizing photon budget. We find that the IMF exerts the strongest influenceon the inferred properties: the systematic uncertainties can be as much as 1dex, 2--5 times larger than the formal reported uncertainties in mass and SFR;and importantly, exceed the scatter seen when using different SED fittingcodes. Although the assumptions on the lower end of the IMF induce degeneracy,our findings suggest that a common practice in the literature of assessinguncertainties in SED-fitting processes by comparing multiple codes issubstantively underestimating the true systematic uncertainty. Highlystochastic SFHs change the inferred SFH by much larger than the formaluncertainties, and introduce $\sim 0.8$ dex systematics in SFR averaged overshort time scale and $\sim 0.3$ dex systematics in average age. Finally,employing a flexible nebular emission model causes $\sim 0.2$ dex systematicincrease in mass and SFR, comparable to the formal uncertainty. This paperconstitutes an initial step toward a complete uncertainty estimate in SEDmodeling.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Accepted for publication in ApJ. 22 pages, 10 figures, 2 tables
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2310.06781v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2310.06781v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Bingjie Wang</author><pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2023 16:55:48 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2310.06781v2</guid></item><item><title>Cosmic Vine: A z=3.44 large-scale structure hosting massive quiescent  galaxies</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2311.04867v3</link><description>Shuowen Jin, Nikolaj B. Sillassen, Georgios E. Magdis, Malte Brinch, Marko Shuntov, Gabriel Brammer, Raphael Gobat, Francesco Valentino, Adam C. Carnall, Minju Lee, Aswin P. Vijayan, Steven Gillman, Vasily Kokorev, Aurélien Le Bail, Thomas R. Greve, Bitten Gullberg, Katriona M. L. Gould, Sune Toft
    &lt;p&gt;
    We report the discovery of a large-scale structure at z=3.44 revealed by JWSTdata in the Extended Groth Strip (EGS) field. This structure, called the CosmicVine, consists of 20 galaxies with spectroscopic redshifts at 3.43&lt;z&lt;3.45 andsix galaxy overdensities ($4-7\sigma$) with consistent photometric redshifts,making up a vine-like structure extending over a ~4x0.2 pMpc^2 area. The twomost massive galaxies ($M_*\approx10^{10.9}~M_\odot$) of the Cosmic Vine arefound to be quiescent with bulge-dominated morphologies ($B/T&gt;70\%$).Comparisons with simulations suggest that the Cosmic Vine would form a clusterwith halo mass $M_{\rm halo}&gt;10^{14}M_\odot$ at z=0, and the two massivegalaxies are likely forming the brightest cluster galaxies (BCGs). The resultsunambiguously reveal that massive quiescent galaxies can form in growinglarge-scale structures at z&gt;3, thus disfavoring the environmental quenchingmechanisms that require a virialized cluster core. Instead, as suggested by theinteracting and bulge-dominated morphologies, the two galaxies are likelyquenched by merger-triggered starburst or active galactic nucleus (AGN)feedback before falling into a cluster core. Moreover, we found that theobserved specific star formation rates of massive quiescent galaxies in z&gt;3dense environments are one to two orders of magnitude lower than that of theBCGs in the TNG300 simulation. This discrepancy potentially poses a challengeto the models of massive cluster galaxy formation. Future studies comparing alarge sample with dedicated cluster simulations are required to solve theproblem.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: A&amp;A Letters in press, open access at  https://doi.org/10.1051/0004-6361/202348540
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2311.04867v3" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2311.04867v3 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Shuowen Jin</author><pubDate>Wed, 08 Nov 2023 18:12:18 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2311.04867v3</guid></item><item><title>A Steep Decline in the Galaxy Space Density Beyond Redshift 9 in the  CANUCS UV Luminosity Function</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2311.12234v2</link><description>Chris J. Willott, Guillaume Desprez, Yoshihisa Asada, Ghassan T. E. Sarrouh, Roberto Abraham, Maruša Bradač, Gabe Brammer, Vince Estrada-Carpenter, Kartheik G. Iyer, Nicholas S. Martis, Jasleen Matharu, Lamiya Mowla, Adam Muzzin, Gaël Noirot, Marcin Sawicki, Victoria Strait, Gregor Rihtaršič, Sunna Withers
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present a new sample of 158 galaxies at redshift $z&gt;7.5$ selected fromdeep \jwst\ NIRCam imaging of five widely-separated sightlines in the CANUCSsurvey. Two-thirds of the pointings and 80\% of the galaxies are covered by 12to 14 NIRCam filters, including seven to nine medium bands, providing accuratephotometric redshifts and robustness against low redshift interlopers. A sampleof 28 galaxies at $z&gt;7.5$ with spectroscopic redshifts shows a low systematicoffset and scatter in the difference between photometric and spectroscopicredshifts. We derive the galaxy UV luminosity function at redshifts 8 to 12,finding a slightly higher normalization than previously seen with \hst\ atredshifts 8 to 10. We observe a steeper decline in the galaxy space densityfrom $z=8$ to $12$ than found by most \jwst\ Cycle 1 studies. In particular, wefind only eight galaxies at $z&gt;10$ and none at $z&gt;12.5$, with no $z&gt;10$galaxies brighter than F277W AB=28 or $M_{\rm UV}=-20$ in our unmasked,delensed survey area of 53.4 square arcminutes. We attribute the lack of bright$z&gt;10$ galaxies in CANUCS compared to GLASS and CEERS to intrinsic variance inthe galaxy density along different sightlines. The evolution in the CANUCSluminosity function between $z=8$ and $12$ is comparable to that predicted bysimulations that assume a standard star formation efficiency, without invokingany special adjustments.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 30 pages, 12 figures, ApJ, in press
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2311.12234v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2311.12234v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Chris J. Willott</author><pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2023 23:24:46 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2311.12234v2</guid></item><item><title>JWST UNCOVER: The Overabundance of Ultraviolet-luminous Galaxies at  $z&gt;9$</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2312.05030v2</link><description>Iryna Chemerynska, Hakim Atek, Lukas J. Furtak, Adi Zitrin, Jenny E. Greene, Pratika Dayal, Andrea Weibel, Seiji Fujimoto, Vasily Kokorev, Andy D. Goulding, Christina C. Williams, Themiya Nanayakkara, Rachel Bezanson, Gabriel Brammer, Sam E. Cutler, Ivo Labbe, Joel Leja, Richard Pan, Sedona H. Price, Pieter van Dokkum, Bingjie Wang, John R. Weaver, Katherine E. Whitaker
    &lt;p&gt;
    Over the past year, JWST has uncovered galaxies at record-breaking distancesup to $z \sim 13$. The JWST UNCOVER (ultra-deep NIRSpec and NIRcam observationsbefore the epoch of reionization) program has obtained ultra-deepmultiwavelength NIRCam imaging of the massive galaxy cluster Abell 2744 over$\sim 45$ arcmin$^{2}$ down to $\sim 29.5$ AB mag. Here, we present a robustultraviolet (UV) luminosity function derived through lensing clusters at$9&lt;z&lt;12$. Using comprehensive end-to-end simulations, we account for alllensing effects and systematic uncertainties in deriving both the amplificationfactors and the effective survey volume. Our results confirm the intriguingexcess of UV-bright galaxies ($M_{UV} &lt; -20$ AB mag) previously reported at$z&gt;9$ in recent JWST studies. In particular, a double power-law (DPL) describesbetter the bright-end of the luminosity function compared to the classicalSchechter form. The number density of these bright galaxies is 10-100 timeslarger than theoretical predictions and previous findings based on Hubble SpaceTelescope (HST) observations. Additionally, we measure a star formation ratedensity of $\rho_{\rm SFR} = 10^{-2.64}$ M$_{\odot}$~yr$^{-1}$~Mpc$^{-3}$ atthese redshifts, which is 4 to 10 times higher than galaxy formation modelsthat assume a constant star formation efficiency. Future wide-area surveys andaccurate modeling of lensing-assisted observations will reliably constrain boththe bright and the dim end of the UV luminosity function at $z&gt;9$, which willprovide key benchmarks for galaxy formation models.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Published in MNRAS
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2312.05030v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2312.05030v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Iryna Chemerynska</author><pubDate>Fri, 08 Dec 2023 13:18:47 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2312.05030v2</guid></item><item><title>Modelling and Subtracting Diffuse Cluster Light in JWST Images: A  Relation between the Spatial Distribution of Globular Clusters, Dwarf  Galaxies, and Intracluster Light in the Lensing Cluster SMACS 0723</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2401.01945v1</link><description>Nicholas S. Martis, Ghassan T. E. Sarrouh, Chris J. Willott, Roberto Abraham, Yoshihisa Asada, Maruša Bradač, Gabe Brammer, Anishya Harshan, Adam Muzzin, Gaël Noirot, Marcin Sawicki, Gregor Rihtaršič
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present a methodology for modeling and removing light from clustergalaxies and intracluster light (ICL) from $James\ Webb\ Space\ Telescope$($JWST$) images of gravitational lensing clusters. We apply our method toWebb's First Deep Field the SMACS 0723 Early Release Observations and use theICL subtracted images to select a sample of globular clusters (GCs) and dwarfgalaxies within the cluster. We compare the spatial distributions of these twosamples with our models of the galaxy and ICL light, finding significantsimilarity. Specifically we find that GCs trace the diffuse ICL, while dwarfgalaxies are centrally concentrated near the cluster center We quantify therelationship between the surface density of compact sources and total clusterlight, demonstrating a significant, tight correlation. We repeat ourmethodology and compare distributions of GCs with dark matter surface densityand find a comparable result. Our findings suggest a common origin for GCs anddiffuse ICL, with stripping from massive galaxies as they merge with thecluster being a plausible scenario.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 16 pages, 13 figures. Submitted to ApJ. Comments welcome
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2401.01945v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2401.01945v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Nicholas S. Martis</author><pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 19:05:24 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2401.01945v1</guid></item><item><title>Bound star clusters observed in a lensed galaxy 460 Myr after the Big  Bang</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2401.03224v2</link><description>Angela Adamo, Larry D. Bradley, Eros Vanzella, Adélaïde Claeyssens, Brian Welch, Jose M Diego, Guillaume Mahler, Masamune Oguri, Keren Sharon, Abdurro'uf, Tiger Yu-Yang Hsiao, Xinfeng Xu, Matteo Messa, Augusto E. Lassen, Erik Zackrisson, Gabriel Brammer, Dan Coe, Vasily Kokorev, Massimo Ricotti, Adi Zitrin, Seiji Fujimoto, Akio K. Inoue, Tom Resseguier, Jane R. Rigby, Yolanda Jiménez-Teja, Rogier A. Windhorst, Takuya Hashimoto, Yoichi Tamura
    &lt;p&gt;
    The Cosmic Gems arc is among the brightest and highly magnified galaxiesobserved at redshift $z\sim10.2$. However, it is an intrinsically UV faintgalaxy, in the range of those now thought to drive the reionization of theUniverse. Hitherto the smallest features resolved in a galaxy at a comparableredshift are between a few hundreds and a few tens of parsecs. Here we reportJWST observations of the Cosmic Gems. The light of the galaxy is resolved intofive star clusters located in a region smaller than 70 parsec. They exhibitminimal dust attenuation and low metallicity, ages younger than 50 Myr andintrinsic masses of $\sim10^6$ M$_{\odot}$. Their lensing-corrected sizes areapproximately 1 pc, resulting in stellar surface densities near$10^5$~M$_{\odot}$/pc$^2$, three orders of magnitude higher than typical youngstar clusters in the local universe. Despite the uncertainties inherent to thelensing model, they are consistent with being gravitationally bound stellarsystems, i.e., proto-globular clusters. We conclude that star cluster formationand feedback likely contributed to shape the properties of galaxies during theepoch of reionization. [Abridged]
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Accepted for publication
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2401.03224v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2401.03224v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Angela Adamo</author><pubDate>Sat, 06 Jan 2024 14:26:24 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2401.03224v2</guid></item><item><title>The Firefly Sparkle: The Earliest Stages of the Assembly of A Milky  Way-type Galaxy in a 600 Myr Old Universe</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2402.08696v1</link><description>Lamiya Mowla, Kartheik Iyer, Yoshihisa Asada, Guillaume Desprez, Vivian Yun Yan Tan, Nicholas Martis, Ghassan Sarrouh, Victoria Strait, Roberto Abraham, Maruša Bradač, Gabriel Brammer, Adam Muzzin, Camilla Pacifici, Swara Ravindranath, Marcin Sawicki, Chris Willott, Vince Estrada-Carpenter, Nusrath Jahan, Gaël Noirot, Jasleen Matharu, Gregor Rihtaršič, Johannes Zabl
    &lt;p&gt;
    The most distant galaxies detected by JWST are assembling in a Universe thatis less than 5\% of its present age. At these times, the progenitors ofgalaxies like the Milky Way are expected to be about 10,000 times less massivethan they are now, with masses quite comparable to that of massive globularclusters seen in the local Universe. Composed today primarily of old stars andcorrelating with the properties of their parent dark matter halos, the firstglobular clusters are thought to have formed during the earliest stages ofgalaxy assembly. In this article we explore the connection between starclusters and galaxy assembly by showing JWST observations of a strongly lensedgalaxy at zspec = 8.304, exhibiting a network of massive star clusters (the'Firefly Sparkle') cocooned in a diffuse arc. The Firefly Sparkle exhibits thehallmarks expected of a future Milky Way-type galaxy captured during itsearliest and most gas-rich stage of formation. The mass distribution of thegalaxy seems to be concentrated in ten distinct clusters, with individualcluster masses that straddle the boundary between low-mass galaxies andhigh-mass globular clusters. The cluster ages suggest that they aregravitationally bound with star formation histories showing a recent starburstpossibly triggered by the interaction with a companion galaxy at the sameredshift at a projected distance of $\sim$2 kpc away from the Firefly Sparkle.The central star cluster shows nebular-dominated spectra consistent with hightemperatures and a top-heavy initial mass function, the product of formation ina very metal poor environment. Combined with abundance matching that suggeststhat this is likely to be a progenitor of galaxies like our own, the FireflySparkle provides an unprecedented case study of a Milky Way-like galaxy in theearliest stages of its assembly in only a 600 million year old Universe.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: submitted, comments are welcome! 36 pages, 9 figures
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2402.08696v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2402.08696v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Lamiya Mowla</author><pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 21:58:57 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2402.08696v1</guid></item><item><title>The cold interstellar medium of a normal sub-$L^\star$ galaxy at the end  of reionization</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2402.17845v1</link><description>F. Valentino, S. Fujimoto, C. Giménez-Arteaga, G. Brammer, K. Kohno, F. Sun, V. Kokorev, F. E. Bauer, C. Di Cesare, D. Espada, M. Lee, M. Dessauges-Zavadsky, Y. Ao, A. M. Koekemoer, M. Ouchi, J. F. Wu, E. Egami, J. -B. Jolly, C. del P. Lagos, G. E. Magdis, D. Schaerer, K. Shimasaku, H. Umehata, W. -H. Wang
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present the results of a ~60-hr observational campaign with ALMA targetinga spectroscopically confirmed and lensed sub-$L^\star$ galaxy at z=6.07,identified during the ALMA Lensing Cluster Survey (ALCS). We sample the dustcontinuum emission from rest frame 90 to 370 $\mu$m at six differentfrequencies and set constraining upper limits on the molecular gas lineemission and content via CO(7-6) and [CI](2-1) for two lensed images with$\mu\gtrsim20$. Complementing these sub-mm observations with deep optical andnear-IR photometry and spectroscopy with JWST, we find this galaxy to formstars at a rate of SFR~7 Msun/yr, ~50-70% of which is obscured by dust. This isconsistent with what is expected for a $M_\star$~7.5$\times10^{8}$ Msun objectby extrapolating the $M_\star$-obscured SFR fraction relation at z&lt;2.5 and withobservations at 5&lt;z&lt;7. The dust temperature of ~50K is similar to that of moremassive galaxies at similar redshifts, although with large uncertainties andwith possible negative gradients. We measure a dust mass of $M_{\rmdust}$~1.5$\times10^6$ Msun and, by combining [CI], [CII], and a dynamicalestimate, a gas mass of ~2$\times10^9$ Msun. Their ratio is in good agreementwith the predictions from models in the literature. The $M_{\rmdust}$/$M_\star$ fraction of ~0.002 and the young stellar age are consistentwith dust production via supernovae. Also, models predict a number density ofgalaxies with $M_{\rm dust}\sim10^{6}$ Msun at z=6 in agreement with ourestimate from the parent ALCS survey. The combination of lensing andmultiwavelength observations allow us to probe luminosity regimes up to twoorders of magnitude lower than what has been explored so far for field galaxiesat similar redshifts. Our results serve as a benchmark for future observationsof faint sub-$L^\star$ galaxy population that might have driven thereionization of the Universe. [Abridged]
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Accepted for publication in A&amp;A; 13 pages+appendix; supplementary  figures: https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10703293. See also the companion  papers on arXiv: Fujimoto+2024 and Gim\'{e}nez-Arteaga+2024
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2402.17845v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2402.17845v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>F. Valentino</author><pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2024 19:17:55 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2402.17845v1</guid></item><item><title>Outshining in the Spatially Resolved Analysis of a Strongly-Lensed  Galaxy at z=6.072 with JWST NIRCam</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2402.17875v1</link><description>C. Giménez-Arteaga, S. Fujimoto, F. Valentino, G. B. Brammer, C. A. Mason, F. Rizzo, V. Rusakov, L. Colina, G. Prieto-Lyon, P. A. Oesch, D. Espada, K. E. Heintz, K. K. Knudsen, M. Dessauges-Zavadsky, N. Laporte, M. Lee, G. E. Magdis, Y. Ono, Y. Ao, M. Ouchi, K. Kohno, A. M. Koekemoer
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present JWST/NIRCam observations of a strongly-lensed, multiply-imagedgalaxy at $z=6.072$, with magnification factors &gt;~20 across the galaxy. Weperform a spatially-resolved analysis of the physical properties at scales of~200 pc, inferred from SED modelling of 5 NIRCam imaging bands on apixel-by-pixel basis. We find young stars surrounded by extended older stellarpopulations. By comparing H$\alpha$+[NII] and [OIII]+H$\beta$ maps inferredfrom the image analysis with our additional NIRSpec IFU data, we find that thespatial distribution and strength of the line maps are in agreement with theIFU measurements. We explore different parametric SFH forms with Bagpipes onthe spatially-integrated photometry, finding that a double power-law starformation history retrieves the closest value to the spatially-resolved stellarmass estimate, and other SFH forms suffer from the dominant outshining emissionfrom the youngest stars, thus underestimating the stellar mass - up to ~0.5dex-. On the other hand, the DPL cannot match the IFU measured emission lines.Additionally, the ionizing photon production efficiency may be overestimated ina spatially-integrated approach by ~0.15 dex, when compared to aspatially-resolved analysis. The agreement with the IFU measurements pointstowards the pixel-by-pixel approach as a way to mitigate the general degeneracybetween the flux excess from emission lines and underlying continuum,especially when lacking photometric medium-band coverage and/or IFUobservations. This study stresses the importance of studying galaxies as thecomplex systems that they are, resolving their stellar populations whenpossible, or using more flexible SFH parameterisations. This can aid ourunderstanding of the early stages of galaxy evolution by addressing thechallenge of inferring robust stellar masses and ionizing photon productionefficiencies of high redshift galaxies.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Submitted to A&amp;A; 13 pages. See also the companion papers on arXiv  today: Fujimoto+2024 and Valentino+2024
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2402.17875v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2402.17875v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>C. Giménez-Arteaga</author><pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2024 20:28:02 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2402.17875v1</guid></item><item><title>RUBIES: JWST/NIRSpec Confirmation of an Infrared-luminous, Broad-line  Little Red Dot with an Ionized Outflow</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2403.02304v1</link><description>Bingjie Wang, Anna de Graaff, Rebecca L. Davies, Jenny E. Greene, Joel Leja, Andy D. Goulding, Christina C. Williams, Gabriel B. Brammer, Katherine A. Suess, Andrea Weibel, Rachel Bezanson, Leindert A. Boogaard, Nikko J. Cleri, Michaela Hirschmann, Harley Katz, Ivo Labbe, Michael V. Maseda, Jorryt Matthee, Ian McConachie, Rohan P. Naidu, Pascal A. Oesch, Hans-Walter Rix, David J. Setton, Katherine E. Whitaker
    &lt;p&gt;
    The JWST discovery of ``little red dots'' (LRDs) is reshaping our picture ofthe early Universe, yet the physical mechanisms driving their compact size andUV-optical colors remain elusive. Here we report an unusually bright LRD($z=3.1$) observed as part of the RUBIES program. This LRD exhibits broademission lines (FWHM $\sim4000$km/s), a blue UV continuum, a clear Balmer breakand a red continuum sampled out to rest 4 $\mu$m with MIRI. We develop a newjoint galaxy and AGN model within the Prospector Bayesian inference frameworkand perform spectrophotometric modeling using NIRCam, MIRI, and NIRSpec/Prismobservations. Our fiducial model reveals a $M_*\sim 10^9M_\odot$ galaxyalongside a dust-reddened AGN driving the optical emission. Explaining therest-frame optical color as a reddened AGN requires $A_{\rm v}\gtrsim4$,suggesting that a great majority of the accretion disk energy is re-radiated asdust emission. Yet despite clear AGN signatures, we find a surprising lack ofhot torus emission, which implies that either the dust emission in this objectmust be cold, or the red continuum must instead be driven by a massive, evolvedstellar population of the host galaxy -- seemingly inconsistent with the highEW broad lines (H$\alpha$ EW $\sim800$\AA). The widths and luminosities ofPa$\beta$, Pa$\delta$, Pa$\gamma$, and H$\alpha$ imply a modest black hole massof $M_{\rm BH}\sim10^8M_\odot$. Additionally, we identify a narrow blue-shiftedHeI absorption in G395M spectra, signaling an ionized outflow with kineticenergy up to $\sim1$\% the luminosity of the AGN. The low redshift ofRUBIES-BLAGN-1 combined with the depth and richness of the JWST imaging andspectroscopic observations provide a unique opportunity to build a physicalmodel for these so-far mysterious LRDs, which may prove to be a crucial phasein the early formation of massive galaxies and their supermassive black holes.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 20 pages, 8 figures, 4 tables
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2403.02304v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2403.02304v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Bingjie Wang</author><pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2024 18:35:55 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2403.02304v1</guid></item><item><title>CANUCS: An Updated Mass and Magnification Model of Abell 370 with JWST</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07062v1</link><description>Rachel Gledhill, Victoria Strait, Guillaume Desprez, Gregor Rihtaršič, Maruša Bradač, Gabriel Brammer, Chris J. Willott, Nicholas Martis, Marcin Sawicki, Gaël Noirot, Ghassan T. E. Sarrouh, Adam Muzzin
    &lt;p&gt;
    We report an updated mass and magnification model of galaxy cluster Abell 370using new NIRCam and NIRISS data from the CAnadian NIRISS Unbiased ClusterSurvey (CANUCS). Using Lenstool and a combination of archival HST and MUSE datawith new JWST data as constraints, we derive an improved gravitational lensingmodel and extract magnifications of background galaxies with uncertainties.Using our best fit model, we perform a search for new multiply imaged systemsvia predicted positions. We report no new multiply imaged systems withidentifiable redshifts, likely due to already very deep HST and Spitzer data,but confirm a $z\sim8$ multiply imaged system by measuring its redshift withNIRISS and NIRSpec spectra. We find that the overall shape of the criticalcurve for a source at $z = 9.0$ is similar to previous models of Abell 370,with small changes. We investigate the $z\sim8$ galaxy with two imagesobservable with an apparent magnitude in the F125W band of $26.0\pm0.2$ and$25.6\pm0.1$. After correcting for the magnifications of the images,7.2$^{+0.2}_{-1.2}$ and 8.7$^{+0.4}_{-0.4}$, we use SED fitting to find anintrinsic stellar mass of log($M^*/M_{\odot})$ = 7.35$^{+0.04}_{-0.05}$,intrinsic SFR of 3.5$^{+2.2}_{-1.4}$ M$_{\odot}$/yr, and $M_{UV}$ of-21.3$^{+0.2}_{-0.2}$, which is close to the knee of the luminosity function atthat redshift. Our model, and corresponding magnification, shear, andconvergence maps are available on request and will be made publicly availableon MAST in a CANUCS data release (DOI: 10.17909/ph4n-6n76).
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 15 pages
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2403.07062v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2403.07062v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Rachel Gledhill</author><pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2024 18:00:12 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07062v1</guid></item><item><title>Galaxy Build-up in the first 1.5 Gyr of Cosmic History: Insights from  the Stellar Mass Function at $z\sim4-9$ from JWST NIRCam Observations</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08872v2</link><description>Andrea Weibel, Pascal A. Oesch, Laia Barrufet, Rashmi Gottumukkala, Richard S. Ellis, Paola Santini, John R. Weaver, Natalie Allen, Rychard Bouwens, Rebecca A. A. Bowler, Gabe Brammer, Adam C. Carnall, Fergus Cullen, Pratika Dayal, Callum T. Donnan, James S. Dunlop, Mauro Giavalisco, Norman A. Grogin, Garth D. Illingworth, Anton M. Koekemoer, Ivo Labbe, Danilo Marchesini, Derek J. McLeod, Ross J. McLure, Rohan P. Naidu, Marko Shuntov, Mauro Stefanon, Sune Toft, Mengyuan Xiao
    &lt;p&gt;
    Combining the public JWST/NIRCam imaging programs CEERS, PRIMER and JADES,spanning a total area of $\sim500\,{\rm arcmin}^2$, we obtain a sample of$&gt;$30,000 galaxies at $z_{\rm phot}\sim4-9$ that allows us to perform acomplete, rest-optical selected census of the galaxy population at $z&gt;3$.Comparing the stellar mass $M_*$ and the UV-slope $\beta$ distributions betweenJWST- and HST-selected samples, we generally find very good agreement and nosignificant biases. Nevertheless, JWST enables us to probe a new population ofUV-red galaxies that was missing from previous HST-based Lyman Break Galaxy(LBG) samples. We measure galaxy stellar mass functions (SMFs) at $z\sim4-9$down to limiting masses of $10^{7.5}-10^{8.5}\,{\rm M_\odot}$, finding steeplow mass slopes over the entire redshift range, reaching values of$\alpha\approx-2$ at $z\gtrsim6$. At the high-mass end, UV-red galaxiesdominate at least out to $z\sim6$. The implied redshift evolution of the SMFsuggests a rapid build-up of massive dust-obscured or quiescent galaxies from$z\sim6$ to $z\sim4$ as well as an enhanced efficiency of star formationtowards earlier times ($z\gtrsim6$). Finally, we show that the galaxy massdensity grows by a factor $\sim20\times$ from $z\sim9$ to $z\sim4$. Our resultsemphasize the importance of rest-frame optically-selected samples in inferringaccurate distributions of physical properties and studying the mass build-up ofgalaxies in the first 1.5 Gyr of cosmic history.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 31 pages, 17 figures, published in MNRAS
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2403.08872v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2403.08872v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Andrea Weibel</author><pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2024 18:00:11 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08872v2</guid></item><item><title>The JWST-PRIMAL Legacy Survey. A JWST/NIRSpec reference sample for the  physical properties and Lyman-$α$ absorption and emission of $\sim 500$  galaxies at $z=5.5-13.4$</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02211v1</link><description>K. E. Heintz, G. B. Brammer, D. Watson, P. A. Oesch, L. C. Keating, M. J. Hayes, Abdurro'uf, K. Z. Arellano-Córdova, A. C. Carnall, C. R. Christiansen, F. Cullen, R. Davé, P. Dayal, A. Ferrara, K. Finlator, J. P. U. Fynbo, S. R. Flury, V. Gelli, S. Gillman, R. Gottumukkala, K. Gould, T. R. Greve, S. E. Hardin, T. Y. -Y Hsiao, A. Hutter, P. Jakobsson, M. Killi, N. Khosravaninezhad, P. Laursen, M. M. Lee, G. E. Magdis, J. Matthee, R. P. Naidu, D. Narayanan, C. Pollock, M. Prescott, V. Rusakov, M. Shuntov, A. Sneppen, R. Smit, N. R. Tanvir, C. Terp, S. Toft, F. Valentino, A. P. Vijayan, J. R. Weaver, J. H. Wise, J. Witstok
    &lt;p&gt;
    One of the surprising early findings with JWST has been the discovery of astrong "roll-over" or a softening of the absorption edge of Ly$\alpha$ in alarge number of galaxies at ($z\gtrsim 6$), in addition to systematic offsetsfrom photometric redshift estimates and fundamental galaxy scaling relations.This has been interpreted as damped Ly$\alpha$ absorption (DLA) wings from highcolumn densities of neutral atomic hydrogen (HI), signifying major gasaccretion events in the formation of these galaxies. To explore this newphenomenon systematically, we assemble the JWST/NIRSpec PRImordial gas MassAssembLy (PRIMAL) legacy survey of 494 galaxies at $z=5.5-13.4$. Wecharacterize this benchmark sample in full and spectroscopically derive thegalaxy redshifts, metallicities, star-formation rates, and ultraviolet slopes.We define a new diagnostic, the Ly$\alpha$ damping parameter $D_{\rm Ly\alpha}$to measure and quantify the Ly$\alpha$ emission strength, HI fraction in theIGM, or local HI column density for each source. The JWST-PRIMAL survey isbased on the spectroscopic DAWN JWST Archive (DJA-Spec). All the software,reduced spectra, and spectroscopically derived quantities and catalogs are madepublicly available in dedicated repositories. The fraction of strong galaxyDLAs are found to be in the range $65-95\%$ at $z&gt;5.5$. The fraction of strongLy$\alpha$ emitters (LAEs) is found to increase with decreasing redshift, inqualitative agreement with previous observational results, and arepredominantly associated with low-metallicity and UV faint galaxies. Bycontrast, strong DLAs are observed in galaxies with a variety of intrinsicphysical properties. Our results indicate that strong DLAs likely reflect aparticular early assembly phase of reionization-era galaxies, at which pointthey are largely dominated by pristine HI gas accretion. [abridged]
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 20 pages, 18 figures, 3 tables. Submitted to A&amp;A. Comments welcome!  All data and catalogs are available through the DAWN JWST Archive (DJA):  https://dawn-cph.github.io/dja/ and https://github.com/keheintz/jwst-primal
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.02211v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.02211v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>K. E. Heintz</author><pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2024 18:03:18 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02211v1</guid></item><item><title>Exploring the Mpc Environment of the Quasar ULAS J1342+0928 at z = 7.54</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02960v1</link><description>Sofía Rojas-Ruiz, Chiara Mazzucchelli, Steven L. Finkelstein, Eduardo Bañados, Emanuele P. Farina, Bram P. Venemans, Roberto Decarli, Christopher J. Willott, Feige Wang, Fabian Walter, Enrico Congiu, Gabriel B. Brammer, Peter Zeidler
    &lt;p&gt;
    Theoretical models predict that z~6 quasars are hosted in the most massivehalos of the underlying dark matter distribution and thus would be immersed inprotoclusters of galaxies. However, observations report inconclusive results.We investigate the 1.1 pMpc2 environment of the z = 7.54 luminous quasar ULASJ1342+0928. We search for Lyman-break galaxy candidates (LBG) using deepimaging from the Hubble Space Telescope (HST) in the ACS/F814W,WFC3/F105W/F125W bands, and Spitzer/IRAC at 3.6 $\mu$m and 4.5 $\mu$m. Wereport a zphot = $7.69^{+0.33}_{-0.23}$ LBG with magF125W = 26.41 at 223projected-pkpc from the quasar. We find no HST counterpart to one [CII]-emitterpreviously found with ALMA at 27 projected-pkpc and $z[CII]=7.5341\pm0.0009$(Venemans et al. 2020). We estimate the completeness of our LBG candidatesusing results from CANDELS/GOODS deep blank field searches sharing a similarfilter setup. We find that &gt;50% of the z~7.5 LBGs with magF125W &gt;25.5 aremissed due to the absence of a filter redward of the Lyman-break in F105W,hindering the UV color accuracy of the candidates. We conduct a QSO-LBGclustering analysis revealing a low LBG excess of $0.46^{+1.52}_{-0.08}$ inthis quasar field, consistent with an average or low-density field.Consequently, this result does not present strong evidence of an LBGoverdensity around ULAS J1342+0928. Furthermore, we identify two LBG candidateswith a zphot matching a confirmed z=6.84 absorber along the line-of-sight tothe quasar. All these galaxy candidates are excellent targets for follow-upobservations with JWST and/or ALMA to confirm their redshift and physicalproperties.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Accepted to ApJ, 16 pages, 8 figures
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.02960v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.02960v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Sofía Rojas-Ruiz</author><pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2024 18:00:02 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02960v1</guid></item><item><title>Efficient formation of a massive quiescent galaxy at redshift 4.9</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05683v3</link><description>Anna de Graaff, David J. Setton, Gabriel Brammer, Sam Cutler, Katherine A. Suess, Ivo Labbe, Joel Leja, Andrea Weibel, Michael V. Maseda, Katherine E. Whitaker, Rachel Bezanson, Leindert A. Boogaard, Nikko J. Cleri, Gabriella De Lucia, Marijn Franx, Jenny E. Greene, Michaela Hirschmann, Jorryt Matthee, Ian McConachie, Rohan P. Naidu, Pascal A. Oesch, Sedona H. Price, Hans-Walter Rix, Francesco Valentino, Bingjie Wang, Christina C. Williams
    &lt;p&gt;
    Within the established framework of structure formation, galaxies start assystems of low stellar mass and gradually grow into far more massive galaxies.The existence of massive galaxies in the first billion years of the Universe,suggested by recent observations, appears to challenge this model, as suchgalaxies would require highly efficient conversion of baryons into stars. Aneven greater challenge in this epoch is the existence of massive galaxies thathave already ceased forming stars. However, robust detections of early massivequiescent galaxies have been challenging due to the coarse wavelength samplingof photometric surveys. Here we report the spectroscopic confirmation with theJames Webb Space Telescope of the quiescent galaxy RUBIES-EGS-QG-1 at redshift$z=4.90$, 1.2 billion years after the Big Bang. Deep stellar absorptionfeatures in the spectrum reveal that the galaxy's stellar mass of$10^{11}\,M_\odot$, corroborated by the mass implied by its gas kinematics,formed in a short $200\,$Myr burst of star formation, after which starformation activity dropped rapidly and persistently. According to currentgalaxy formation models, systems with such rapid stellar mass growth and earlyquenching are too rare to plausibly occur in the small area probedspectroscopically with JWST. Instead, the discovery of RUBIES-EGS-QG-1 impliesthat early massive quiescent galaxies can be quenched earlier or exhaust gasavailable for star formation more efficiently than currently assumed.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 9 figures
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.05683v3" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.05683v3 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Anna de Graaff</author><pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2024 17:05:38 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05683v3</guid></item><item><title>Uncovering the physical origin of the prominent Lyman-$α$ emission  and absorption in GS9422 at $z = 5.943$</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06543v1</link><description>Chamilla Terp, Kasper E. Heintz, Darach Watson, Gabriel Brammer, Adam Carnall, Joris Witstok, Renske Smit, Simone Vejlgaard
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present a comprehensive spectro-photometric analysis of the galaxy GS9422from the JADES GTO survey located at $z=5.943$, anomalously showing asimultaneous strong Ly$\alpha$ emission feature and damped Ly$\alpha$absorption (DLA), based on JWST NIRSpec and NIRCam observations. The best-fitmodelling of the spectral energy distribution (SED) reveals a young, low-mass(${\rm log}(M_\star/M_{\odot}) = 7.8 \pm 0.01$) galaxy, with a mass-weightedmean age of the stellar population of $(10.9^{+0.07}_{-0.12})\,$Myr. Theidentified strong nebular emission lines suggest a highly ionized ($O_{32} =59$), low-metallicity ($12+\log({\rm O/H}) = 7.78\pm 0.10$) star-forming galaxywith a star-formation rate SFR = ($8.2 \pm 2.8$) $\rm M_{\odot}\;yr^{-1}$ overa compact surface area $A_e = 1.85$ kpc$^{2}$, typical for galaxies at thisepoch. We carefully model the rest-frame UV NIRSpec Prism spectrum around theLy$\alpha$ edge, finding that the Ly$\alpha$ emission-line redshift isconsistent with the longer-wavelength recombination lines and an escapefraction of $f_{\rm esc,Ly\alpha} = 30\%$ but that the broad DLA feature is notable to converge on the same redshift. Instead, our modelling suggests $z_{\rmabs}= 5.40 \pm 0.10$, the exact redshift of a newly identified proto-cluster innearby projection to the target galaxy. We argue that most of the HI gasproducing the strong Ly$\alpha$ damping wing indeed has to be unassociated withthe galaxy itself, and thus may indicate that we are probing the cold, densecircumcluster medium of this massive galaxy overdensity. These results providean alternative solution to the recent claims of continuum nebular emission oran obscured active galactic nucleus dominating the rest-frame UV parts of thespectrum and provide further indications that strong DLAs might preferentiallybe associated with galaxy overdensities. [Abridged]
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 11 pages, 6 figures + appendix, 2 tables. Submitted to A&amp;A
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.06543v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.06543v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Chamilla Terp</author><pubDate>Tue, 09 Apr 2024 18:00:27 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06543v1</guid></item><item><title>Unveiling the Cosmic Gems Arc at $z\sim10.2$ with JWST</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10770v1</link><description>Larry D. Bradley, Angela Adamo, Eros Vanzella, Keren Sharon, Gabriel Brammer, Dan Coe, Jose M. Diego, Vasily Kokorev, Guillaume Mahler, Masamune Oguri, Abdurro'uf, Rachana Bhatawdekar, Lise Christensen, Seiji Fujimoto, Takuya Hashimoto, Tiger Y. -Y Hsiao, Akio K. Inoue, Yolanda Jiménez-Teja, Matteo Messa, Colin Norman, Massimo Ricotti, Yoichi Tamura, Rogier A. Windhorst, Xinfeng Xu, Adi Zitrin
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present recent JWST NIRCam imaging observations of SPT0615-JD (also knownas the Cosmic Gems Arc), lensed by the galaxy cluster SPT-CL J0615-5746. The5-arcsec-long arc is the most highly magnified $z&gt;10$ galaxy known, straddlingthe lensing critical curve and revealing five star clusters with radii $\sim 1$pc or less. We measure the full arc to have F200W 24.5 AB mag, consisting oftwo mirror images, each 25.3 AB mag with a magnification $\mu \sim 60$(delensed 29.7 AB mag, $M_{UV} = -17.8$). The galaxy has an extremely strongLyman break F115W$-$F200W $&gt;3.2$ mag ($2\sigma$ lower limit), is undetected inall bluer filters ($&lt; 2\sigma$), and has a very blue continuum slope redward ofthe break ($\beta = -2.7 \pm 0.1$), resulting in a photometric redshift$z_{phot} = 10.2 \pm 0.2$ (95% confidence) with no significant likelihood below$z &lt; 9.8$. Based on SED fitting to the total photometry, we estimate anintrinsic stellar mass of $M_{*} \sim 2.4 - 5.6 \times 10^{7} M_{\odot}$, youngmass-weighted age of $\sim 21 - 79$ Myr, low dust content ($A_V &lt; 0.15$), and alow metallicity of $\lesssim 1\%~Z_{\odot}$. We identify a fainter thirdcounterimage candidate within 2.2 arcsec of the predicted position, lensed toAB mag 28.4 and magnified by $\mu \sim 2$, suggesting the fold arc may onlyshow $\sim60$% of the galaxy. SPT0615-JD is a unique laboratory to study starclusters observed within a galaxy just 460 Myr after the Big Bang.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 22 pages, 8 figures, 4 tables, submitted to ApJ
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.10770v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.10770v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Larry D. Bradley</author><pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2024 17:54:49 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10770v1</guid></item><item><title>FRESCO: The Paschen-$α$ Star Forming Sequence at Cosmic Noon</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10816v2</link><description>Chloe Neufeld, Pieter van Dokkum, Yasmeen Asali, Alba Covelo-Paz, Joel Leja, Jamie Lin, Jorryt Matthee, Pascal A. Oesch, Naveen A. Reddy, Irene Shivaei, Katherine E. Whitaker, Stijn Wuyts, Gabriel Brammer, Danilo Marchesini, Michael V. Maseda, Rohan P. Naidu, Erica J. Nelson, Anna Velichko, Andrea Weibel, Mengyuan Xiao
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present results from the JWST First Reionization Epoch SpectroscopicallyComplete Observations survey (FRESCO) on the star forming sequence of galaxiesat $1.0&lt;z&lt;1.7$, around the peak of the cosmic star formation history. Starformation rates (SFRs) are measured from the redshifted, nearlydust-insensitive Paschen-$\alpha$ emission line, and stellar mass measurementsinclude the F444W (4.4 $\mu$m; rest-frame H) band. We find SFRs of galaxieswith $M*&gt;9.5 M_\odot$ that are lower than found in many earlier studies by upto 0.6 dex, but in good agreement with recent results obtained with theProspector fitting framework. The differencelog(SFR(Pa$\alpha$)-SFR(Prospector)) is -0.09 $\pm$ 0.04 dex at $10^{10-11}M_\odot$. We also measure the empirical relation between Paschen-$\alpha$luminosity and rest-frame H band magnitude and find that the scatter is only0.04 dex lower than that of the SFR-M* relation and is much lower than thesystematic differences among relations in the literature due to various methodsof converting observed measurements to physical properties. We additionallyidentify examples of sources -- that, with standard cutoffs via the UVJdiagram, would be deemed quiescent -- with significant, typically extended,Paschen-$\alpha$ emission. Our results may be indicative of the potentialunification of methods used to derive the star forming sequence with carefulselection of star forming galaxies and independent star formation rate andstellar mass indicators.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 17 pages, 9 figures. Accepted for publication in ApJ
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.10816v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.10816v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Chloe Neufeld</author><pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2024 18:00:01 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10816v2</guid></item><item><title>The JWST-SUSPENSE Ultradeep Spectroscopic Program: Survey Overview and  Star-Formation Histories of Quiescent Galaxies at 1 &lt; z &lt; 3</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12432v2</link><description>Martje Slob, Mariska Kriek, Aliza G. Beverage, Katherine A. Suess, Guillermo Barro, Rachel Bezanson, Gabriel Brammer, Chloe M. Cheng, Charlie Conroy, Anna de Graaff, Natascha M. Förster Schreiber, Marijn Franx, Brian Lorenz, Pavel E. Mancera Piña, Danilo Marchesini, Adam Muzzin, Andrew B. Newman, Sedona H. Price, Alice E. Shapley, Mauro Stefanon, Pieter van Dokkum, Daniel R. Weisz
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present an overview and first results from the Spectroscopic UltradeepSurvey Probing Extragalactic Near-infrared Stellar Emission (SUSPENSE),executed with NIRSpec on JWST. The primary goal of the SUSPENSE program is tocharacterize the stellar, chemical, and kinematic properties of massivequiescent galaxies at cosmic noon. In a single deep NIRSpec/MSA configuration,we target 20 distant quiescent galaxy candidates ($z=1-3$, $H_{AB}\le23$), aswell as 53 star-forming galaxies at $z=1-4$. With 16~hr of integration and theG140M-F100LP dispersion-filter combination, we observe numerous Balmer andmetal absorption lines for all quiescent candidates. We derive stellar masses(log$M_*/M_{\odot}\sim10.2-11.5$) and detailed star-formation histories (SFHs)and show that all 20 candidate quiescent galaxies indeed have quenched stellarpopulations. These galaxies show a variety of mass-weighted ages($0.8-3.3$~Gyr) and star formation timescales ($\sim0.5-4$~Gyr), and four outof 20 galaxies were already quiescent by $z=3$. On average, the $z&gt;1.75$$[z&lt;1.75]$ galaxies formed 50\% of their stellar mass before $z=4$ $[z=3]$.Furthermore, the typical SFHs of galaxies in these two redshift bins($z_{\text{mean}}=2.2~[1.3]$) indicate that galaxies at higher redshift formedearlier and over shorter star-formation timescales compared to lower redshifts.Although this evolution is naturally explained by the growth of the quiescentgalaxy population over cosmic time, number density calculations imply thatmergers and/or late-time star formation also contribute to the evolution. Infuture work, we will further unravel the early formation, quenching, andlate-time evolution of these galaxies by extending this work with studies ontheir chemical abundances, resolved stellar populations and kinematics.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Accepted in ApJ; 25 pages, 14 figures, 2 tables (excluding  appendices)
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.12432v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.12432v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Martje Slob</author><pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2024 18:00:02 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12432v2</guid></item><item><title>Medium Bands, Mega Science: a JWST/NIRCam Medium-Band Imaging Survey of  Abell 2744</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.13132v1</link><description>Katherine A. Suess, John R. Weaver, Sedona H. Price, Richard Pan, Bingjie Wang, Rachel Bezanson, Gabriel Brammer, Sam E. Cutler, Ivo Labbe, Joel Leja, Christina C. Williams, Katherine E. Whitaker, Pratika Dayal, Anna de Graaff, Robert Feldmann, Marijn Franx, Yoshinobu Fudamoto, Seiji Fujimoto, Lukas J. Furtak, Andy D. Goulding, Jenny E. Greene, Gourav Khullar, Vasily Kokorev, Mariska Kriek, Brian Lorenz, Danilo Marchesini, Michael V. Maseda, Jorryt Matthee, Tim B. Miller, Ikki Mitsuhashi, Lamiya A. Mowla, Adam Muzzin, Rohan P. Naidu, Themiya Nanayakkara, Erica J. Nelson, Pascal A. Oesch, David J. Setton, Heath Shipley, Renske Smit, Justin S. Spilker, Pieter van Dokkum, Adi Zitrin
    &lt;p&gt;
    In this paper, we describe the "Medium Bands, Mega Science" JWST Cycle 2survey (JWST-GO-4111) and demonstrate the power of these data to reveal boththe spatially-integrated and spatially-resolved properties of galaxies from thelocal universe to the era of cosmic dawn. Executed in November 2023,MegaScience obtained ~30 arcmin^2 of deep multiband NIRCam imaging centered onthe z~0.3 Abell 2744 cluster, including eleven medium-band filters and the twoshortest-wavelength broad-band filters, F070W and F090W. Together, MegaScienceand the UNCOVER Cycle 1 treasury program provide a complete set of deep (~28-30mag) images in all NIRCam medium- and broad-band filters. This unique datasetallows us to precisely constrain photometric redshifts, map stellar populationsand dust attenuation for large samples of distant galaxies, and examine theconnection between galaxy structures and formation histories. MegaScience alsoincludes ~17 arcmin^2 of NIRISS parallel imaging in two broad-band and fourmedium-band filters from 0.9-4.8um, expanding the footprint where robustspectral energy distribution (SED) fitting is possible. We provide example SEDsand multi-band cutouts at a variety of redshifts, and use a catalog of JWSTspectroscopic redshifts to show that MegaScience improves both the scatter andcatastrophic outlier rate of photometric redshifts by factors of 2-3.Additionally, we demonstrate the spatially-resolved science enabled byMegaScience by presenting maps of the [OIII] line emission and continuumemission in three spectroscopically-confirmed z&gt;6 galaxies. We show that lineemission in reionization-era galaxies can be clumpy, extended, and spatiallyoffset from continuum emission, implying that galaxy assembly histories arecomplex even at these early epochs. We publicly release fully reduced mosaicsand photometric catalogs for both the NIRCam primary and NIRISS parallelfields.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 21 pages, 10 figures. Fully reduced imaging, photometric catalogs,  and photometric redshift fits publicly available at  https://jwst-uncover.github.io/megascience/
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.13132v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.13132v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Katherine A. Suess</author><pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2024 18:40:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.13132v1</guid></item><item><title>A First Look at Spatially Resolved Star Formation at $4.8&lt;z&lt;6.5$ with  JWST FRESCO NIRCam Slitless Spectroscopy</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17629v2</link><description>Jasleen Matharu, Erica J. Nelson, Gabriel Brammer, Pascal A. Oesch, Natalie Allen, Irene Shivaei, Rohan P. Naidu, John Chisholm, Alba Covelo-Paz, Yoshinobu Fudamoto, Emma Giovinazzo, Thomas Herard-Demanche, Josephine Kerutt, Ivan Kramarenko, Danilo Marchesini, Romain A. Meyer, Gonzalo Prieto-Lyon, Naveen Reddy, Marko Shuntov, Andrea Weibel, Stijn Wuyts, Mengyuan Xiao
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present the first results on the spatial distribution of star formation in454 star-forming galaxies at $4.8&lt;z&lt;6.5$ using H-Alpha emission-line maps andF444W imaging tracing the stellar continuum from JWST FRESCO NIRCam SlitlessSpectroscopy. Star-forming galaxies with stellar masses$6.8\leq$log($M_{*}/\mathrm{M}_{\odot}$)$&lt;11.1$ have positive H-Alphaequivalent width profiles, providing direct evidence for the inside-out growthof galaxies just after the epoch of reionisation. GALFIT is used to calculatehalf-light radii, $R_{\mathrm{eff}}$ and central surface densities within 1kiloparsec, $\Sigma_{1\mathrm{kpc}}$. At a fixed stellar mass oflog$(M_{*}/\mathrm{M}_{\odot})=9.5$, $\Sigma_{1\mathrm{kpc, H}\alpha}$ is$1.04\pm0.05$ times higher than $\Sigma_{1\mathrm{kpc, C}}$, $R_{\mathrm{eff,H}\alpha}$ is $1.18\pm0.03$ times larger than $R_{\mathrm{eff, C}}$ and both$R_{\mathrm{eff}}$ measurements are less than 1 kiloparsec. These measurementssuggest the rapid build-up of compact bulges just after the epoch ofreionisation. By comparing to work done at lower redshifts with HST WFC3Slitless Spectroscopy as part of the 3D-HST ($z=1$) and CLEAR ($z=0.5$)surveys, we find that $R_{\mathrm{eff}}(z)$ evolves at the same pace forH$\alpha$ and the continuum, but $\Sigma_{1\mathrm{kpc}}(z)$ evolves faster forH$\alpha$. As a function of the Hubble parameter, $\frac{R_{\mathrm{eff,H}\alpha}}{R_{\mathrm{eff, C}}}=1.1h(z)$ and$\frac{\Sigma_{1\mathrm{kpc,H}\alpha}}{\Sigma_{1\mathrm{kpc,C}}}=h(z)^{1.3}$.These functions suggest that the inside-out growth of the disk dominates theinside-out growth of the bulge towards lower redshifts. This is supported bythe redshift evolution in EW(H$\alpha$) profiles, where there is rapid increasein EW(H$\alpha$) with radius within the half-light radius at $z=5.3$ but onlysignificantly increasing EW(H$\alpha$) with radius in the outer disk at$z=0.5$.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 12 pages, 6 figures, accepted for publication by A&amp;A
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.17629v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.17629v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Jasleen Matharu</author><pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2024 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17629v2</guid></item><item><title>RUBIES: Evolved Stellar Populations with Extended Formation Histories at  $z \sim 7-8$ in Candidate Massive Galaxies Identified with JWST/NIRSpec</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01473v2</link><description>Bingjie Wang, Joel Leja, Anna de Graaff, Gabriel B. Brammer, Andrea Weibel, Pieter van Dokkum, Josephine F. W. Baggen, Katherine A. Suess, Jenny E. Greene, Rachel Bezanson, Nikko J. Cleri, Michaela Hirschmann, Ivo Labbe, Jorryt Matthee, Ian McConachie, Rohan P. Naidu, Erica Nelson, Pascal A. Oesch, David J. Setton, Christina C. Williams
    &lt;p&gt;
    The identification of red, apparently massive galaxies at $z&gt;7$ in early JWSTphotometry suggests a strongly accelerated timeline compared to standard modelsof galaxy growth. A major uncertainty in the interpretation is whether the redcolors are caused by evolved stellar populations, dust, or other effects suchas emission lines or AGN. Here we show that three of the massive galaxycandidates at $z=6.7-8.4$ have prominent Balmer breaks in JWST/NIRSpecspectroscopy from the RUBIES program. The Balmer breaks demonstrateunambiguously that stellar emission dominates at $\lambda_{\rm rest} =0.4\,\mu$m, and require formation histories extending hundreds of Myr into thepast in galaxies only 600--800 Myr after the Big Bang. Two of the threegalaxies also show broad Balmer lines, with H$\beta$ FWHM $&gt;2500~{\rmkm\,s^{-1}}$, suggesting that dust-reddened AGN contribute to, or evendominate, the SEDs of these galaxies at $\lambda_{\rm rest}\gtrsim 0.6\,\mu$m.All three galaxies have relatively narrow [O III] lines, seemingly ruling out ahigh-mass interpretation if the lines arise in dynamically-relaxed, inclineddisks. Yet, the inferred masses also remain highly uncertain. We model thehigh-quality spectra using Prospector to decompose the continuum into stellarand AGN components, and explore limiting cases in stellar/AGN contribution.This produces a wide range of possible stellar masses, spanning $M_\star \sim10^9 - 10^{11}\,{\rm M_{\odot}}$. Nevertheless, all fits suggest a very earlyand rapid formation, most of which follow with a truncation in star formation.Potential origins and evolutionary tracks for these objects are discussed, fromthe cores of massive galaxies to low-mass galaxies with over-massive blackholes. Intriguingly, we find all of these explanations to be incomplete; deeperand redder data are needed to understand the physics of these systems.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Accepted for publication in ApJL; 20 pages, 10 figures, 1 table
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2405.01473v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2405.01473v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Bingjie Wang</author><pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 17:06:30 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01473v2</guid></item><item><title>JWST FRESCO: a comprehensive census of H$β$+[OIII] emitters at  6.8&lt;z&lt;9.0 in the GOODS fields</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05111v3</link><description>R. A. Meyer, P. A. Oesch, E. Giovinazzo, A. Weibel, G. Brammer, J. Matthee, R. P. Naidu, R. J. Bouwens, J. Chisholm, A. Covelo-Paz, Y. Fudamoto, M. Maseda, E. Nelson, I. Shivaei, M. Xiao, T. Herard-Demanche, G. D. Illingworth, J. Kerutt, I. Kramarenko, I. Labbe, E. Leonova, D. Magee, J. Matharu, G. Prieto Lyon, N. Reddy, D. Schaerer, A. Shapley, M. Stefanon, M. A. Wozniak, S. Wuyts
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present the census of H$\beta$+[OIII] 4960,5008 \AA emitters at 6.8&lt;z&lt;9.0from the JWST FRESCO survey over 124 arcmin$^2$ in the GOODS-North andGOODS-South fields. Our unbiased spectroscopic search results in 137spectroscopically-confirmed galaxies at $6.8&lt;z&lt;9.0$ with observed [OIII] fluxes$f_{[OIII]}\gtrsim 1\times 10^{-18}\ \rm{ergs}\ \rm{s}^{-1} \ \rm{cm}^{-2}$.The rest-frame optical line ratios of the median stacked spectrum (median$M_{\rm{UV}}=-19.65^{+0.59}_{-1.05}$) indicate negligible dust attenuation, lowmetallicity ($12+\log(\rm{O/H})= 7.2-7.7$) and a high ionisation parameter$\log_{10}U \simeq -2.5$. We find a factor $\times 1.3$ difference in thenumber density of $6.8&lt;z&lt;9.0$ galaxies between GOODS-South and GOODS-North,which is caused by a single overdensity at $7.0&lt;z&lt;7.2$ in GOODS-North. Thebright end of the UV luminosity function of spectroscopically-confirmed [OIII]emitters is in good agreement with HST dropout-selected samples. Discrepanciesbetween the observed [OIII] LF, [OIII]/UV ratio and [OIII] equivalent widths,and that predicted by theoretical models, suggest burstier star-formationhistories and/or more heterogeneous metallicity and ionising conditions in$z&gt;7$ galaxies. We report a rapid decline of the [OIII] luminosity density at$z\gtrsim 6-7$ which cannot be explained by the evolution of the cosmicstar-formation rate density. Finally we find that FRESCO detects in only 2hgalaxies likely accounting for $\sim 10-20\%$ of the ionising budget at $z=7-8$(assuming an escape fraction of 10%), raising the prospect of directlydetecting a significant fraction of the sources of reionisation with JWST.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 20 pages + appendices. Accepted in MNRAS. Public catalogue release at  https://github.com/rameyer/fresco. V3: matching accepted version
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2405.05111v3" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2405.05111v3 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>R. A. Meyer</author><pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2024 15:07:57 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05111v3</guid></item><item><title>The First Billion Years, According to JWST</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2405.21054v1</link><description>Angela Adamo, Hakim Atek, Micaela B. Bagley, Eduardo Bañados, Kirk S. S. Barrow, Danielle A. Berg, Rachel Bezanson, Maruša Bradač, Gabriel Brammer, Adam C. Carnall, John Chisholm, Dan Coe, Pratika Dayal, Daniel J. Eisenstein, Jan J. Eldridge, Andrea Ferrara, Seiji Fujimoto, Anna de Graaff, Melanie Habouzit, Taylor A. Hutchison, Jeyhan S. Kartaltepe, Susan A. Kassin, Mariska Kriek, Ivo Labbé, Roberto Maiolino, Rui Marques-Chaves, Michael V. Maseda, Charlotte Mason, Jorryt Matthee, Kristen B. W. McQuinn, Georges Meynet, Rohan P. Naidu, Pascal A. Oesch, Laura Pentericci, Pablo G. Pérez-González, Jane R. Rigby, Guido Roberts-Borsani, Daniel Schaerer, Alice E. Shapley, Daniel P. Stark, Massimo Stiavelli, Allison L. Strom, Eros Vanzella, Feige Wang, Stephen M. Wilkins, Christina C. Williams, Chris J. Willott, Dominika Wylezalek, Antonella Nota
    &lt;p&gt;
    With stunning clarity, JWST has revealed the Universe's first billion years.The scientific community is analyzing a wealth of JWST imaging andspectroscopic data from that era, and is in the process of rewriting theastronomy textbooks. Here, 1.5 years into the JWST science mission, we providea snapshot of the great progress made towards understanding the initialchapters of our cosmic history. We highlight discoveries and breakthroughs,topics and issues that are not yet understood, and questions that will beaddressed in the coming years, as JWST continues its revolutionary observationsof the Early Universe. While this compendium is written by a small number ofauthors, invited to ISSI Bern in March 2024 as part of the 2024 ISSIBreakthrough Workshop, we acknowledge the work of a large community that isadvancing our collective understanding of the evolution of the Early Universe.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: review article written by the attendees of the 2024 ISSI breakthrough  workshop "The first billion year of the Universe", submitted. Comments  welcome
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2405.21054v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2405.21054v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Angela Adamo</author><pubDate>Fri, 31 May 2024 17:46:10 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2405.21054v1</guid></item><item><title>The Structure of Massive Star-Forming Galaxies from JWST and ALMA:  Dusty, High Redshift Disk Galaxies</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2406.03544v2</link><description>Steven Gillman, Ian Smail, Bitten Gullberg, A. M. Swinbank, Aswin P. Vijayan, Minju Lee, Gabe Brammer, U. Dudzevičiūtė, Thomas R. Greve, Omar Almaini, Malte Brinch, Scott C. Chapman, Chian-Chou Chen, Soh Ikarashi, Yuichi Matsuda, Wei-Hao Wang, Fabian Walter, Paul P. van der Werf
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present an analysis of the JWST NIRCam and MIRI morphological propertiesof 80 massive ($\log_{10}(M_\ast[M_{\odot}])$=11.2$\pm$0.1) dusty star-forminggalaxies at $z$$=$2.7$^{+1.2}_{-0.7}$, identified as sub-millimetre galaxies(SMGs) by ALMA, that have been observed as part of the JWST PRIMER project. Tocompare the structure of these massive, active galaxies to more typical lessactively star-forming galaxies, we define two comparison samples. The first of850 field galaxies matched in specific star-formation rate and redshift and thesecond of 80 field galaxies matched in stellar mass. We identify 20$\pm$5% ofthe SMGs as candidate late-stage major mergers, a further 40$\pm$10% aspotential minor mergers and 40$\pm$10% which have comparatively undisturbeddisk-like morphologies, with no obvious massive neighbours. These rates arecomparable to those for the field samples and indicate that the majority of thesub-millimetre-detected galaxies are not late-stage major mergers, but haveinteraction rates similar to the less-active population at $z$$\sim$2-3. Weestablish that SMGs have comparable near-infrared sizes to the less activepopulations, but exhibit lower S\'ersic indices, consistent with bulge-lessdisks and have more structured morphologies at 2$\mu$m relative to 4$\mu$m. Wefind evidence for dust reddening as the origin of the morphological differencesbetween the populations, identifying a strong correlation between theF200W$-$F444W pixel colour and the 870$\mu$m surface brightness. We concludethat SMGs and less active galaxies at the same epochs share a common disk-likestructure, but the weaker bulge components of the SMGs results in a lowerdynamical stability. Consequently, instabilities triggered either secularly orby minor external perturbations result in higher levels of activity (and dustcontent) in SMGs compared to typical star-forming galaxies. [Abridged]
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 23 pages, 13 figures. Accepted for publication in A&amp;A
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2406.03544v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2406.03544v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Steven Gillman</author><pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2024 18:00:04 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2406.03544v2</guid></item><item><title>The Star-Forming Main Sequence in JADES and CEERS at $z&gt;1.4$:  Investigating the Burstiness of Star Formation</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05178v1</link><description>Leonardo Clarke, Alice E. Shapley, Ryan L. Sanders, Michael W. Topping, Gabriel B. Brammer, Trinity Bento, Naveen A. Reddy, Emily Kehoe
    &lt;p&gt;
    We have used public JWST/NIRSpec and JWST/NIRCam observations from the CEERSand JADES surveys in order to analyze the star-forming main sequence (SFMS)over the redshift range $1.4 \leq z &lt; 7$. We calculate the star-formation rates(SFRs) of the galaxy sample using three approaches: Balmer line luminosity,spectral energy distribution (SED) fitting, and UV luminosity. We find a largerdegree of scatter about the SFMS using the Balmer-based SFRs compared to theUV-based SFRs. Because these SFR indicators are sensitive to star formation ondifferent time scales, the difference in scatter may be evidence of burstystar-formation histories in the early universe. We additionally compare theH$\alpha$-to-UV luminosity ratio (L(H$\alpha$)/$\nu$L$_{\nu,1600}$) forindividual galaxies in the sample and find that 29\%$-$52\% of the ratiosacross the sample are poorly described by predictions from a smoothstar-formation history. Measuring the burstiness of star formation in the earlyuniverse has multiple significant implications, such as deriving accuratephysical parameters from SED fitting, explaining the evolution of the UVluminosity function, and providing constraints for sub-grid models of feedbackin simulations of galaxy formation and evolution.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 21 pages, 7 figures, submitted to ApJ
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2406.05178v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2406.05178v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Leonardo Clarke</author><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2024 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05178v1</guid></item><item><title>CANUCS: Constraining the MACS J0416.1-2403 Strong Lensing Model with  JWST NIRISS, NIRSpec and NIRCam</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10332v1</link><description>Gregor Rihtaršič, Maruša Bradač, Guillaume Desprez, Anishya Harshan, Gaël Noirot, Vicente Estrada-Carpenter, Nicholas S. Martis, Roberto G. Abraham, Yoshihisa Asada, Gabriel Brammer, Kartheik G. Iyer, Jasleen Matharu, Lamiya Mowla, Adam Muzzin, Ghassan T. E. Sarrouh, Marcin Sawicki, Victoria Strait, Chris J. Willott, Rachel Gledhill, Vladan Markov, Roberta Tripodi
    &lt;p&gt;
    Strong gravitational lensing in galaxy clusters has become an essential toolin astrophysics, allowing us to directly probe the dark matter distribution andstudy magnified background sources. The precision and reliability of stronglensing models rely heavily on the number and quality of multiple images ofbackground sources with spectroscopic redshifts. We present an updated stronglensing model of the galaxy cluster MACS J0416.1-2403 with the largest sampleof multiple images with spectroscopic redshifts in a galaxy cluster field todate. Furthermore, we aim to demonstrate the effectiveness of JWST particularlyits NIRISS camera, for strong lensing studies. We use the JWST 's NIRCamimaging and NIRSpec and NIRISS spectroscopy from the CAnadian NIRISS UnbiasedCluster Survey (CANUCS). The cluster mass model is constrained using Lenstoolsoftware. Our new dataset, used for constraining the lens model, comprises 303secure multiple images from 111 background sources and includes systems withpreviously known MUSE redshift and systems for which we obtained spectroscopicredshift for the first time using NIRISS and NIRSpec spectroscopy. The totalnumber of secure spectroscopic systems is &gt;20% higher than in the previousstrong lensing studies of this cluster. The derived strong lensing model canreproduce multiple images with the root-mean-square distance of 0.53''. We alsoprovide a full catalogue with 415 multiple images, including less reliablecandidates. We furthermore demonstrate the effectiveness of JWST particularlyNIRISS, for strong lensing studies. As NIRISS F115W, F150W, and F200W grismspectroscopy captures at least two of the [OII] {\lambda}3727, [OIII]{\lambda}{\lambda}4959, 5007, and H{\alpha} lines at 1&lt;z&lt;3 (a redshift rangeparticularly relevant for strong lensing studies) without target pre-selection,it complements MUSE and NIRSpec observations extremely well.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Submitted to A&amp;A, 23 pages, 12 figures, 6 tables
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2406.10332v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2406.10332v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Gregor Rihtaršič</author><pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2024 18:00:01 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10332v1</guid></item><item><title>When, Where, and How Star Formation Happens in a Galaxy Pair at Cosmic  Noon Using CANUCS JWST/NIRISS Grism Spectroscopy</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2406.15551v1</link><description>Vicente Estrada-Carpenter, Marcin Sawicki, Gabe Brammer, Guillaume Desprez, Roberto Abraham, Yoshihisa Asada, Maruša Bradač, Kartheik G. Iyer, Nicholas S. Martis, Jasleen Matharu, Lamiya Mowla, Adam Muzzin, Gaël Noirot, Ghassan T. E. Sarrouh, Victoria Strait, Chris J. Willott
    &lt;p&gt;
    Spatially resolved studies are key to understanding when, where, and howstars form within galaxies. Using slitless grism spectra and broadband imagingfrom the CAnadian NIRISS Unbiased Cluster Survey (CANUCS) we study thespatially resolved properties of a strongly lensed ($\mu$ = 5.4$\pm$1.8) z =0.8718 galaxy pair consisting of a blue face-on galaxy (10.2 $\pm$ 0.2log($M/M_\odot$)) with multiple star-forming clumps and a dusty red edge-ongalaxy (9.9 $\pm$ 0.3 log($M/M_\odot$)). We produce accurate H$\alpha$ mapsfrom JWST/NIRISS grism data using a new methodology that accurately modelsspatially varying continuum and emission line strengths. With spatiallyresolved indicators, we probe star formation on timescales of $\sim$ 10 Myr(NIRISS H$\alpha$ emission line maps) and $\sim$ 100 Myr (UV imaging andbroadband SED fits). Taking the ratio of the H$\alpha$ to UV flux ($\eta$), wemeasure spatially resolved star formation burstiness. We find that in theface-on galaxy both H$\alpha$ and broadband star formation rates (SFRs) drop atlarge galactocentric radii by a factor of $\sim$ 4.7 and 3.8 respectively,while SFR over the last $\sim$ 100 Myrs has increased by a factor of 1.6.Additionally, of the 20 clumps identified in the galaxy pair we find that 7 areexperiencing bursty star formation, while 10 clumps are quenching and 3 are inequilibrium (either being in a state of steady star formation or post-burst).Our analysis reveals that the blue face-on galaxy disk is predominantly in aquenching or equilibrium phase. However, the most intense quenching within thegalaxy is seen in the quenching clumps. This pilot study demonstrates whatJWST/NIRISS data can reveal about spatially varying star formation in galaxiesat Cosmic Noon.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: MNRAS Accepted, 15 pages, 12 figures
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2406.15551v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2406.15551v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Vicente Estrada-Carpenter</author><pubDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2024 18:00:01 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2406.15551v1</guid></item><item><title>The Size-Mass relation at Rest-Frame $1.5μ$m from JWST/NIRCam in the  COSMOS-WEB and PRIMER-COSMOS fields</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17756v2</link><description>Marco Martorano, Arjen van der Wel, Maarten Baes, Eric F. Bell, Gabriel Brammer, Marijn Franx, Angelos Nersesian
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present the galaxy stellar mass - size relation in the rest-frame near-IR($1.5~\mu{\text{m}}$) and its evolution with redshift up to $z=2.5$. S\'ersicprofiles are measured for $\sim$ $26\,000$ galaxies with stellar masses$M_\star &gt; 10^9~{\text{M}}_\odot$ from JWST/NIRCam F277W and F444W imagingprovided by the COSMOS-WEB and PRIMER surveys, using coordinates, redshifts,colors and stellar mass estimates from the COSMOS2020 catalog. The newrest-frame near-IR effective radii are generally smaller than previouslymeasured rest-frame optical sizes, on average by 0.14~dex, with no significantdependence on redshift. For quiescent galaxies this size offset does not dependon stellar mass, but for star-forming galaxies the offset increases from-0.1~dex at $M_\star = 10^{9.5}~{\text{M}}_\odot$ to -0.25~dex at $M_\star &gt;10^{11}~{\text{M}}_\odot$. That is, we find that the near-IR stellar mass -size relation for star-forming galaxies is flatter in the rest-frame near-IRthan in the rest-frame optical at all redshifts $0.5&lt;z&lt;2.5$. The general paceof size evolution is the same in the near-IR as previously demonstrated in theoptical, with slower evolution ($R_{\text{e}} \propto (1+z)^{-0.7}$) for$L^*$~star-forming galaxies and faster evolution ($R_{\text{e}} \propto(1+z)^{-1.3}$) for $L^*$~quiescent galaxies. Massive($M_\star&gt;10^{11}~{\text{M}}_\odot$) star-forming galaxies evolve in sizealmost as fast as quiescent galaxies. Low-mass($M_\star&lt;10^{10}~{\text{M}}_\odot$)~quiescent galaxies evolve as slow asstar-forming galaxies. Our main conclusion is that the size evolution narrativeas it has emerged over the past two decades does not radically change whenaccessing with JWST the rest-frame near-IR, a better proxy of the underlyingstellar mass distribution.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Accepted for publication. V2: includes a new table (table 1) of the  data produced and available in machine-readable format on the journal version  of the article
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2406.17756v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2406.17756v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Marco Martorano</author><pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2024 17:41:53 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17756v2</guid></item><item><title>The AURORA Survey: A New Era of Emission-line Diagrams with JWST/NIRSpec</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00157v2</link><description>Alice E. Shapley, Ryan L. Sanders, Michael W. Topping, Naveen A. Reddy, Danielle A. Berg, Rychard J. Bouwens, Gabriel Brammer, Adam C. Carnall, Fergus Cullen, Romeel Davé, James S. Dunlop, Richard S. Ellis, N. M. Förster Schreiber, Steven R . Furlanetto, Karl Glazebrook, Garth D. Illingworth, Tucker Jones, Mariska Kriek, Derek J. McLeod, Ross J. McLure, Desika Narayanan, Pascal Oesch, Anthony J. Pahl, Max Pettini, Daniel Schaerer, Daniel P. Stark, Charles C. Steidel, Mengtao Tang, Leonardo Clarke, Callum T. Donnan, Emily Kehoe
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present results on the emission-line properties of z=1.4-7.5 star-forminggalaxies in the Assembly of Ultradeep Rest-optical Observations RevealingAstrophysics (AURORA) Cycle 1 JWST/NIRSpec program. Based on its depth,continuous wavelength coverage from 1--5 microns, and medium spectralresolution (R~1000), AURORA includes detections of a large suite of nebularemission lines spanning a broad range in rest wavelength. We investigate thelocations of AURORA galaxies in multiple different emission-line diagrams,including traditional "BPT" diagrams of [OIII]/Hbeta vs. [NII]/Halpha,[SII]/Halpha, and [OI]/Halpha, and the "ionization-metallicity" diagram of[OIII]/[OII] (O32) vs. ([OIII]+[OII])/Hbeta (R23). We also consider a bluerrest-frame "ionization-metallicity" diagram introduced recently to characterizez&gt;10 galaxies: [NeIII]/[OII] vs. ([NeIII]+[OII])/Hdelta; as well aslonger-wavelength diagnostic diagrams extending into the rest-frame near-IR:[OIII]/Hbeta vs. [SIII]/[SII] (S32); and HeI/Pagamma and [SIII]/Pagamma vs.[FeII]/Pabeta. With a significant boost in signal-to-noise and large,representative samples of individual galaxy detections, the AURORAemission-line diagrams presented here definitively confirm a physical picturein which chemically-young, alpha-enhanced, massive stars photoionize the ISM indistant galaxies with a harder ionizing spectrum at fixed nebular metallicitythan in their z~0 counterparts. We also uncover previously unseen evolutionprior to z~2 in the [OIII]/Hbeta vs. [NII]/Halpha diagram, which motivates deepNIRSpec observations at even higher redshift. Finally, we present the firststatistical sample of rest-frame near-IR emission-line diagnostics instar-forming galaxies at high redshift. In order to truly interpret rest-framenear-IR line ratios including [FeII], we must obtain better constraints on dustdepletion in the high-redshift ISM.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 17 pages, 8 figures, submitted to ApJ
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2407.00157v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2407.00157v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Alice E. Shapley</author><pubDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2024 18:00:05 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00157v2</guid></item><item><title>Carbon and Iron Deficiencies in Quiescent Galaxies at z=1-3 from  JWST-SUSPENSE: Implications for the Formation Histories of Massive Galaxies</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02556v1</link><description>Aliza G. Beverage, Martje Slob, Mariska Kriek, Charlie Conroy, Guillermo Barro, Rachel Bezanson, Gabriel Brammer, Chloe M. Cheng, Anna de Graaff, Natascha M. Förster Schreiber, Marijn Franx, Brian Lorenz, Pavel E. Mancera Piña, Danilo Marchesini, Adam Muzzin, Andrew B. Newman, Sedona H. Price, Alice E. Shapley, Mauro Stefanon, Katherine A. Suess, Pieter van Dokkum, David Weinberg, Daniel R. Weisz
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present the stellar metallicities and multi-element abundances (C, Mg, Si,Ca, Ti, Cr, and Fe) of 15 massive (log M/M$_\odot$=10.2-11.2) quiescentgalaxies at z=1-3, derived from ultradeep JWST-SUSPENSE spectra. Compared toquiescent galaxies at z~0, these galaxies exhibit a deficiency of 0.25 dex in[C/H], 0.16 dex in [Fe/H], and 0.07 dex in [Mg/H], implying rapid formation andquenching before significant enrichment from asymptotic giant branch stars andType Ia supernovae. Additionally, we find that galaxies that form at higherredshift have higher [Mg/Fe] and lower [Fe/H] and [Mg/H], irrespective of theirobserved redshift. The evolution in [Fe/H] and [C/H] is therefore primarilyexplained by lower redshift samples naturally including galaxies with longerstar-formation timescales. On the other hand, the lower [Mg/H] can be explainedby galaxies forming at earlier epochs expelling larger gas reservoirs duringtheir quenching phase. Consequently, the mass-metallicity relation, primarilyreflecting [Mg/H], is also lower at z=1-3 compared to the lower redshiftrelation, though the slopes are similar. Finally, we compare our results tostandard stellar population modeling approaches employing solar abundancepatterns and non-parametric star-formation histories (using Prospector). OurSSP-equivalent ages agree with the mass-weighted ages from Prospector, whilethe metallicities disagree significantly. Nonetheless, the metallicities betterreflect [Fe/H] than total [Z/H]. We also find that star-formation timescalesinferred from elemental abundances are significantly shorter than those fromProspector, and we discuss the resulting implications for the early formationof massive galaxies.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Submitted to ApJ; 18 pages, 6 figures, 1 table
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2407.02556v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2407.02556v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Aliza G. Beverage</author><pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2024 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02556v1</guid></item><item><title>A spectroscopic analysis of the ionizing photon production efficiency in  JADES and CEERS: implications for the ionizing photon budget</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03399v1</link><description>Anthony J. Pahl, Michael W. Topping, Alice Shapley, Ryan Sanders, Naveen A. Reddy, Leonardo Clarke, Emily Kehoe, Trinity Bento, Gabe Brammer
    &lt;p&gt;
    We have used a combined sample of JADES and CEERS objects in order toconstrain ionizing photon production efficiency ($\xi_{\rm ion}$) fromJWST/NIRSpec and JWST/NIRCam data. We examine 163 objects at 1.06 &lt; z &lt; 6.71with significant (3$\sigma$) spectroscopic detections of H$\alpha$ and H$\beta$in order to constrain intrinsic H$\alpha$ luminosities corrected from nebulardust attenuation via Balmer decrements. We constrain dust-corrected UVluminosities from best-fit spectral-energy distribution modeling. We find asample median log$_{10}$($\xi{\rm ion,0}$/erg Hz$^{-1}$) =$25.29^{+0.29}_{-0.37}$, assuming f$_{\rm esc}$=0 for the escape fraction ofLyman continuum emission. We find significant correlation between $\xi_{\rmion,0}$ and z, with 17 objects at z &gt; 4.64 having median log$_{10}$($\xi_{\rmion,0}$/erg Hz$^{-1}$) = $25.38^{+0.38}){-0.38}$, with those below havinglog$_{10}$($\xi_{\rm ion,0}$/erg Hz$^{-1}$) = $25.24^{+0.30}_{-0.33}$. We alsofind significant, positive correlations between $\xi_{\rm ion,0}$ and LUV;W{\lambda}([O iii]); [O iii]{\lambda}5007/[O ii]{\lambda}{\lambda}3726, 3729;and inverse correlations with metallicity. In contrast with some previousresults, we find no trends between $\xi_{\rm ion,0}$ and stellar mass, stellardust attenuation, or UV slope. Applying a multivariate fit to $\xi_{\rmion,0}$, z, and MUV to an empirically-motivated model of reionization, andfolding in f$_{\rm esc}$ estimates from direct observations of the Lymancontinuum at z ~ 3 from the Keck Lyman Continuum Spectroscopic survey, we findthat the number of ionizing photons entering the IGM causes reionization to endat z ~ 5 - 7.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 17 pages, 8 figures, submitted to ApJ
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2407.03399v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2407.03399v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Anthony J. Pahl</author><pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2024 18:00:01 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03399v1</guid></item><item><title>A massive, neutral gas reservoir permeating a galaxy proto-cluster after  the reionization era</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06287v1</link><description>Kasper E. Heintz, Jake S. Bennett, Pascal A. Oesch, Albert Sneppen, Douglas Rennehan, Joris Witstok, Renske Smit, Simone Vejlgaard, Chamilla Terp, Umran S. Koca, Gabriel B. Brammer, Kristian Finlator, Matthew J. Hayes, Debora Sijacki, Rohan P. Naidu, Jorryt Matthee, Francesco Valentino, Nial R. Tanvir, Páll Jakobsson, Peter Laursen, Darach J. Watson, Romeel Davé, Laura C. Keating, Alba Covelo-Paz
    &lt;p&gt;
    Galaxy clusters are the most massive, gravitationally-bound structures in theUniverse, emerging through hierarchical structure formation of large-scale darkmatter and baryon overdensities. Early galaxy ``proto-clusters'' are believedto be important physical drivers of the overall cosmic star-formation ratedensity and serve as ``hotspots'' for the reionization of the intergalacticmedium. Our understanding of the formation of these structures at the earliestcosmic epochs is, however, limited to sparse observations of their galaxymembers, or based on phenomenological models and cosmological simulations. Herewe report the detection of a massive neutral, atomic hydrogen (HI) gasreservoir permeating a galaxy proto-cluster at redshift $z=5.4$, observed onebillion years after the Big Bang. The presence of this cold gas is revealed bystrong damped Lyman-$\alpha$ absorption features observed in several backgroundgalaxy spectra taken with JWST/NIRSpec in close on-sky projection. Whileoverall the sightlines probe a large range in HI column densities, $N_{\rm HI}= 10^{21.7}-10^{23.5}$ cm$^{-2}$, they are similar across nearby sightlines,demonstrating that they probe the same dense, neutral gas. This observation ofa massive, large-scale overdensity of cold neutral gas challenges currentlarge-scale cosmological simulations and has strong implications for thereionization topology of the Universe.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Submitted
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2407.06287v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2407.06287v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Kasper E. Heintz</author><pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2024 18:03:01 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06287v1</guid></item><item><title>The Extreme Low-mass End of the Mass-Metallicity Relation at $z\sim7$</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17110v1</link><description>Iryna Chemerynska, Hakim Atek, Pratika Dayal, Lukas J. Furtak, Robert Feldmann, Jenny E. Greene, Michael V. Maseda, Themiya Nanayakkara, Pascal A. Oesch, Ivo Labbe, Rachel Bezanson, Gabriel Brammer, Sam E. Cutler, Joel Leja, Richard Pan, Sedona H. Price, Bingjie Wang, John R. Weaver, Katherine E. Whitaker
    &lt;p&gt;
    The mass-metallicity relation (MZR) provides crucial insights into the baryoncycle in galaxies and provides strong constraints on galaxy formation models.We use JWST NIRSpec observations from the UNCOVER program to measure thegas-phase metallicity in a sample of eight galaxies during the epoch ofreionization at $z=6-8$. Thanks to strong lensing of the galaxy cluster Abell2744, we are able to probe extremely low stellar masses between $10^{6}$ and$10^{8} M_{\odot}$. Using strong lines diagnostics and the most recent JWSTcalibrations, we derive extremely-low oxygen abundances ranging from12+log(O/H)=6.7 to 7.8. By combining this sample with more massive galaxies atsimilar redshifts, we derive a best-fit relation of 12+{\rmlog(O/H)}=$0.39_{-0.02}^{+0.02} \times$ log(\mstar) $+ 4.52_{-0.17}^{+0.17}$,which is steeper than determinations at $z \sim 3$. Our results show a clearredshift evolution in the overall normalization of the relation, galaxies athigher redshift having significantly lower metallicities at a given mass. Acomparison with theoretical models provides important constraints on whichphysical processes, such as metal mixing, star formation or feedback recipes,are important in reproducing the observations. Additionally, these galaxiesexhibit star formation rates that are higher by a factor of a few to tenscompared to extrapolated relations at similar redshifts or theoreticalpredictions of main-sequence galaxies, pointing to a recent burst of starformation. All these observations are indicative of highly stochastic starformation and ISM enrichment, expected in these low-mass systems, suggestingthat feedback mechanisms in high-$z$ dwarf galaxies might be different fromthose in place at higher masses.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Submitted to ApJL
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2407.17110v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2407.17110v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Iryna Chemerynska</author><pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 09:19:25 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17110v1</guid></item><item><title>The UNCOVER Survey: First Release of Ultradeep JWST/NIRSpec PRISM  spectra for ~700 galaxies from z~0.3-13 in Abell 2744</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03920v2</link><description>Sedona H. Price, Rachel Bezanson, Ivo Labbe, Lukas J. Furtak, Anna de Graaff, Jenny E. Greene, Vasily Kokorev, David J. Setton, Katherine A. Suess, Gabriel Brammer, Sam E. Cutler, Joel Leja, Richard Pan, Bingjie Wang, John R. Weaver, Katherine E. Whitaker, Hakim Atek, Adam J. Burgasser, Iryna Chemerynska, Pratika Dayal, Robert Feldmann, Natascha M. Förster Schreiber, Yoshinobu Fudamoto, Seiji Fujimoto, Karl Glazebrook, Andy D. Goulding, Gourav Khullar, Mariska Kriek, Danilo Marchesini, Michael V. Maseda, Tim B. Miller, Adam Muzzin, Themiya Nanayakkara, Erica Nelson, Pascal A. Oesch, Heath Shipley, Renske Smit, Edward N. Taylor, Pieter van Dokkum, Christina C. Williams, Adi Zitrin
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present the design and observations of low resolution JWST/NIRSpec PRISMspectroscopy from the Ultradeep NIRSpec and NIRCam ObserVations before theEpoch of Reionization (UNCOVER) Cycle 1 JWST Treasury program. Targets areselected using JWST/NIRCam photometry from UNCOVER and other programs, andcover a wide range of categories and redshifts to ensure the legacy value ofthe survey. These categories include the first galaxies at $z\gtrsim10$, faintgalaxies during the Epoch of Reionization ($z\sim6-8$), high redshift AGN($z\gtrsim6$), Population III star candidates, distant quiescent and dustygalaxies ($1\lesssim z \lesssim 6$), and filler galaxies samplingredshift--color--magnitude space from $z\sim 0.1-13$. Seven NIRSpec MSA masksacross the extended Abell 2744 cluster were observed, along with NIRCamparallel imaging in 8 filters (F090W, F115W, F150W, F200W, F277W, F356W, F410M,F444W, F480M) over a total area of ~26 arcmin$^2$, overlapping existing HSTcoverage from programs including the Hubble Frontier Fields and BUFFALO. Wesuccessfully observed 553 objects down to$m_{\mathrm{F444W}}\sim30\mathrm{AB}$, and by leveraging mask overlaps, wereach total on-target exposure times ranging from 2.4-16.7h. We demonstrate thesuccess rate and distribution of confirmed redshifts, and also highlight therich information revealed by these ultradeep spectra for a subset of ourtargets. An updated lens model of Abell 2744 is also presented, including 14additional spectroscopic redshifts and finding a total cluster mass of$M_{\mathrm{SL}}=(2.1\pm0.3)\times10^{15}\,\mathrm{M}_{\odot}$. We publiclyrelease reduced 1D and 2D spectra for all objects observed in Summer 2023 alongwith a spectroscopic redshift catalog and the updated lens model of the cluster(https://jwst-uncover.github.io/DR4.html).
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 19 pages, 9 figures, 4 tables, submitted to ApJ, comments welcome!  Data available at: https://jwst-uncover.github.io/DR4.html (v2: figure format  correction)
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2408.03920v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2408.03920v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Sedona H. Price</author><pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2024 17:24:12 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03920v2</guid></item><item><title>The AURORA Survey: The Nebular Attenuation Curve of a Galaxy at z=4.41  from Ultraviolet to Near-Infrared Wavelengths</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2408.05273v1</link><description>Ryan L. Sanders, Alice E. Shapley, Michael W. Topping, Naveen A. Reddy, Danielle A. Berg, Rychard J. Bouwens, Gabriel Brammer, Adam C. Carnall, Fergus Cullen, Romeel Davé, James S. Dunlop, Richard S. Ellis, N. M. Förster Schreiber, Steven R. Furlanetto, Karl Glazebrook, Garth D. Illingworth, Tucker Jones, Mariska Kriek, Derek J. McLeod, Ross J. McLure, Desika Narayanan, Pascal A. Oesch, Anthony J. Pahl, Max Pettini, Daniel Schaerer, Daniel P. Stark, Charles C. Steidel, Mengtao Tang, Leonardo Clarke, Callum T. Donnan, Emily Kehoe
    &lt;p&gt;
    We use JWST/NIRSpec observations from the Assembly of Ultradeep Rest-opticalObservations Revealing Astrophysics (AURORA) survey to constrain the shape ofthe nebular attenuation curve of a star-forming galaxy at z=4.41, GOODSN-17940.We utilize 11 unblended HI recombination lines to derive the attenuation curvespanning optical to near-infrared wavelengths (3751-9550 \r{A}). We thenleverage a high-S/N spectroscopic detection of the rest-frame ultravioletcontinuum in combination with rest-UV photometric measurements to constrain theshape of the curve at ultraviolet wavelengths. While this UV constraint ispredominantly based on stellar emission, the large measured equivalent widthsof H$\alpha$ and H$\beta$ indicate that GOODSN-17940 is dominated by anextremely young stellar population &lt;10 Myr in age such that the UV stellarcontinuum experiences the same attenuation as the nebular emission. Theresulting combined nebular attenuation curve spans 1400-9550 \r{A} and has ashape that deviates significantly from commonly assumed dust curves inhigh-redshift studies. Relative to the Milky Way, SMC, and Calzetti curves, thenew curve has a steeper slope at long wavelengths ($\lambda&gt;5000$ \r{A}) whiledisplaying a similar slope across blue-optical wavelengths ($\lambda=3750-5000$\r{A}). In the ultraviolet, the new curve is shallower than the SMC andCalzetti curves and displays no significant 2175 \r{A} bump. This workdemonstrates that the most commonly assumed dust curves are not appropriate forall high-redshift galaxies. These results highlight the ability to derivenebular attenuation curves for individual high-redshift sources with deepJWST/NIRSpec spectroscopy, thereby improving the accuracy of physicalproperties inferred from nebular emission lines.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 21 pages, 6 figures, 1 table, submitted to ApJ
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2408.05273v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2408.05273v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Ryan L. Sanders</author><pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2024 18:00:03 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2408.05273v1</guid></item><item><title>The Small Sizes and High Implied Densities of `Little Red Dots' with  Balmer Breaks Could Explain Their Broad Emission Lines Without an AGN</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2408.07745v1</link><description>Josephine F. W. Baggen, Pieter van Dokkum, Gabriel Brammer, Anna de Graaff, Marijn Franx, Jenny Greene, Ivo Labbé, Joel Leja, Michael V. Maseda, Erica J. Nelson, Hans-Walter Rix, Bingjie Wang, Andrea Weibel
    &lt;p&gt;
    Early JWST studies found an apparent population of massive, compact galaxiesat redshifts $z\gtrsim7$. Recently three of these galaxies were shown to haveprominent Balmer breaks, demonstrating that their light at $\lambda_{\rm rest}\sim 3500$ $\r{A}$ is dominated by a stellar population that is relatively old($\sim$200 Myr). All three also have broad H$\beta$ emission with $\sigma &gt;1000 \,\rm km s^{-1}$, a common feature of such `little red dots'. FromS\'ersic profile fits to the NIRCam images in F200W we find that the stellarlight of galaxies is extremely compact: the galaxies have half-light radii of$r_{\rm e}\sim$ 100 pc, in the regime of ultra compact dwarfs in the nearbyUniverse. Their masses are uncertain, as they depend on the contribution ofpossible light from an AGN to the flux at $\lambda_{\rm rest}&gt;5000$ $\r{A}$. Ifthe AGN contribution is low beyond the Balmer break region, the masses are $M_*\sim 10^{10}-10^{11}\mathrm{M}_{\odot}$, and the central densities are higherthan those of any other known galaxy population by an order of magnitude.Interestingly, the implied velocity dispersions of $\sim$1500 kms$^{-1}$ are invery good agreement with the measured H$\beta$ line widths. We suggest thatsome of the broad lines in `little red dots' are not due to AGNs but simplyreflect the kinematics of the galaxies, and speculate that the galaxies areobserved in a short-lived phase where the central densities are much higherthan at later times. We stress, however, that the canonical interpretation ofAGNs causing the broad H$\beta$ lines also remains viable.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2408.07745v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2408.07745v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Josephine F. W. Baggen</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2024 18:00:02 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2408.07745v1</guid></item><item><title>The GLASS-JWST Early Release Science Program. IV. Data release of 263  spectra from 245 unique sources</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16675v1</link><description>S. Mascia, G. Roberts-Borsani, T. Treu, L. Pentericci, W. Chen, A. Calabrò, E. Merlin, D. Paris, P. Santini, G. Brammer, A. Henry, P. L. Kelly, C. Mason, T. Morishita, T. Nanayakkara, N. Roy, X. Wang, H. Williams, K. Boyett, M. Bradač, M. Castellano, K. Glazebrook, T. Jones, L. Napolitano, B. Vulcani, P. J. Watson, L. Yang
    &lt;p&gt;
    We release fully reduced spectra obtained with NIRSpec onboard JWST as partof the GLASS-JWST Early Release Science Program and a follow-up Director'sDiscretionary Time program 2756. From these 263 spectra of 245 unique sources,acquired with low ($R =30-300$) and high dispersion ($R\sim2700$) gratings, wederive redshifts for 200 unique sources in the redshift range $z=0-10$. Wedescribe the sample selection and characterize its high completeness as afunction of redshift and apparent magnitude. Comparison with independentestimates based on different methods and instruments shows that the redshiftsare accurate, with 80\% differing less than 0.005. We stack the GLASS-JWSTspectra to produce the first high-resolution ($R \sim 2700$) JWST spectraltemplate extending in the rest frame wavelength from 2000~\AA\ to 20, 000~\AA.Catalogs, reduced spectra, and template are made publicly available to thecommunity.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Accepted for publication in A&amp;A
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2408.16675v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2408.16675v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>S. Mascia</author><pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 16:23:14 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16675v1</guid></item><item><title>RUBIES Reveals a Massive Quiescent Galaxy at z=7.3</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.03829v1</link><description>Andrea Weibel, Anna de Graaff, David J. Setton, Tim B. Miller, Pascal A. Oesch, Gabriel Brammer, Claudia D. P. Lagos, Katherine E. Whitaker, Christina C. Williams, Josephine F. W. Baggen, Rachel Bezanson, Leindert A. Boogaard, Nikko J. Cleri, Jenny E. Greene, Michaela Hirschmann, Raphael E. Hviding, Adarsh Kuruvanthodi, Ivo Labbé, Joel Leja, Michael V. Maseda, Jorryt Matthee, Ian McConachie, Rohan P. Naidu, Guido Roberts-Borsani, Daniel Schaerer, Katherine A. Suess, Francesco Valentino, Pieter van Dokkum, Bingjie Wang
    &lt;p&gt;
    We report the spectroscopic discovery of a massive quiescent galaxy at$z_{\rm spec}=7.29\pm0.01$, just $\sim700\,$Myr after the Big Bang.RUBIES-UDS-QG-z7 was selected from public JWST/NIRCam and MIRI imaging from thePRIMER survey and observed with JWST/NIRSpec as part of RUBIES. TheNIRSpec/PRISM spectrum reveals one of the strongest Balmer breaks observed thusfar at $z&gt;6$, no emission lines, but tentative Balmer and Ca absorptionfeatures, as well as a Lyman break. Simultaneous modeling of the NIRSpec/PRISMspectrum and NIRCam and MIRI photometry (spanning $0.9-18\,\mu$m) shows thatthe galaxy formed a stellar mass of log$(M_*/M_\odot)=10.23^{+0.04}_{-0.04}$ ina rapid $\sim 100-200\,$Myr burst of star formation at $z\sim8-9$, and ceasedforming stars by $z\sim8$ resulting in $\log \rm{sSFR/yr}^{-1}&lt;-10$. We measurea small physical size of $209_{-24}^{+33}\,{\rm pc}$, which implies a highstellar mass surface density within the effective radius of $\log(\Sigma_{*,\rme}/{\rm M_\odot\,kpc}^{-2})=10.85_{-0.12}^{+0.11}$ comparable to the densitiesmeasured in quiescent galaxies at $z\sim2-5$. The 3D stellar mass densityprofile of RUBIES-UDS-QG-z7 is remarkably similar to the central densities oflocal massive ellipticals, suggesting that at least some of their cores mayhave already been in place at $z&gt;7$. The discovery of RUBIES-UDS-QG-z7 hasstrong implications for galaxy formation models: the estimated number densityof quiescent galaxies at $z\sim7$ is $&gt;100\times$ larger than predicted fromany model to date, indicating that quiescent galaxies have formed earlier thanpreviously expected.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 21 pages, 7 figures, submitted to ApJ
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.03829v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.03829v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Andrea Weibel</author><pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 18:00:04 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.03829v1</guid></item><item><title>RUBIES: a complete census of the bright and red distant Universe with  JWST/NIRSpec</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05948v1</link><description>Anna de Graaff, Gabriel Brammer, Andrea Weibel, Zach Lewis, Michael V. Maseda, Pascal A. Oesch, Rachel Bezanson, Leindert A. Boogaard, Nikko J. Cleri, Olivia R. Cooper, Rashmi Gottumukkala, Jenny E. Greene, Michaela Hirschmann, Raphael E. Hviding, Harley Katz, Ivo Labbé, Joel Leja, Jorryt Matthee, Ian McConachie, Tim B. Miller, Rohan P. Naidu, Sedona H. Price, Hans-Walter Rix, David J. Setton, Katherine A. Suess, Bingjie Wang, Katherine E. Whitaker, Christina C. Williams
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present the Red Unknowns: Bright Infrared Extragalactic Survey (RUBIES),providing JWST/NIRSpec spectroscopy of red sources selected across ~150arcmin$^2$ from public JWST/NIRCam imaging in the UDS and EGS fields. RUBIESnovel observing strategy offers a well-quantified selection function: thesurvey is optimised to reach high (&gt;70%) completeness for bright and red(F150W-F444W&gt;2) sources that are very rare. To place these rare sources incontext, we simultaneously observe a reference sample of the 2&lt;z&lt;7 galaxypopulation, sampling sources at a rate that is inversely proportional to theirnumber density in the 3D space of F444W magnitude, F150W-F444W colour, andphotometric redshift. In total, RUBIES observes ~3000 targets across$1&lt;z_{phot}&lt;10$ with both the PRISM and G395M dispersers, and ~1500 targets at$z_{phot}&gt;3$ using only the G395M disperser. The RUBIES data reveal a highlydiverse population of red sources that span a broad redshift range($z_{spec}\sim1-9$), with photometric redshift scatter and outlier fractionthat are 3 times higher than for similarly bright sources that are less red.This diversity is not apparent from the photometric SEDs. Only spectroscopyreveals that the SEDs encompass a mixture of galaxies with dust-obscured starformation, extreme line emission, a lack of star formation indicating earlyquenching, and luminous active galactic nuclei. As a first demonstration of ourbroader selection function we compare the stellar masses and rest-frame U-Vcolours of the red sources and our reference sample: red sources are typicallymore massive ($M_*\sim10^{10-11.5} M_\odot$) across all redshifts. However, wefind that the most massive systems span a wide range in U-V colour. We describeour data reduction procedure and data quality, and publicly release the reducedRUBIES data and vetted spectroscopic redshifts of the first half of the surveythrough the DJA.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 21 pages, 16 figures; submitted to A&amp;A
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.05948v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.05948v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Anna de Graaff</author><pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2024 18:00:01 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05948v1</guid></item><item><title>UNCOVERing the High-Redshift AGN Population Among Extreme UV Line  Emitters</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12232v1</link><description>Helena Treiber, Jenny Greene, John R. Weaver, Tim B. Miller, Lukas J. Furtak, David J. Setton, Bingjie Wang, Anna de Graaff, Rachel Bezanson, Gabriel Brammer, Sam E. Cutler, Pratika Dayal, Robert Feldmann, Seiji Fujimoto, Andy D. Goulding, Vasily Kokorev, Ivo Labbe, Joel Leja, Danilo Marchesini, Themiya Nanayakkara, Erica Nelson, Richard Pan, Sedona H. Price, Jared Siegel, Katherine Suess, Katherine Whitaker
    &lt;p&gt;
    JWST has revealed diverse new populations of high-redshift ($z\sim4-11$) AGNand extreme star-forming galaxies that challenge current models. In this paper,we use rest-frame UV emission-line diagnostics to identify AGN candidates andother exceptional ionizing sources, complementing previous studiespredominantly focused on broad-line AGN. In this paper, we use rest-frame UVemission-line diagnostics to identify AGN candidates and other exceptionalionizing sources, complementing previous studies predominantly focused onbroad-line AGN. From a parent sample of 205 $\mathrm{z_{spec}}&gt;3$ UNCOVERgalaxies with NIRSpec/PRISM follow-up, we identify 12 C IV, He II, and C III]emitters. Leveraging the combined rest-optical and UV coverage of PRISM, welimit the emission-line model space using the sample's [O III]/H$\beta$distribution, significantly decreasing the overlap between AGN andstar-formation models in the UV diagnostics. We then find that the five He IIemitters are the strongest AGN candidates, with further support from two [Ne V]detections and one X-ray detection from Chandra. We cannot robustly quantifythe AGN fraction in this sample, but we note that close to 20% of$\mathrm{M_{*}&gt;2\times10^{9}\,M_{\odot}}$ parent sample galaxies are AGNcandidates. The lower-mass line emitters, which are consistent with both AGNand star-forming photoionization models, have more compact sizes and higherspecific star formation rates than the parent sample. Higher-resolution anddeeper data on these UV line emitters should provide much stronger constraintson the obscured AGN fraction at $z &gt; 3$.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Submitted to ApJ
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.12232v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.12232v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Helena Treiber</author><pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 18:00:02 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12232v1</guid></item><item><title>An Hα view of galaxy build-up in the first 2 Gyr: luminosity  functions at z~4-6.5 from NIRCam/grism spectroscopy</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17241v2</link><description>Alba Covelo-Paz, Emma Giovinazzo, Pascal A. Oesch, Romain A. Meyer, Andrea Weibel, Gabriel Brammer, Yoshinobu Fudamoto, Josephine Kerutt, Jamie Lin, Jasleen Matharu, Rohan P. Naidu, Anna Velichko, Victoria Bollo, Rychard Bouwens, John Chisholm, Garth D. Illingworth, Ivan Kramarenko, Daniel Magee, Michael Maseda, Jorryt Matthee, Erica Nelson, Naveen Reddy, Daniel Schaerer, Mauro Stefanon, Mengyuan Xiao
    &lt;p&gt;
    The H{\alpha} nebular emission line is an optimal tracer for recent starformation in galaxies. With the advent of JWST, this line has recently becomeobservable at z&gt;3 for the first time. We present a catalog of 1013 H{\alpha}emitters at 3.7&lt;z&lt;6.7 in the GOODS fields obtained from a blind search in JWSTNIRCam/grism data. We make use of the FRESCO survey's 124 arcmin^2 ofobservations in GOODS-North and GOODS-South with the F444W filter, probingH{\alpha} at 4.9&lt;z&lt;6.7; and the CONGRESS survey's 62 arcmin^2 in GOODS-Northwith F356W, probing H{\alpha} at 3.8&lt;z&lt;5.1. We find an overdensity with 97sources at z~4.4 in GOODS-N and confirm previously reported overdensities at$z\sim5.2$ in GOODS-N and at z~5.4 and z~5.9 in GOODS-S. We compute theobserved H{\alpha} luminosity functions (LFs) in three bins centered at z~4.45,5.30, and 6.15, which are the first such measurements at z&gt;3 obtained basedpurely on spectroscopic data, robustly tracing galaxy star formation rates(SFRs) beyond the peak of the cosmic star formation history. We compare ourresults with theoretical predictions from three different simulations and findgood agreement at z~4-6. The UV LFs of this spectroscopically-confirmed sampleare in good agreement with pre-JWST measurements obtained withphotometrically-selected objects. Finally, we derive SFR functions andintegrate these to compute the evolution of the cosmic star-formation ratedensities across z~4-6, finding values in good agreement with recent UVestimates from Lyman-break galaxies, which imply a continuous decrease in SFRdensity by a factor of 3x over z~4 to z~6. Our work shows the power of NIRCamgrism observations to efficiently provide new tests for early galaxy formationmodels based on emission line statistics.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 17 pages, 14 figures
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.17241v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.17241v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Alba Covelo-Paz</author><pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2024 18:00:13 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17241v2</guid></item><item><title>The AURORA Survey: An Extraordinarily Mature, Star-forming Galaxy at  $z\sim 7$</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00110v2</link><description>Alice E. Shapley, Ryan L. Sanders, Michael W. Topping, Naveen A. Reddy, Anthony J. Pahl, Pascal A. Oesch, Danielle A. Berg, Rychard J. Bouwens, Gabriel Brammer, Adam C. Carnall, Fergus Cullen, Romeel Davé, James S. Dunlop, Richard S. Ellis, N. M. Förster Schreiber, Steven R . Furlanetto, Karl Glazebrook, Garth D. Illingworth, Tucker Jones, Mariska Kriek, Derek J. McLeod, Ross J. McLure, Desika Narayanan, Max Pettini, Daniel Schaerer, Daniel P. Stark, Charles C. Steidel, Mengtao Tang, Leonardo Clarke, Callum T. Donnan, Emily Kehoe
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present the properties of a massive, large, dusty, metal-rich,star-forming galaxy at z_spec=6.73. GOODSN-100182 was observed withJWST/NIRSpec as part of the AURORA survey, and is also covered by publicmulti-wavelength HST and JWST imaging. While the large mass of GOODSN-100182(~10^10 M_sun) was indicated prior to JWST, NIRCam rest-optical imaging nowreveals the presence of an extended disk (r_eff~1.5 kpc). In addition, theNIRSpec R~1000 spectrum of GOODSN-100182 includes the detection of a largesuite of rest-optical nebular emission lines ranging in wavelength from[OII]3727 up to [NII]6583. The ratios of Balmer lines suggest significant dustattenuation (E(B-V)_gas=0.40+0.10/-0.09), consistent with the red rest-UV slopeinferred for GOODSN-100182 (beta=-0.50+/-0.09). The star-formation rate basedon dust-corrected H-alpha emission is log(SFR(H-alpha)/M_sun/yr)=2.02+0.13/-0.14, well above the z~7 star-forming main sequence interms of specific SFR. Strikingly, the ratio of [NII]6583/H-alpha emissionsuggests almost solar metallicity, as does the ratio([OIII]5007/H-beta)/([NII]6583/H-alpha) and the detection of the faint[FeII]4360 emission feature, whereas the [OIII]5007/[OII]3727 ratio suggestsroughly 50% solar metallicity. Overall, the excitation and ionizationproperties of GOODSN-100182 more closely resemble those of typical star-forminggalaxies at z~2-3 rather than z~7. Based on public spectroscopy of the GOODS-Nfield, we find that GOODSN-100182 resides within a significant galaxyoverdensity, and is accompanied by a spectroscopically-confirmed neighborgalaxy. GOODSN-100182 demonstrates the existence of mature, chemically-enrichedgalaxies within the first billion years of cosmic time, whose properties mustbe explained by galaxy formation models.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 16 pages, 13 figures, submitted to ApJ
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.00110v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.00110v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Alice E. Shapley</author><pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 18:00:06 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00110v2</guid></item><item><title>All the Little Things in Abell 2744: $&gt;$1000 Gravitationally Lensed  Dwarf Galaxies at $z=0-9$ from JWST NIRCam Grism Spectroscopy</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01874v1</link><description>Rohan P. Naidu, Jorryt Matthee, Ivan Kramarenko, Andrea Weibel, Gabriel Brammer, Pascal A. Oesch, Peter Lechner, Lukas J. Furtak, Claudia Di Cesare, Alberto Torralba, Gauri Kotiwale, Rachel Bezanson, Rychard J. Bouwens, Vedant Chandra, Adélaïde Claeyssens, A. Lola Danhaive, Anna Frebel, Anna de Graaff, Jenny E. Greene, Kasper E. Heintz, Alexander P. Ji, Daichi Kashino, Harley Katz, Ivo Labbe, Joel Leja, Yijia Li, Michael V. Maseda, Johan Richard, Irene Shivaei, Robert A. Simcoe, David Sobral, Katherine A. Suess, Sandro Tacchella, Christina C. Williams
    &lt;p&gt;
    Dwarf galaxies hold the key to crucial frontiers of astrophysics, however,their faintness renders spectroscopy challenging. Here we present the JWSTCycle 2 survey, All the Little Things (ALT, PID 3516), which is designed toseek late-forming Pop III stars and the drivers of reionization at $z\sim6-7$.ALT has acquired the deepest NIRCam grism spectroscopy yet (7-27 hr), at JWST'smost sensitive wavelengths (3-4 $\mu$m), covering the powerful lensing clusterAbell 2744. Over the same 30 arcmin$^2$, ALT's ultra-deep F070W+F090W imaging($\sim$30 mag) enables selection of very faint sources at $z&gt;6$. We demonstratethe success of ALT's novel ``butterfly" mosaic to solve spectral confusion andcontamination, and introduce the ``Allegro" method for emission lineidentification. By collecting spectra for every source in the field of view,ALT has measured precise ($R\sim1600$) redshifts for 1630 sources at$z=0.2-8.5$. This includes one of the largest samples of distant dwarfgalaxies: [1015, 475, 50] sources less massive than the SMC, Fornax, andSculptor with $\log(M_{*}/M_{\odot})&lt;$[8.5, 7.5, 6.5]. We showcase ALT'sdiscovery space with: (i) spatially resolved spectra of lensed clumps ingalaxies as faint as $M_{\rm{UV}}\sim-15$; (ii) large-scale clustering --overdensities at $z$=[2.50, 2.58, 3.97, 4.30, 5.66, 5.77, 6.33] hosting massivegalaxies with striking Balmer breaks; (iii) small-scale clustering -- a systemof satellites around a Milky Way analog at $z\sim6$; (iv) spectroscopicallyconfirmed multiple images that help constrain the lensing model underlying allscience in this legacy field; (v) sensitive star-formation maps based ondust-insensitive tracers such as Pa$\alpha$; (vi) direct spectroscopicdiscovery of rare sources such as AGN with ionized outflows. These resultsprovide a powerful proof of concept for how grism surveys maximize thepotential of strong lensing fields.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Submitted to the Open Journal of Astrophysics. Figs. 6 and 10  illustrate the quality of the spectra and imaging, while Fig. 12 summarizes  the yield of the survey. Comments warmly welcomed and greatly appreciated.  The ALT DR1 catalog is available at https://zenodo.org/records/13871850
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.01874v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.01874v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Rohan P. Naidu</author><pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01874v1</guid></item><item><title>The PANORAMIC Survey: Pure Parallel Wide Area Legacy Imaging with  JWST/NIRCam</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01875v1</link><description>Christina C. Williams, Pascal A. Oesch, Andrea Weibel, Gabriel Brammer, Aidan P. Cloonan, Katherine E. Whitaker, Laia Barrufet, Rachel Bezanson, Rebecca A. A. Bowler, Pratika Dayal, Marijn Franx, Jenny E. Greene, Anne Hutter, Zhiyuan Ji, Ivo Labbé, Sinclaire M. Manning, Michael V. Maseda, Mengyuan Xiao
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present the PANORAMIC survey, a pure parallel extragalactic imagingprogram with NIRCam observed during JWST Cycle 1. The survey obtained $\sim$530sq arcmin of NIRCam imaging from 1-5$\mu$m, totaling $\sim$192 hours of scienceintegration time. This represents the largest on-sky time investment of anyCycle 1 GO extragalactic NIRCam imaging program by nearly a factor of 2. Thesurvey includes $\sim$432 sq arcmin of novel sky area not yet observed withJWST using at least $6$ NIRCam broad-band filters, increasing the existing areacovered by similar Cycle 1 data by $\sim$60%. 70 square arcmin was also coveredby a 7th filter (F410M). A fraction of PANORAMIC data ($\sim$200 sq arcmin) wasobtained in or around extragalactic deep-fields, enhancing their legacy value.Pure parallel observing naturally creates a wedding cake survey with both wideand ultra-deep tiers, with 5$\sigma$ point source depths at F444W ranging from27.8-29.4 (ABmag), and with minimized cosmic variance. The 6+ filter observingsetup yields remarkably good photometric redshift performance, achievingsimilar median scatter and outlier fraction as CANDELS ($\sigma_{\rmNMAD}\sim0.07$; $\eta\sim0.2$), which enables a wealth of science acrossredshift without the need for followup or ancillary data. We overview theproposed survey, the data obtained as part of this program, and document thescience-ready data products in the first data release. PANORAMIC has deliveredwide-area and deep imaging with excellent photometric performance,demonstrating that pure parallel observations with JWST are a highly efficientobserving mode that is key to acquiring a complete picture of galaxy evolutionfrom rare bright galaxies to fainter, more abundant sources at all redshifts.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Submitted to AAS Journals; comments welcome. Initial data release  available at https://panoramic-jwst.github.io/
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.01875v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.01875v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Christina C. Williams</author><pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01875v1</guid></item><item><title>The formation histories of massive and quiescent galaxies in the 3 &lt; z &lt;  4.5 Universe</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.02076v1</link><description>Themiya Nanayakkara, Karl Glazebrook, Corentin Schreiber, Harry Chittenden, Gabriel Brammer, James Esdaile, Colin Jacobs, Glenn G. Kacprzak, Lalitwadee Kawinwanichakij, Lucas C. Kimmig, Ivo Labbe, Claudia Lagos, Danilo Marchesini, M. Martìnez-Marìn, Z. Cemile Marsan, Pascal A. Oesch, Casey Papovich, Rhea-Silvia Remus, Kim-Vy H. Tran
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present the formation histories of 19 massive($\gtrsim3\times10^{10}\text{M}_\odot$) quiescent galaxy candidates at$z\sim3.0-4.5$ observed using JWST/NIRSpec. This completes the spectroscopicconfirmation of the 24 $K$-selected quiescent galaxy sample from the ZFOURGEand 3DHST surveys \citep{Schreiber2018}. Utilizing Prism $1-5\mu$mspectroscopy, we confirm that all 12 sources that eluded confirmation byground-based spectroscopy lie at $z&gt;3$, resulting in a spectroscopicallyconfirmed number density of $\sim1.4\times10^{-5}\text{Mpc}^{-3}$ between$z\sim3-4$. Rest-frame $U-V$ vs $V-J$ color selections show high effectivenessin identifying quiescent galaxies, with a purity of $\sim90\%$. Our analysisshows that parametric star-formation histories (SFHs) from FAST++ and binnedSFHs from Prospector on average yield consistent results, revealing diverseformation and quenching times. The oldest galaxy formed$\sim6\times10^{10}\text{M}_\odot$ by $z\sim10$ and has been quiescent for over1 Gyr at $z\sim3.2$. We detect two galaxies with ongoing star formation and sixwith active galactic nuclei (AGN). We demonstrate that the choice of stellarpopulation models, stellar libraries, wavelength range, and nebular or AGNcontributions does not significantly affect the derived average SFHs of thegalaxies. The assumed SFH prior, however, influences the star formation rate atearly times, where spectral diagnostic power is limited. Simulated $z\sim3$quiescent galaxies from IllustrisTNG, SHARK, and Magneticum broadly match theaverage SFHs of the observed sample but struggle to capture the full diversity,particularly at early stages. Our results emphasize the need for mechanismsthat rapidly build stellar mass and quench star formation within the firstbillion years of the Universe.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Submitted to ApJ. Comments welcome
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.02076v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.02076v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Themiya Nanayakkara</author><pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 22:48:06 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.02076v1</guid></item><item><title>UNCOVER: 404 Error -- Models Not Found for the Triply Imaged Little Red  Dot A2744-QSO1</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06257v1</link><description>Yilun Ma, Jenny E. Greene, David J. Setton, Marta Volonteri, Joel Leja, Bingjie Wang, Rachel Bezanson, Gabriel Brammer, Sam E. Cutler, Pratika Dayal, Pieter van Dokkum, Lukas J. Furtak, Karl Glazebrook, Andy D. Goulding, Anna de Graaff, Vasily Kokorev, Ivo Labbe, Richard Pan, Sedona H. Price, John R. Weaver, Christina C. Williams, Katherine E. Whitaker, Adi Zitrin
    &lt;p&gt;
    JWST has revealed an abundance of compact, red objects at $z\approx5-8$dubbed "little red dots" (LRDs), whose SEDs display a faint blue UV continuumfollowed by a steep rise in the optical. Despite extensive study of theircharacteristic V-shaped SEDs, the nature of LRDs remains unknown. We present anew analysis of the NIRSpec/PRISM spectrum of A2744-QSO1, a triply imaged LRDat $z=7.04$ from the UNCOVER survey. The spectrum shows a strong Balmer breakand broad Balmer emission lines, both of which are difficult to explain withmodels invoking exclusively AGN or stellar contributions. Our fiducial modeldecomposes the spectrum into a post-starburst galaxy dominating the UV-opticalcontinuum and a reddened AGN being sub-dominant at all wavelength andcontributing at $\sim20\%$ level. However, our most credible model infers astellar mass of $M_\star\approx 4\times10^9\,\mathrm{M_\odot}$ within a radiusof $r_\mathrm{e}&lt;30\,$pc, driving its central density to the highest amongobservations to date. This high central density could be explained ifA2744-QSO-1 is the early-forming core of a modern-day massive elliptical galaxythat later puffed up via the inside-out growth channel. The models alsonecessitate an unusually steep dust law to preserve the strong break strength,though this steepness may be explained by a deficit of large dust grains. It isalso probable that these challenges reflect our ignorance of A2744-QSO1's truenature. Future variability and reverberation mapping studies could helpdisentangle the galaxy and AGN contribution to the continuum, and deeper redderobservations could also unveil the dust properties in LRDs.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 19 pages, 7 figures, 2 tables. Submitted to ApJ. Comments are welcome
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.06257v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.06257v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Yilun Ma</author><pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 18:00:05 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06257v1</guid></item><item><title>RUBIES: JWST/NIRSpec resolves evolutionary phases of dusty star-forming  galaxies at $z\sim2$</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08387v1</link><description>Olivia R. Cooper, Gabriel Brammer, Kasper E. Heintz, Sune Toft, Caitlin M. Casey, David J. Setton, Anna de Graaff, Leindert Boogaard, Nikko J. Cleri, Steven Gillman, Rashmi Gottumukkala, Jenny E. Greene, Bitten Gullberg, Michaela Hirschmann, Raphael E. Hviding, Erini Lambrides, Joel Leja, Arianna S. Long, Sinclaire M. Manning, Michael V. Maseda, Ian McConachie, Jed McKinney, Desika Narayanan, Sedona H. Price, Victoria Strait, Andrea Weibel, Christina C. Williams
    &lt;p&gt;
    The dearth of high quality spectroscopy of dusty star-forming galaxies(DSFGs) -- the main drivers of the assembly of dust and stellar mass at thepeak of activity in the Universe -- greatly hinders our ability to interprettheir physical processes and evolutionary pathways. We present JWST/NIRSpecobservations from RUBIES of four submillimeter-selected, ALMA-detected DSFGs atcosmic noon, $z\sim2.3-2.7$. While photometry uniformly suggests vigorousongoing star formation for the entire sample in line with canonical DSFGs, thespectra differ: one source has spectroscopic evidence of an evolved stellarpopulation, indicating a recent transition to a post-starburst phase, while theremainder show strong spectroscopic signatures of ongoing starbursts. All fourgalaxies are infrared-luminous (log$_{10}$$L_{\rm{IR}}$/L$_{\rm \odot}$$&gt;12.4$), massive (log$_{10}\,M_\star$/M$_{\rm \odot}$ $&gt;11$), and verydust-obscured ($A_V\sim3-4$ ABmag). Leveraging detections of multiple Balmerand Paschen lines, we derive an optical attenuation curve consistent withCalzetti overall, yet an optical extinction ratio $R_V\sim2.5$, potentiallyindicating smaller dust grains or differences in star-dust geometry. This casestudy provides some of the first detailed spectroscopic evidence that the DSFGsencompass a heterogeneous sample spanning a range of star formation propertiesand evolutionary stages, and illustrates the advantages of synergistic JWST andALMA analysis of DSFGs.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 20 pages, 4 figures; submitted to ApJ
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.08387v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.08387v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Olivia R. Cooper</author><pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 21:46:54 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08387v1</guid></item></channel></rss>