<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>JWST arXiv Feed</title><link>https://github.com/gbrammer/arxiv-to-rss</link><description>Custom arXiv Query of JWST articles</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2024 18:17:08 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.1.1</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Interpreting Multi-band Galaxy Observations with Large Language  Model-Based Agents</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14807v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Zechang Sun, Yuan-Sen Ting, Yaobo Liang, Nan Duan, Song Huang, Zheng Cai
&lt;br&gt;
Astronomical research traditionally relies on extensive domain knowledge tointerpret observations and narrow down hypotheses. We demonstrate that thisprocess can be emulated using large language model-based agents to accelerateresearch workflows. We propose mephisto, a multi-agent collaboration frameworkthat mimics human reasoning to interpret multi-band galaxy observations.mephisto interacts with the CIGALE codebase, which includes spectral energydistribution (SED) models to explain observations. In this open-world setting,mephisto learns from its self-play experience, performs tree search, andaccumulates knowledge in a dynamically updated base. As a proof of concept, weapply mephisto to the latest data from the James Webb Space Telescope. mephistoattains near-human proficiency in reasoning about galaxies' physical scenarios,even when dealing with a recently discovered population of "Little Red Dot"galaxies. This represents the first demonstration of agentic research inastronomy, advancing towards end-to-end research via LLM agents and potentiallyexpediting astronomical discoveries.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: Submitted. Comments are welcome!
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.14807v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.14807v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Zechang Sun</author><pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 09:32:22 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14807v1</guid></item><item><title>Unveiling Multiple Physical Processes on a Cluster Galaxy at z=0.3 Using  JWST</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.15215v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Peter J. Watson, Benedetta Vulcani, Ariel Werle, Bianca Poggianti, Marco Gullieuszik, Michele Trenti, Xin Wang, Namrata Roy
&lt;br&gt;
We present a study of a previously identified candidate ``jellyfish'' galaxyin the Abell 2744 cluster, F0083, which showed faint signs of a tidalinteraction in archival imaging. We used publicly available, PSF-matched deepphotometric data from the Hubble and James Webb Space Telescopes, to infer thespatially-resolved star-formation history of this galaxy. F0083 shows clearsigns of ram-pressure stripping (RPS), with a recently enhanced star-formationrate (SFR) orientated towards the South-West quadrant of the stellar disc. Thestellar mass surface density is heavily asymmetric, with a variation of nearly1 dex between the Western spiral arm and the postulated tidal feature. Thisfeature appears to contain a high proportion of older stars, ruling out RPS asthe cause of this ``unwinding''. An investigation of nearby galaxies revealsthe most probable interaction candidate to be a compact elliptical galaxy,28171, of mass $\log_{10}(M_*/\rm{M}_{\odot})=8.53\pm0.04$ embedded in thetidal stream along our line-of-sight. The star-formation history of the tidalfeature indicates a steep change in SFR at lookback times $t_L\lesssim1\,$Gyr.The most probable formation scenario of F0083 thus indicates a low-speedinteraction with 28171, followed by RPS as the combined system approachespericentre passage. Our results demonstrate the ability of photometric data todistinguish between these consecutive processes.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 18 pages, 14 figures. Submitted to A&amp;A
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.15215v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.15215v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Peter J. Watson</author><pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 17:59:25 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.15215v1</guid></item><item><title>The impact of faint AGN discovered by JWST on reionization</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.15453v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Shikhar Asthana, Martin G. Haehnelt, Girish Kulkarni, James S. Bolton, Prakash Gaikwad, Laura C. Keating, Ewald Puchwein
&lt;br&gt;
The relative contribution of emission from stellar sources and accretion ontosupermassive black holes to reionization has been brought into focus again bythe apparent high abundance of faint AGN at $4\lesssim z\lesssim11$ uncoveredby JWST. We investigate the contribution of these faint AGN to hydrogen and theearly stages of helium reionization using the GPU-based radiative transfer codeATON-HE by post-processing a cosmological hydrodynamical simulation from theSHERWOOD-RELICS suite of simulations. We study four models of reionization: twopreviously studied galaxy-only late-end reionization models and two new models-- a QSO-assisted model and a QSO-only model. In the QSO-assisted model, 1\% ofthe haloes host AGN with a 10~Myr lifetime, and the AGN luminosities are scaledsuch that the AGN contribution to the hydrogen-ionizing emissivity is 20\% ofthat contributed by galaxies. In the QSO-only model, quasars account for allthe hydrogen-ionizing emissivity, with 10\% of the haloes hosting AGN, eachwith a 10 Myr lifetime. All models are calibrated to the observed meanLyman-$\alpha$ forest transmission at $5\lesssim z\lesssim6.2$. We find thatthe QSO-assisted model requires an emissivity factor of $1.8$ lower than thegalaxy-only models towards the end of reionization and fits the observeddistribution of the Lyman-$\alpha$ optical depths well. Our QSO-only model isinconsistent with the observed Lyman-$\alpha$ optical depths distribution. Italso results in too high IGM temperatures at $z\lesssim 5$ due to an earlyonset of HeII reionization unless the escape fraction of HeII-ionizing photonsis assumed to be low. Our results suggest that a modest contribution toreionization by faint AGN is in good agreement with the Lyman-$\alpha$ forestdata. In contrast, a scenario dominated by faint AGN appears difficult toreconcile with these observations.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 19 pages, 11 figures
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.15453v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.15453v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Shikhar Asthana</author><pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 19:29:27 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.15453v1</guid></item><item><title>The emergence of galactic thin and thick discs across cosmic history</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.15909v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Takafumi Tsukui, Emily Wisnioski, Joss Bland-Hawthorn, Ken Freeman
&lt;br&gt;
Modern disc galaxies commonly have distinct thin and thick discs that areseparable in some combination of their kinematics, radial structure, chemistryand/or age. The formation mechanisms of the two discs and the timing of theironset remain open questions. To address these questions, we select edge-ongalaxies from flagship JWST programs and investigate their disc structures inrest-frame, near-infrared bands. For the first time, we identify thick and thindiscs at cosmological distances, dating back over 10 Gyr, and investigate theirdecomposed structural properties. We classify galaxies into those requires twodiscs (thin and thick discs) and those well fitted by a single disc. Discradial sizes and vertical heights correlate strongly with total galaxy massand/or disc mass, independent of cosmic time. The structure of thick discsresemble discs found in single-disc galaxies, suggesting that galaxies form athick disc first followed by thin disc formation. The transition from single todouble discs occurred around 8 Gyr ago in high-mass galaxies ($10^{9.75} -10^{11}M_\odot$), earlier than the transition which occurred 4 Gyr ago inlow-mass galaxies ($10^{9.0} - 10^{9.75}M_\odot$), indicating sequentialformation proceeds in a "downsizing" manner. Toomre $Q$-regulated discformation explains the delayed thin disc formation in low-mass galaxies,leading to the observed anti-correlation between the thick-to-thin disc massratio and total galaxy mass. Despite the dominant sequential formation,observations suggest that thick discs may continue to build up mass alongsidetheir thin-disc counterparts.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 18 pages and 14 figures (30 pages and 25 figures including the  appendix), submitted version. Comments are warmly welcomed
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.15909v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.15909v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Takafumi Tsukui</author><pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 10:26:06 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.15909v1</guid></item><item><title>JWST Observations of Young protoStars (JOYS). HH 211: the textbook case  of a protostellar jet and outflow</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.16061v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
A. Caratti o Garatti, T. P. Ray, P. J. Kavanagh, M. J. McCaughrean, C. Gieser, T. Giannini, E. F. van Dishoeck, K. Justtanont, M. L. van Gelder, L. Francis, H. Beuther, Ł. Tychoniec, B. Nisini, M. G. Navarro, R. Devaraj, S. Reyes, P. Nazar, P. Klaassen, M. Güdel, Th. Henning, P. O. Lagage, G. Östlin, B. Vandenbussche, C. Waelkens, G. Wright
&lt;br&gt;
We use the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) and its Mid-Infrared Instrument(MIRI) (5-28 um), to study the embedded HH 211 flow. We map a 0.95'x0.22'region, covering the full extent of the blue-shifted lobe, the centralprotostellar region, and a small portion of the red-shifted lobe. The jetdriving source is not detected even at the longest mid-IR wavelengths. Theoverall morphology of the flow consists of a highly collimated jet, mostlymolecular (H2, HD) with an inner atomic ([FeI], [FeII], [SI], [NiII])structure. The jet shocks the ambient medium, producing several largebow-shocks, rich in forbidden atomic and molecular lines, and is driving an H2molecular outflow, mostly traced by low-J, v=0 transitions. Moreover, 0-0 S(1)uncollimated emission is also detected down to 2"-3" (~650-1000 au) from thesource, tracing a cold (T=200-400 K), less dense and poorly collimatedmolecular wind. The atomic jet ([FeII] at 26 um) is detected down to ~130 aufrom source, whereas the lack of H2 emission close to the source is likely dueto the large visual extinction. Dust continuum-emission is detected at theterminal bow-shocks, and in the blue- and red-shifted jet, being likely dustlifted from the disk. The jet shows an onion-like structure, with layers ofdifferent size, velocity, temperature, and chemical composition. Moreover,moving from the inner jet to the outer bow-shocks, different physical,kinematic and excitation conditions for both molecular and atomic gas areobserved. The jet mass-flux rate, momentum, and momentum flux of the warm H2component are up to one order of magnitude higher than those inferred from theatomic jet component. Our findings indicate that the warm H2 component is theprimary mover of the outflow, namely it is the most significant dynamicalcomponent of the jet, in contrast to jets from more evolved YSOs, where theatomic component is dominant.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: Paper accepted in A&amp;A for publication
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.16061v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.16061v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>A. Caratti o Garatti</author><pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 14:02:58 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.16061v1</guid></item><item><title>TRINITY VI: Connection between Galaxy Star Formation Rates and  Supermassive Black Hole Accretion Rates from z=0-10</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.16347v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Haowen Zhang, Peter Behroozi, Marta Volonteri, Joseph Silk, Xiaohui Fan, James Aird, Jinyi Yang, Feige Wang, Philip F. Hopkins
&lt;br&gt;
We infer supermassive black hole (SMBH) accretion rates and Eddington ratiosas a function of SMBH/host galaxy mass and redshift with the empirical TRINITYmodel of dark matter halo--galaxy--SMBH connection. The galaxy--SMBH mass andgrowth rate connection from TRINITY is constrained by galaxy observables from$0&lt;z&lt;13$ and SMBH observables from $0&lt;z&lt;6.5$. Key findings include: 1) theratio between cosmic SMBH accretion rate and galaxy star formation rate staysconstant at $\sim 2\times 10^{-3}$ from $z=0-4$, and decreases by 2 orders ofmagnitude from $z=4-10$; 2) the average SMBH Eddington ratio $\overline{\eta}$increases towards higher redshifts, nearly reaching $\overline{\eta}=1$ at$z\sim 10$; 3) at fixed redshift for $z&lt;3$, SMBHs/galaxies with higher masseshave lower $\overline{\eta}$, consistent with AGN downsizing; 4) the averageratio of specific SMBH accretion rate ($\overline{\mathrm{SBHAR}}$) to averagespecific star formation rate ($\overline{\mathrm{SSFR}}$) is nearlymass-independent, with a value$\overline{\mathrm{SBHAR}}/\overline{\mathrm{SSFR}}\sim 1$, which decreasesslightly from $z=10$ to $z=0$; 5) similar to galaxies, SMBHs reach their peakefficiency to convert baryons into mass when host halos reach $10^{12}M_\odot$; 6) given galaxy and SMBH growth histories from TRINITY, the localdescendants of $1&lt;z&lt;11$ overmassive JWST AGNs will remain outliers from thelocal SMBH mass--galaxy mass relation. These findings combine to give a simpleexplanation for massive ($10^9-10^{10}M_\odot$) quasars at $z&gt;6$: at theseredshifts, dark matter halos experience $\sim$Eddington specific growth rates,driving $\sim$Eddington specific growth rates in both galaxies and SMBHs.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 14 pages, 19 figures, submitted to MNRAS
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.16347v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.16347v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Haowen Zhang</author><pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 19:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.16347v1</guid></item><item><title>GOALS-JWST: Constraining the Emergence Timescale for Massive Star  Clusters in NGC 3256</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.16503v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Sean T. Linden, Thomas Lai, Aaron S. Evans, Lee Armus, Kirsten L. Larson, Jeffrey A. Rich, Vivian U, George C. Privon, Hanae Inami, Yiqing Song, Marina Bianchin, Thomas Bohn, Victorine A. Buiten, Maria Sanchez-Garcia, Justin Kader, Laura Lenkic, Anne M. Medling, Torsten Boeker, Tanio Diaz-Santos, Vassilis Charmandaris, Loreto Barcos-Munoz, Paul van der Werf, Sabrina Stierwalt, Susanne Aalto, Philip Appleton, Christopher C. Hayward, Justin H. Howell, Matthew A. Malkan, Joseph M. Mazzarella, Eric J. Murphy, Jason Surace
&lt;br&gt;
We present the results of a James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) NIRCam andNIRSpec investigation into the young massive star cluster (YMC) population ofNGC 3256, the most cluster-rich luminous infrared galaxy (LIRG) in the GreatObservatories All Sky LIRG Survey. We detect 3061 compact YMC candidates with a$S/N \geq 3$ at F150W, F200W, and F335M. Based on yggdrasil stellar populationmodels, we identify 116/3061 sources with F150W - F200W $&gt; 0.47$ and F200W -F355M $&gt; -1.37$ colors suggesting they are young (t $\leq 5$ Myr), dusty($A_{V} = 5 - 15$), and massive ($M_{\odot} &gt; 10^{5}$). This increases thesample of dust-enshrouded YMCs detected in this system by an order of magnituderelative to previous HST studies. With NIRSpec IFU pointings centered on thenorthern and southern nucleus, we extract the Pa$\alpha$ and 3.3$\mu$m PAHequivalent widths for 8 bright and isolated YMCs. Variations in both the F200W- F335M color and 3.3$\mu$m PAH emission with the Pa$\alpha$ line strengthsuggest a rapid dust clearing ($&lt; 3 - 4$ Myr) for the emerging YMCs in thenuclei of NGC 3256. Finally, with both the age and dust emission accuratelymeasured we use yggdrasil to derive the color excess (E(B - V)) for all 8 YMCs.We demonstrate that YMCs with strong 3.3$\mu$m PAH emission (F200W - F335M $&gt;0$) correspond to sources with E(B - V) $&gt; 3$, which are typically missed inUV-optical studies. This underscores the importance of deep near-infraredimaging for finding and characterizing these very young and dust-embeddedsources.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 18 pages, 7 figures, 1 table; Accepted for publication in ApJL
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.16503v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.16503v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Sean T. Linden</author><pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2024 00:23:10 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.16503v1</guid></item><item><title>ALMA observations of super-early galaxies: attenuation-free model  predictions</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17223v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
A. Ferrara, S. Carniani, F. di Mascia, R. Bouwens, P. Oesch, S. Schouws
&lt;br&gt;
The abundance and blue color of super-early (redshift $z&gt;10$), luminousgalaxies discovered by JWST can be explained if radiation-driven outflows haveejected their dust on kpc-scales. To test this hypothesis, we predict the ALMAdetectability of such extended dust component. Given the observed properties ofthe galaxy, its observed continuum flux at 88 $\mu$m, $F_{88}$, depends on thedust-to-stellar mass ratio, $\xi_d$, and extent of the dust distribution,$r_d$. Once applied to the most distant galaxy known, GS-z14-0 at $z=14.32$,the fiducial model ($\xi_d = 1/529$) predicts $F_{88}^{\rm fid} = 14.9\,\mu$Jy, and a dust extent $r_d=1.4$ kpc. If the galaxy is very dust-rich($\xi_d =1/40$), $F_{88}^{\rm max} = 40.1\, \mu$Jy. These values are smaller($F_{88}^{\rm fid} = 9.5\, \mu$Jy) if the dust is predominantly made of largegrains as those formed in SN ejecta. Forthcoming ALMA observations might comevery close to constraining the fiducial predictions of the outflow-basedattenuation-free model. Other super-early galaxies are predicted to be fainterat 88 $\mu$m, mostly because of their lower SFR compared to GS-z14-0, withfiducial fluxes in the range $2-5.2\ \mu$Jy.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 9 pages, 2 figures, submitted to A&amp;A, comments welcome
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.17223v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.17223v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>A. Ferrara</author><pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2024 19:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17223v1</guid></item><item><title>Extended hot dust emission around the earliest massive quiescent galaxy</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17233v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Zhiyuan Ji, Christina C. Williams, George H. Rieke, Jianwei Lyu, Stacey Alberts, Fengwu Sun, Jakob M. Helton, Marcia Rieke, Irene Shivaei, Francesco D'Eugenio, Sandro Tacchella, Brant Robertson, Yongda Zhu, Roberto Maiolino, Andrew J. Bunker, Yang Sun, Christopher N. A. Willmer
&lt;br&gt;
A major unsolved problem in galaxy evolution is the early appearance ofmassive quiescent galaxies that no longer actively form stars only $ \sim 1$billion years after the Big Bang. Their high stellar masses and extremelycompact structure indicate that they formed through rapid bursts of starformation between redshift $z \sim 6-11$. Theoretical models of galaxyevolution cannot explain their high number density, rapid growth and truncationof star formation at such early times, which likely requires extreme feedbackto destroy the cold interstellar medium (the fuel for star formation). Wereport the discovery of a significant reservoir of hot dust in one of the mostdistant known examples at $z = 4.658$, GS-9209. The dust was identified usingJWST's Mid-Infrared Instrument (MIRI), whose unprecedented sensitivity and highspatial resolution, for the first time, firmly show that this dust issignificantly more extended than the stars by $\gtrsim 3$ times. We find thatthe dust has preferentially been evacuated or diluted in the galaxy center. Ouranalysis finds that the extended hot dust emission is consistent with recentheating by a younger and more spatially extended generation of star formation.This reveals that the earliest quiescent galaxies did not form in a singlerapid burst; instead, similar to galaxy growth at later times, the centerformed first with star formation continuing in an extended envelope. The growthof this galaxy is truncating from the inside out, consistent with central gasdepletion from early AGN feedback.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: Submitted
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.17233v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.17233v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Zhiyuan Ji</author><pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2024 19:00:02 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17233v1</guid></item><item><title>JOYS+ study of solid state $^{12}$C/$^{13}$C isotope ratios in  protostellar envelopes: Observations of CO and CO$_2$ ice with JWST</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17237v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
N. G. C. Brunken, E. F. van Dishoeck, K. Slavicinska, V. J. M. le Gouellec, W. R. M. Rocha, L. Francis, L. Tychoniec, M. L. van Gelder, M. G. Navarro, A. C. A. Boogert, P. J. Kavanagh, P. Nazari, T. Greene, M. E. Ressler, L. Majumdar
&lt;br&gt;
The carbon isotope ratio is a powerful tool for studying the evolution ofstellar systems. Recent detections of CO isotopologues in disks and exoplanetatmospheres pointed towards significant fractionation in these systems. Inorder to understand the evolution of this quantity, it is crucial to trace theisotope abundance from stellar nurseries to planetary systems. During theprotostellar stage the multiple vibrational modes of CO$_2$ and CO ice providea unique opportunity to examine the carbon isotope ratio in the solid state.Now with the sensitivity of the \textit{James Webb Space Telescope}, theseabsorption features have become accessible at high S/N in Solar-mass systems.We quantify the $^{12}$CO$_2$/$^{13}$CO$_2$ and the $^{12}$CO/$^{13}$CO isotoperatios in 17 class 0/I low mass protostars from the $^{12}$CO$_2$ combinationmodes (2.70 ${\mu}$m and 2.77 ${\mu}$m), the $^{12}$CO$_2$ stretching mode(4.27 ${\mu}$m), the $^{13}$CO$_2$ stretching mode (4.39 ${\mu}$m), the$^{12}$CO$_2$ bending mode (15.2 ${\mu}$m), the $^{12}$CO stretching mode (4.67${\mu}$m) and the $^{13}$CO stretching mode (4.78 ${\mu}$m) using JWSTobservations. We also report a detection of the $^{12}$CO overtone mode at 2.35${\mu}$m. The $^{12}$CO$_2$/$^{13}$CO$_2$ ratios are in agreement and we findmean ratios of 85 $\pm$ 23, 76 $\pm$ 12 and 97 $\pm$ 17 for the 2.70 ${\mu}$m,4.27 ${\mu}$m and the 15.2 ${\mu}$m bands, respectively. The main source ofuncertainty stem from the error on the band strengths. The $^{12}$CO/$^{13}$COratios derived from the 4.67 ${\mu}$m bands are consistent, albeit elevatedwith respect to the $^{12}$CO$_2$/$^{13}$CO$_2$ ratios and we find a mean ratioof 165 $\pm$ 52. These findings indicate that ices leave the pre-stellar stagewith elevated carbon isotope ratios relative to the interstellar medium andthat fractionation becomes significant during the later stages.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.17237v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.17237v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>N. G. C. Brunken</author><pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2024 19:00:03 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17237v1</guid></item><item><title>An Hα view of galaxy build-up in the first 2 Gyr: luminosity  functions at z~4-6.5 from NIRCam/grism spectroscopy</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17241v2</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Alba Covelo-Paz, Emma Giovinazzo, Pascal A. Oesch, Romain A. Meyer, Andrea Weibel, Gabriel Brammer, Yoshinobu Fudamoto, Josephine Kerutt, Jamie Lin, Jasleen Matharu, Rohan P. Naidu, Anna Velichko, Victoria Bollo, Rychard Bouwens, John Chisholm, Garth D. Illingworth, Ivan Kramarenko, Daniel Magee, Michael Maseda, Jorryt Matthee, Erica Nelson, Naveen Reddy, Daniel Schaerer, Mauro Stefanon, Mengyuan Xiao
&lt;br&gt;
The H{\alpha} nebular emission line is an optimal tracer for recent starformation in galaxies. With the advent of JWST, this line has recently becomeobservable at z&gt;3 for the first time. We present a catalog of 1013 H{\alpha}emitters at 3.7&lt;z&lt;6.7 in the GOODS fields obtained from a blind search in JWSTNIRCam/grism data. We make use of the FRESCO survey's 124 arcmin^2 ofobservations in GOODS-North and GOODS-South with the F444W filter, probingH{\alpha} at 4.9&lt;z&lt;6.7; and the CONGRESS survey's 62 arcmin^2 in GOODS-Northwith F356W, probing H{\alpha} at 3.8&lt;z&lt;5.1. We find an overdensity with 97sources at z~4.4 in GOODS-N and confirm previously reported overdensities at$z\sim5.2$ in GOODS-N and at z~5.4 and z~5.9 in GOODS-S. We compute theobserved H{\alpha} luminosity functions (LFs) in three bins centered at z~4.45,5.30, and 6.15, which are the first such measurements at z&gt;3 obtained basedpurely on spectroscopic data, robustly tracing galaxy star formation rates(SFRs) beyond the peak of the cosmic star formation history. We compare ourresults with theoretical predictions from three different simulations and findgood agreement at z~4-6. The UV LFs of this spectroscopically-confirmed sampleare in good agreement with pre-JWST measurements obtained withphotometrically-selected objects. Finally, we derive SFR functions andintegrate these to compute the evolution of the cosmic star-formation ratedensities across z~4-6, finding values in good agreement with recent UVestimates from Lyman-break galaxies, which imply a continuous decrease in SFRdensity by a factor of 3x over z~4 to z~6. Our work shows the power of NIRCamgrism observations to efficiently provide new tests for early galaxy formationmodels based on emission line statistics.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 17 pages, 14 figures
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.17241v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.17241v2 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Alba Covelo-Paz</author><pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2024 19:00:13 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17241v2</guid></item><item><title>A Giant Disk Galaxy Two Billion Years After The Big Bang</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17956v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Weichen Wang, Sebastiano Cantalupo, Antonio Pensabene, Marta Galbiati, Andrea Travascio, Charles C. Steidel, Michael V. Maseda, Gabriele Pezzulli, Stephanie de Beer, Matteo Fossati, Michele Fumagalli, Sofia G. Gallego, Titouan Lazeyras, Ruari Mackenzie, Jorryt Matthee, Themiya Nanayakkara, Giada Quadri
&lt;br&gt;
Observational studies showed that galaxy disks are already in place in thefirst few billion years of the universe. The early disks detected so far, withtypical half-light radii of 3 kiloparsecs at stellar masses around 10^11 M_sunfor redshift z~3, are significantly smaller than today's disks with similarmasses, in agreement with expectations from current galaxy models. Here, wereport observations of a giant disk at z=3.25, when the universe was only 2billion years old, with a half-light radius of 9.6 kiloparsecs and stellar massof 3.7^+2.6_-2.2x10^11 M_sun. This galaxy is larger than any otherkinematically-confirmed disks at similar epochs and surprisingly similar totoday's largest disks regarding size and mass. JWST imaging and spectroscopyreveal its spiral morphology and a rotational velocity consistent with localTully-Fisher relation. Multi-wavelength observations show that it lies in anexceptionally dense environment, where the galaxy number density is over tentimes higher than the cosmic average and mergers are frequent. The discovery ofsuch a giant disk suggests the presence of favorable physical conditions forlarge-disk formation in dense environments in the early universe, which mayinclude efficient accretion of gas carrying coherent angular momentum andnon-destructive mergers between exceptionally gas-rich progenitor galaxies.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 22 pages, 11 figures; submitted
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.17956v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.17956v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Weichen Wang</author><pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2024 16:35:04 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17956v1</guid></item><item><title>Combined JWST-MUSE Integral Field Spectroscopy of the Most Luminous  Quasar in the Local Universe, PDS 456</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18086v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Jerome Seebeck, Sylvain Veilleux, Weizhe Liu, David S. N. Rupke, Andrey Vayner, Dominika Wylezalek, Nadia L. Zakamska, Caroline Bertemes
&lt;br&gt;
Fast accreting, extremely luminous quasars contribute heavily to the feedbackprocess within galaxies. While these systems are most common at cosmic noon($z\sim2$), here we choose to study PDS 456, an extremely luminous($L_{bol}\sim 10^{47}$ erg s$^{-1}$) but nearby ($z\sim0.185$) quasar where thephysics of feedback can be studied in greater detail. We present the resultsfrom our analysis of the JWST MIRI/MRS integral field spectroscopic (IFS) dataof this object. The extreme brightness of PDS 456 makes it challenging to studythe extended emission even in this nearby object. MIRI/MRS instrumental effectsare mitigated by using complementary NIRSpec and MUSE IFS data cubes. We showclear evidence of a multiphase gas outflow extending up to 15 kpc from thecentral source. This includes emission from warm molecular (H$_2$ $\nu$ = 0 $-$0 and 1 $-$ 0) and ionized (e.g. Pa$\alpha$, [O III], [Ne III], [Ne VI]) gaswith typical blueshifted velocities down to $-500$ km s$^{-1}$. We are alsoable to probe the nuclear dust emission in this source through silicate and PAHemission features but are unable to spatially resolve it. Our results areconsistent with this powerful quasar driving a radiatively driven wind over abroad range of distances and altering the ionization structure of the hostgalaxy.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 26 pages, 15 figures
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.18086v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.18086v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Jerome Seebeck</author><pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2024 18:29:03 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18086v1</guid></item><item><title>How Early Could the Milky Way's Disk Form?</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18173v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Vadim A. Semenov, Charlie Conroy, Aaron Smith, Ewald Puchwein, Lars Hernquist
&lt;br&gt;
We investigate early, $z &gt; 3$, galaxy formation in a cosmological zoom-insimulation of a close, early-forming Milky Way (MW) analog extracted from TNG50simulation and re-simulated with detailed modeling of cold interstellar medium(ISM) formation, coupled with on-the-fly UV radiative transfer,turbulence-regulated star formation, and stellar feedback. In ourenhanced-physics simulation, the galaxy develops a bi-stable ISM structure(warm, with $T \sim 10^4$ K, and cold, with $T &lt; 100$ K) and exhibitssignificantly more efficient, early, and bursty star formation than in TNG.Notably, the stellar disk of this MW progenitor forms extremely early, around$z\sim6-7$, and exhibits chemo-kinematic properties consistent with thelow-metallicity population of the MW stars. The disk forms rapidly, on atimescale of $\sim$0.2 Gyr which is significantly shorter than the timescaleimplied by the observable chemo-kinematic signatures of disk spinup, $\sim$0.7Gyr, due to the scatter in the age-metallicity relation. The rotational supportof the gas disk and the location of the galaxy on the main sequence areconsistent with early disk galaxies observed by JWST and ALMA at $z\sim4-7$,suggesting that some of these galaxies could be progenitors of MW-like systems.Remarkably, the variation of the global star formation rate (SFR) before diskformation is similar to the observed SFR scatter at these early times. Ourfindings underscore the critical role of modeling a turbulent cold ISM andturbulence-regulated star formation and feedback in driving early SFRvariability, while at the same time enabling early disk formation, withoutdestroying it with overly efficient stellar feedback.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 17 pages + appendix, 12 figures, 2 tables. To be submitted. Comments  are welcome
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.18173v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.18173v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Vadim A. Semenov</author><pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2024 19:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18173v1</guid></item><item><title>Gravitational Wave Forecasts Constrained by JWST AGN Observations for  Early Massive Black Hole Mergers</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18194v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Hanpu Liu, Kohei Inayoshi
&lt;br&gt;
Massive black holes (BHs) grow by gas accretion and mergers, observablethrough electromagnetic (EM) and gravitational wave (GW) emission. The JamesWebb Space Telescope (JWST) has detected faint active galactic nuclei (AGNs),revealing an abundant population of accreting BHs with masses of $M_\bullet\sim10^{6-8}~M_\odot$. This mass range overlaps with the detection scopes ofspace-based GW interferometers and approaches the upper bounds of the predictedmass of seed BHs. We model BH mass assembly in light of the new JWST findingsto investigate their formation channels and predict merger events. Two types ofseed BHs are considered: heavy seeds ($M_\bullet\sim 10^{2-5}~M_\odot$) formedin rare and overdense cosmic regions, and light seeds ($M_\bullet\sim10^{1-3}~M_\odot$) formed as stellar remnants in less massive dark-matterhalos. The BHs grow through episodic accretion and merger events, which wemodel by fitting the AGN luminosity function to observational data includingJWST-identified AGNs at $z\sim 5$. We find that heavy seeds alone struggle toexplain quasars and faint JWST-selected AGNs simultaneously, requiring the moreabundant light seeds. The observed merger rate of BHs from heavy seeds alone islimited to $\lesssim 10^{-1}~{\rm yr}^{-1}$ for major mergers at $z\geq5$.However, the presence of light seeds increases the major merger rate by severalorders of magnitude, which peaks at a total BH mass of $M_\bullet\simeq 2\times10^3~M_\odot$ over $5&lt;z&lt;10$ at a rate of $\sim 30~{\rm yr}^{-1}$. These eventsare detectable by future GW observatories such as the Laser InterferometerSpace Antenna (LISA). Precise sky localization and distance measurement ofthose GW events, with solid angle and luminosity distance uncertainties$\Delta\Omega\Delta\log D_L\lesssim 10^{-4}~\rm deg^2$, will enable EMidentification of mergers at $z\geq5$ and multi-messenger follow-upobservations.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 23 pages, 15 figures, submitted to PRD
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.18194v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.18194v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Hanpu Liu</author><pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2024 19:10:26 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18194v1</guid></item><item><title>"Little Red Dots" cannot reside in the same dark matter halos as  comparably luminous unobscured quasars</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18208v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Elia Pizzati, Joseph F. Hennawi, Joop Schaye, Anna-Christina Eilers, Jiamu Huang, Jan-Torge Schindler, Feige Wang
&lt;br&gt;
The James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) has uncovered a new population ofcandidate broad-line AGN emerging in the early Universe, named ''little reddots'' (LRDs) because of their compactness and red colors at opticalwavelengths. LRDs appear to be surprisingly abundant ($\approx10^{-5}\,\mathrm{cMpc}^{-3}$) given that their inferred bolometric luminositieslargely overlap with the ones of the UV-luminous quasars identified at high $z$in wide-field spectroscopic surveys. In this work, we investigate how thepopulation of LRDs and/or other UV-obscured AGN relates to the one ofunobscured, UV-selected quasars. By comparing their number densities, we inferan extremely large and rapidly evolving obscured:unobscured ratio, ranging from$\approx20:1$ at $z\approx4$ to $\approx2300:1$ at $z\approx7$, and possiblyextending out to very high ($\approx10^{47}\,\mathrm{erg}\,\mathrm{s}^{-1}$)bolometric luminosities. This large obscured:unobscured ratio is incompatiblewith the UV-luminous duty cycle measured for unobscured quasars at$z\approx4-6$, suggesting that LRDs are too abundant to be hosted by the samehalos as unobscured quasars. This implies that either (a) the bolometricluminosities of LRDs are strongly overestimated (possibly because LRDs aredominated by stellar galaxy light) or (b) LRDs follow different scalingrelations than the ones of UV-selected quasars, representing a new populationof accreting SMBHs emerging in the early Universe. A direct comparison betweenthe clustering of LRDs and the one of faint UV-selected quasars will ultimatelyconfirm these findings, and shed light on key properties of LRDs such as theirhost mass distribution and duty cycle. We provide a mock analysis for theclustering of LRDs and show that it is feasible with current and upcoming JWSTsurveys.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 15 pages. Submitted to MNRAS
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.18208v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.18208v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Elia Pizzati</author><pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2024 19:38:10 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18208v1</guid></item><item><title>Growth of Massive Black-Holes in FFB Galaxies at Cosmic Dawn</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18605v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Avishai Dekel, Nicholas C. Stone, Dhruba Dutta Chowdhury, Shmuel Gilbaum, Zhaozhou Li, Nir Mandelker, Frank C. van den Bosch
&lt;br&gt;
The scenario of feedback-free starbursts (FFB), which predicts excessivelybright galaxies at cosmic dawn as observed using JWST, may provide a naturalsetting for black hole (BH) growth. This involves the formation ofintermediate-mass seed BHs and their runaway mergers into super-massive BHswith high BH-to-stellar mass ratios and low AGN luminosities. We present ascenario of merger-driven BH growth in FFB galaxies and study its feasibility.BH seeds form within the building blocks of the FFB galaxies, namely, thousandsof compact star clusters, each starbursting in a free-fall time of a few Myrbefore the onset of stellar and supernova feedback. The BH seeds form by rapidcore collapse in the FFB clusters, in a few free-fall times, sped up by themigration of massive stars due to the young, broad stellar mass function andstimulated by a `gravo-gyro' instability due to internal cluster rotation andflattening. BHs of $10^4 M_\odot$ are expected in $10^6 M_\odot$ FFB clusterswithin sub-kpc galactic disks at $z \sim 10$. The BHs then migrate to thegalaxy center by dynamical friction, hastened by the compact FFB stellargalactic disk configuration. Efficient mergers of the BH seeds will produce$10^{6-8} M_\odot$ BHs with a BH-to-stellar mass ratio $\sim 0.01$ by $z \sim4-7$, as observed. The growth of the central BH by mergers can overcome thebottleneck introduced by gravitational wave recoils if the BHs inspiral withina relatively cold disk or if the escape velocity from the galaxy is boosted bya wet compaction event. Such events, common in massive galaxies at highredshifts, can also help by speeding up the inward BH migration and byproviding central gas to assist with the final parsec problem. The cold diskversion of the FFB scenario provides a feasible route for the formation ofsupermassive BHs.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 24 pages, 14 figures
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.18605v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.18605v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Avishai Dekel</author><pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 11:10:20 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18605v1</guid></item><item><title>Introducing cosmosTNG: simulating galaxy formation with constrained  realizations of the COSMOS field</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.19047v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Chris Byrohl, Dylan Nelson, Benjamin Horowitz, Khee-Gan Lee, Annalisa Pillepich
&lt;br&gt;
We introduce the new cosmological simulation project cosmosTNG, afirst-of-its-kind suite of constrained galaxy formation simulations for theuniverse at Cosmic Noon ($z\sim 2$). cosmosTNG simulates a $0.2$ deg$^2$ patchof the COSMOS field at $z \simeq 2.0-2.2$ using an initial density fieldinferred from galaxy redshift surveys and the CLAMATO Lyman-alpha foresttomography survey, reconstructed by the TARDIS algorithm. We evolve eightdifferent realizations of this volume to capture small-scale variations. Allruns use the IllustrisTNG galaxy formation model with a baryonic massresolution of $10^6$ M$_\odot$, equal to TNG100-1. In this initial study, wedemonstrate qualitative agreement between the evolved large-scale structure andthe spatial distribution of observed galaxy populations in COSMOS, emphasizingthe zFIRE protocluster region. We then compare the statistical properties andscaling relations of the galaxy population, covering stellar, gaseous, andsupermassive black hole (SMBH) components, between cosmosTNG, observations inCOSMOS, and $z \sim 2$ observational data in general. We find that galaxyquenching and environmental effects in COSMOS are modulated by its specificlarge-scale structure, particularly the collapsing protoclusters in the region.With respect to a random region of the universe, the abundance of high-massgalaxies is larger, and the quenched fraction of galaxies is significant lowerat fixed mass. This suggests an accelerated growth of stellar mass, asreflected in a higher cosmic star formation rate density, due to the uniqueassembly histories of galaxies in the simulated COSMOS subvolume. The cosmosTNGsuite will be a valuable tool for studying galaxy formation at cosmic noon,particularly when interpreting extragalactic observations with HST, JWST, andother large multi-wavelength survey programs of the COSMOS field.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.19047v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.19047v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Chris Byrohl</author><pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 19:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.19047v1</guid></item><item><title>The Ancient Star Formation History of the Extremely Low-Mass Galaxy Leo  P: An Emerging Trend of a Post-Reionization Pause in Star Formation</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.19050v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Kristen B. W. McQuinn, Max J. B. Newman, Evan D. Skillman, O. Grace Telford, Alyson Brooks, Elizabeth A. K. Adams, Danielle A. Berg, Martha L. Boyer, John M. Cannon, Andrew E. Dolphin, Anthony Pahl, Katherine L. Rhode, John J. Salzer, Roger E. Cohen, Steve R. Goldman
&lt;br&gt;
Isolated, low-mass galaxies provide the opportunity to assess the impact ofreionization on their star formation histories (SFHs) without the ambiguity ofenvironmental processes associated with massive host galaxies. There are veryfew isolated, low-mass galaxies that are close enough to determine their SFHsfrom resolved star photometry reaching below the oldest main sequence turnoff.JWST has increased the volume for which this is possible, and here we report onJWST observations of the low-mass, isolated galaxy Leo P. From NIRCam imagingin F090W, F150W, and F277W, we derive a SFH which shows early star formationfollowed by a pause subsequent to the epoch of reionization which is then laterfollowed by a re-ignition of star formation. This is very similar to the SFHsfrom previous studies of other dwarf galaxies in the ``transition zone''between quenched very low-mass galaxies and the more massive galaxies whichshow no evidence of the impact of reionization on their SFHs; this pattern israrely produced in simulations of SFHs. The lifetime SFH reveals that Leo P'sstellar mass at the epoch of reionization was in the range that is normallyassociated with being totally quenched. The extended pause in star formationfrom z~5-1 has important implications for the contribution of low-mass galaxiesto the UV photon budget at intermediate redshifts. We also demonstrate that,due to higher sensitivity and angular resolution, observing in two NIRCam shortwavelength filters is superior to observing in a combination of a short and along wavelength filter.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 24 pages, 9 figures, 3 tables
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.19050v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.19050v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Kristen B. W. McQuinn</author><pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 19:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.19050v1</guid></item><item><title>A Search for $z=5$ H$α$ and H$β+$[O III] Dual-Line Emitting  Galaxies in the JWST CEERS Field: Implications for the AGN Abundance</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.19205v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Jingsong Guo, Masafusa Onoue, Kohei Inayoshi, Dale D. Kocevski, Steven L. Finkelstein, Micaela B. Bagley, Elizabeth J. McGrath
&lt;br&gt;
The James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) has enabled us to uncover faintgalaxies and active galactic nuclei (AGNs) in the early universe. Takingadvantage of the unique filter combination used in the Cosmic Evolution EarlyRelease Science Survey (CEERS) program, we perform an extensive photometricsearch of galaxies emitting strong H$\beta+$[O III] and H$\alpha$ lines. Theredshift range of the galaxies is limited to $5.03\leq z\leq 5.26$ by requiringphotometric excesses in NIRCam's F277W and F410M images. A total of 261H$\beta+$[O III] and H$\alpha$ dual-line emitters are found over the absoluteUV magnitude $-22\lesssim M_{\mathrm{UV}}\lesssim -17$, with a mean rest-frameequivalent width of 1010 A for H$\beta+$[O III] and 1040 A for H$\alpha$. Thispopulation accounts for $\sim 40\%$ of the Lyman break galaxies at thisredshift range. Intriguingly, there are 58 objects (22% of the whole sample)that exhibit compact morphology at the rest-UV or optical wavelength. With anassumption that these compact dual-line emitters are dominated by AGN, theirAGN bolometric luminosities are in the range of $2\times 10^{43} \lesssimL_{\rm bol}/({\rm erg~s}^{-1})\lesssim 3\times 10^{44}$. Their number densityis two orders of magnitude higher than the extrapolation from the UV-selectedluminous quasars, which is in good agreement with previous JWST studies ofbroad-line AGNs, requiring a $\sim 10\%$ of the AGN duty cycle. Moreover, ourdual-line emitter sample reaches the faint end of the H$\alpha$ and [O III]luminosity functions down to $\lesssim 10^{42}~{\rm erg~s}^{-1}$. Spectroscopicfollow-up observations are planned in an approved JWST Cycle 3 program, inwhich we aim to confirm their nature, characterize their black hole activity,and construct their mass distribution at $10^6\lesssim M_{\rm BH}/M_\odot\lesssim 10^8$.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 24 pages, 16 figures, 5 tables. submitted to ApJ
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.19205v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.19205v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Jingsong Guo</author><pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2024 02:40:12 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.19205v1</guid></item><item><title>Explanation of high redshift luminous galaxies from JWST by early dark  energy model</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.19941v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Jun-Qian Jiang, Weiyang Liu, Hu Zhan, Bin Hu
&lt;br&gt;
Recent observations from the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) have uncoveredmassive galaxies at high redshifts, with their abundance significantlysurpassing expectations. This finding poses a substantial challenge to bothgalaxy formation models and our understanding of cosmology. Additionally,discrepancies between the Hubble parameter inferred from high-redshift cosmicmicrowave background (CMB) observations and those derived from low-redshiftdistance ladder methods have led to what is known as the ``Hubble tension''.Among the most promising solutions to this tension are Early Dark Energy (EDE)models. In this study, we employ an axion-like EDE model in conjunction with auniversal Salpeter initial mass function to fit the luminosity function derivedfrom JWST data, as well as other cosmological probes, including the CMB, baryonacoustic oscillations (BAO), and the SH0ES local distance ladder. Our findingsindicate that JWST observations favor a high energy fraction of EDE, $f_\text{EDE} \sim 0.2 \pm 0.03 $, and a high Hubble constant value of $ H_0\sim 74.6 \pm 1.2 $ km/s/Mpc, even in the absence of SH0ES data. This suggeststhat EDE not only addresses the $ H_0 $ tension but also provides a compellingexplanation for the observed abundance of massive galaxies identified by JWST.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 21 pages, 4 figures
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.19941v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.19941v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Jun-Qian Jiang</author><pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 05:39:05 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.19941v1</guid></item><item><title>Lyman Continuum Leakers at $z&gt;3$ in the GOODS-S Field: Starburst or Not?</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.20349v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Shuairu Zhu, Fang-Ting Yuan, Chunyan Jiang, Zhen-Ya Zheng, Ruqiu Lin
&lt;br&gt;
We investigate the star-forming properties of 23 Lyman Continuum (LyC)leakers at z &gt; 3 in the Great Observatories' Deep Survey-South (GOODS-S) fieldbased on a systematic review of LyC observations from the literature. Usingdata from the Hubble Space Telescope (HST) and the James Webb Space Telescope(JWST), we construct the spectral energy distributions (SEDs) for these LyCleakers, covering the spectrum from rest-frame ultraviolet to near-infrared.Through the application of a unified modeling approach, we measure theultraviolet slope, star formation rate, and stellar mass for these LyC leakersin a consistent manner. These high-redshift LyC leakers demonstratestatistically blue UV-continuum slopes, which is consistent with their highescape fraction of LyC photons. We find that these high-redshift LyC leakersspan a wide range of specific star formation rate (log(sSFR/yr) from -8.6 to-6.7). Ten of these LyC leakers are located on the star formation mainsequence, instead of all being in the starburst mode. The results indicate thatintense bursts of star formation are not necessarily required for the leakageof LyC photons for galaxies at z &gt; 3.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 12 pages, 3 figures, 2 tables, accepted by ApJL
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.20349v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.20349v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Shuairu Zhu</author><pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 15:50:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.20349v1</guid></item><item><title>Merging Signatures in an Offset Lyman Continuum Emitter at Redshift 3.8</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.20352v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Fang-Ting Yuan, Zhen-Ya Zheng, Chunyan Jiang, Shuairu Zhu, Ruqiu Lin, Cheng Cheng
&lt;br&gt;
Lyman continuum (LyC) emitters at $z&gt;3$ provide critical samples for studyingthe contribution of galaxies to the ionizing background in the Epoch ofReionization. We collect a sample of $z&gt;3$ LyC emitters, a dominant fraction($\sim$60%-70%) of which shows spatial offsets between LyC emission and thenon-ionizing continuum. From this sample, especially, we find a case of anoffset LyC emitter, CDFS-6664 ($z=3.797$), which shows two components in thehigh-resolution Hubble Space Telescope (HST) and James Webb Space Telescope(JWST) images. The exceptionally rich data set of CDFS-6664 enables us toextract the two components across multiple wavelengths and estimate theirphysical properties. We show that CDFS-6664 is consistent with a major mergersystem with boosted star formation in both components and the offset LyCemission is most likely associated with the bluer and younger component in thismerging system. Our result offers an example in which the offset can be causedby a merger. Future observations of more offset LyC emitters would elucidatethe role that mergers play in the escape of LyC photons.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 15 pages, 4 figures, ApJ, in press
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.20352v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.20352v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Fang-Ting Yuan</author><pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 15:50:10 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.20352v1</guid></item><item><title>A physically-motivated template set for high-z galaxy SED fitting</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.20519v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Judah Luberto, Steven Furlanetto, Jordan Mirocha
&lt;br&gt;
We introduce a new physically-motivated spectral template set for fitting thespectral energy distributions (SEDs) of high-z galaxies. We use the publicgalaxy formation code ARES to generate star formation histories of thirteenrepresentative galaxies with diverse masses and generate their predictedspectra across a set of redshifts at z &gt; 6. The model parameters are calibratedto reproduce the properties of z &gt; 6 galaxies observed by HST. Motivated by theapparent importance of bursty star formation at high redshifts, we also includetemplates with recent starbursts. We use these templates with the SED-fittingcode EAZY to analyze both an independent theoretical model and a public sampleof JWST-observed galaxies from the JADES survey. The comparison with asemi-analytic model demonstrates that our fitting framework accurately measuresthe galaxy properties, even when the underlying assumptions of the model differfrom ours. Our preliminary application to JWST data shows that galaxies at z &gt;8 are often bursty (especially at small galaxy masses), follow a star-formingmain sequence similar to those at lower redshift (albeit with a highernormalization), and form stars earlier than expected in ares. Our SED-fittingframework is very fast (thanks to the efficiency of EAZY) but provides fullinferred star formation histories for each source. Additionally, it enables adirect comparison to theoretical models and helps point toward improvementsnecessary in those models.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 31 pages, 14 figures
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.20519v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.20519v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Judah Luberto</author><pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 18:20:19 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.20519v1</guid></item><item><title>The eventful life of a luminous galaxy at z = 14: metal enrichment,  feedback, and low gas fraction?</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.20533v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Stefano Carniani, Francesco D'Eugenio, Xihan Ji, Eleonora Parlanti, Jan Scholtz, Fengwu Sun, Giacomo Venturi, Tom J. L. C. Bakx, Mirko Curti, Roberto Maiolino, Sandro Tacchella, Jorge A. Zavala, Kevin Hainline, Joris Witstok, Benjamin D. Johnson, Stacey Alberts, Andrew J. Bunker, Stéphane Charlot, Daniel J. Eisenstein, Jakob M. Helton, Peter Jakobsen, Nimisha Kumari, Brant Robertson, Aayush Saxena, Hannah Übler, Christina C. Williams, Christopher N. A. Willmer, Chris Willott
&lt;br&gt;
JADES-GS-z14-0 is the most distant spectroscopically confirmed galaxy so far,at $z&gt;14$. With a UV magnitude of -20.81, it is one of the most luminousgalaxies at cosmic dawn and its half-light radius of 260 pc means that starsdominate the observed UV emission. We report the ALMA detection of[OIII]88$\mu$m line emission with a significance of 6.67$\sigma$ and at afrequency of 223.524 GHz, corresponding to a redshift of $14.1796\pm0.0007$,which is consistent with the candidate CIII] line detected in the NIRSpecspectrum. At this spectroscopic redshift, the Lyman break identified withNIRSpec requires a damped Lyman-$\alpha$ absorber with a column density of$\log(N_{\rm HI}/\mathrm{cm}^{-2})=22.23$. The total [OIII]88$\mu$m luminosity(log($(L_{\rm [OIII]}/L_\odot) = 8.3\pm0.1$) is fully consistent with the local$L_{\rm [OIII]}-SFR$ relation. Based on the ${L_{\rm [OIII]}/SFR}$, we infer agas-phase metallicity $&gt;0.1~{\rm Z_{\rm \odot}}$, which is somewhat unexpectedgiven the weakness of the UV emission lines. Using prospector SED modeling andcombining the ALMA data with JWST observations, we find $Z=0.17~{Z_{\rm\odot}}$ and an escape fraction of ionizing photons of 20%, which is necessaryto explain the UV spectrum. We measure an [O III]5007\r{A}/[O III]88$\mu$m lineflux ratio between 1 and 10, resulting in an upper limit to the electrondensity of roughly 300 cm$^{-3}$, which is lower than those measured in otherhigh-$z$ luminous galaxies. The [OIII]88$\mu$m emission line is spectrallyresolved, with a FWHM of 100 km/s, resulting in a dynamical mass of$\log$(M$_{\rm dyn}/M_\odot$) = 9.0$\pm0.2$. This value is comparable to thestellar mass derived from the SED fitting, which implies a very low gasfraction. Past radiation-driven outflows may have cleared the galaxy from thegas, reducing the gas fraction and thus increasing the escape fraction ofionizing photons.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 12 pages, 7 figure
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.20533v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.20533v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Stefano Carniani</author><pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 18:37:31 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.20533v1</guid></item><item><title>Detection of [OIII]88$μ$m in JADES-GS-z14-0 at z=14.1793</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.20549v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Sander Schouws, Rychard J. Bouwens, Katherine Ormerod, Renske Smit, Hiddo Algera, Laura Sommovigo, Jacqueline Hodge, Andrea Ferrara, Pascal A. Oesch, Lucie E. Rowland, Ivana van Leeuwen, Mauro Stefanon, Thomas Herard-Demanche, Yoshinobu Fudamoto, Huub Röttgering, Paul van der Werf
&lt;br&gt;
We report the first successful ALMA follow-up observations of a secure $z &gt;10$ JWST-selected galaxy, by robustly detecting ($6.6\sigma$) the[OIII]$_{88\mu m}\,$ line in JADES-GS-z14-0 (hereafter GS-z14). The ALMAdetection yields a spectroscopic redshift of $z=14.1793\pm0.0007$, andincreases the precision on the prior redshift measurement of$z=14.32_{-0.20}^{+0.08}$ from NIRSpec by $\gtrsim$180$\times$. Moreover, theredshift is consistent with that previously determined from a tentativedetection ($3.6\sigma$) of CIII]$_{1907,1909}$ ($z=14.178\pm0.013$),solidifying the redshift determination via multiple line detections. We measurea line luminosity of $L_\mathrm{[OIII]88} = (2.1 \pm 0.5)\times10^8\,L_\odot$,placing GS-z14 at the lower end, but within the scatter of, the local$L_\mathrm{[OIII]88}$-star formation rate relation. No dust continuum fromGS-z14 is detected, suggesting an upper limit on the dust-to-stellar mass ratioof $&lt; 2 \times 10^{-3}$, consistent with dust production from supernovae with ayield $y_d &lt; 0.3\,M_\odot$. Combining a previous JWST/MIRI photometricmeasurement of the [OIII]$\lambda\lambda$4959,5007$\mathrm{\mathring{A}}$ andH$\beta$ lines with Cloudy models, we find GS-z14 to be surprisinglymetal-enriched ($Z\sim0.05 - 0.2\,Z_\odot$) a mere $300\,\mathrm{Myr}$ afterthe Big Bang. The detection of a bright oxygen line in GS-z14 thus reinforcesthe notion that galaxies in the early Universe undergo rapid evolution.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 11 Pages, 6 Figures, 1 Table. Submitted to The Astrophysical Journal
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.20549v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.20549v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Sander Schouws</author><pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 18:50:10 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.20549v1</guid></item><item><title>An Investigation Into The Selection and Colors of Little Red Dots and  Active Galactic Nuclei</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00100v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Kevin N. Hainline, Roberto Maiolino, Ignas Juodzbalis, Jan Scholtz, Hannah Ubler, Francesco D'Eugenio, Jakob M. Helton, Yang Sun, Fengwu Sun, Brant Robertson, Sandro Tacchella, Andrew J. Bunker, Stefano Carniani, Stephane Charlot, Emma Curtis-Lake, Eiichi Egami, Benjamin D. Johnson, Xiaojing Lin, Jianwei Lyu, Pablo G. Perez-Gonzalez, Pierluigi Rinaldi, Maddie S. Silcock, Christina C. Williams, Christopher N. A. Willmer, Chris Willott, Junyu Zhang, Yongda Zhu
&lt;br&gt;
Recently, a large number of compact sources at $z &gt; 4$ with blue UV slopesand extremely red rest-frame optical slopes have been found in James Webb SpaceTelescope (JWST) extragalactic surveys. As a subsample of these sources,commonly called ``little red dots'' (LRDs), have been spectroscopicallyobserved to host a broad-line active galactic nucleus (AGN), they have been thefocus of multiple recent studies in an attempt to understand the origin oftheir UV and optical emission. Here, we assemble a sample of 123 LRDs from theliterature along with spectroscopic and photometric JWST-identified samples ofAGNs to compare their colors and spectral slopes. We find that while obscuredAGNs at $z &lt; 6$ have highly dissimilar colors to LRDs, unobscured AGNs at $z &lt;6$ span a wide range of colors, with only a subsample showing colors similar toLRDs. At $z &gt; 6$, the majority of the unobscured AGNs that have been found inthese samples are LRDs, but this may be related to the fact that these sourcesare at large bolometric luminosities. Because LRDs occupy a unique position ingalaxy color space, they are more straightforward to target, and the largenumber of broad-line AGNs that do not have LRD colors and slopes are thereforeunderrepresented in many spectroscopic surveys because they are more difficultto pre-select. Current LRD selection techniques return a large and disparatepopulation, including many sources having $2-5\mu$m colors impacted by emissionline flux boosting in individual filters.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 18 pages, 6 figures, submitted to AAS Journals
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.00100v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.00100v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Kevin N. Hainline</author><pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 19:00:01 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00100v1</guid></item><item><title>Improved Empirical Backgrounds for JWST NIRISS Image/WFSS Data Reduction</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00103v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Raphael E. Hviding, Ivelina G. Momcheva, Leonardo Clarke
&lt;br&gt;
The Near Infrared Imager and Slitless Spectrograph (NIRISS) on the James WebbSpace Telescope (JWST) is a versatile instrument for collecting imaging andwide-field slitless spectroscopy (WFSS) data for surveys of galaxy clusters,emission-line galaxies, stellar populations, and more. Dispersed zodiacal lightimprints distinct structures on space-based near-infrared imaging and WFSSobservations, necessitating careful subtraction during JWST NIRISS datareduction. As of 2024-09-24 NIRISS WFSS calibration backgrounds introducesignificant spatially-dependent artifacts, up to 5% of the overall backgroundlevel, which can severely affect data quality and following astronomicalanalysis. Notably, there are no existing backgrounds for NIRISS imaging datawhich also show systematic artifacts, such as the `light saber' effect. In thiswork, we present improved empirical JWST NIRISS imaging and WFSS backgroundsderived from all available public data in the F115W, F150W, and F200W filters.We demonstrate that our empirical backgrounds provide a more accuraterepresentation of the background structure in NIRISS imaging and WFSS data thanexisting reference files, mitigating the impact of spatially-dependentartifacts. Our empirical backgrounds are publicly available and can be used toimprove the quality of JWST NIRISS imaging and WFSS data reduction.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 12 pages, 7 figures, re-submitted to AAS Journals for final approval.  Empirical Backgrounds described in this work can be found at:  https://zenodo.org/records/13838016
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.00103v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.00103v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Raphael E. Hviding</author><pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 19:00:02 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00103v1</guid></item><item><title>Crimson Behemoth: a Massive Clumpy Structure Hosting a Dusty AGN at  $z=4.91$</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00104v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Takumi S. Tanaka, John D. Silverman, Yurina Nakazato, Masafusa Onoue, Kazuhiro Shimasaku, Yoshinobu Fudamoto, Seiji Fujimoto, Xuheng Ding, Andreas L. Faisst, Francesco Valentino, Shuowen Jin, Christopher C. Hayward, Vasily Kokorev, Daniel Ceverino, Boris S. Kalita, Caitlin M. Casey, Zhaoxuan Liu, Aidan Kaminsky, Qinyue Fei, Irham T. Andika, Erini Lambrides, Hollis B. Akins, Jeyhan S. Kartaltepe, Anton M. Koekemoer, Henry Joy McCracken, Jason Rhodes, Brant E. Robertson, Maximilien Franco, Daizhong Liu, Nima Chartab, Steven Gillman, Ghassem Gozaliasl, Michaela Hirschmann, Marc Huertas-Company, Richard Massey, Namrata Roy, Zahra Sattari, Marko Shuntov, Joseph Sterling, Sune Toft, Benny Trakhtenbrot, Naoki Yoshida, Jorge A. Zavala
&lt;br&gt;
The current paradigm for the co-evolution of galaxies and their supermassiveblack holes postulates that dust-obscured active galactic nuclei (AGNs)represent a transitional phase towards a more luminous and unobscured state.However, our understanding of dusty AGNs and their host galaxies at earlycosmic times is inadequate due to observational limitations. Here, we presentJWST observations of CID-931, an X-ray-detected AGN at a spectroscopic redshiftof $z_{\rm spec}=4.91$. Multiband NIRCam imaging from the COSMOS-Web programreveals an unresolved red core, similar to JWST-discovered dusty AGNs.Strikingly, the red core is surrounded by at least eight massive star-formingclumps spread over $1.\!\!^{\prime\prime}6 \approx 10~{\rm kpc}$, each of whichhas a stellar mass of $10^9-10^{10}M_\odot$ and $\sim0.1-1~{\rm kpc}$ inradius. The whole system amounts to $10^{11}M_\odot$ in stellar mass, higherthan typical star-forming galaxies at the same epoch. In this system, gasinflows and/or complex merger events may trigger clump formation and AGNactivity thus leading to the rapid formation of a massive galaxy hosting asupermassive black hole. Future follow-up observations will provide newinsights into the evolution of the galaxy-black hole relationship during suchtransitional phases in the early universe.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 13 pages, 10 figures, submitted to PASJ
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.00104v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.00104v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Takumi S. Tanaka</author><pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 19:00:02 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00104v1</guid></item><item><title>The AURORA Survey: An Extraordinarily Mature, Star-forming Galaxy at  $z\sim 7$</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00110v2</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Alice E. Shapley, Ryan L. Sanders, Michael W. Topping, Naveen A. Reddy, Anthony J. Pahl, Pascal A. Oesch, Danielle A. Berg, Rychard J. Bouwens, Gabriel Brammer, Adam C. Carnall, Fergus Cullen, Romeel Davé, James S. Dunlop, Richard S. Ellis, N. M. Förster Schreiber, Steven R . Furlanetto, Karl Glazebrook, Garth D. Illingworth, Tucker Jones, Mariska Kriek, Derek J. McLeod, Ross J. McLure, Desika Narayanan, Max Pettini, Daniel Schaerer, Daniel P. Stark, Charles C. Steidel, Mengtao Tang, Leonardo Clarke, Callum T. Donnan, Emily Kehoe
&lt;br&gt;
We present the properties of a massive, large, dusty, metal-rich,star-forming galaxy at z_spec=6.73. GOODSN-100182 was observed withJWST/NIRSpec as part of the AURORA survey, and is also covered by publicmulti-wavelength HST and JWST imaging. While the large mass of GOODSN-100182(~10^10 M_sun) was indicated prior to JWST, NIRCam rest-optical imaging nowreveals the presence of an extended disk (r_eff~1.5 kpc). In addition, theNIRSpec R~1000 spectrum of GOODSN-100182 includes the detection of a largesuite of rest-optical nebular emission lines ranging in wavelength from[OII]3727 up to [NII]6583. The ratios of Balmer lines suggest significant dustattenuation (E(B-V)_gas=0.40+0.10/-0.09), consistent with the red rest-UV slopeinferred for GOODSN-100182 (beta=-0.50+/-0.09). The star-formation rate basedon dust-corrected H-alpha emission is log(SFR(H-alpha)/M_sun/yr)=2.02+0.13/-0.14, well above the z~7 star-forming main sequence interms of specific SFR. Strikingly, the ratio of [NII]6583/H-alpha emissionsuggests almost solar metallicity, as does the ratio([OIII]5007/H-beta)/([NII]6583/H-alpha) and the detection of the faint[FeII]4360 emission feature, whereas the [OIII]5007/[OII]3727 ratio suggestsroughly 50% solar metallicity. Overall, the excitation and ionizationproperties of GOODSN-100182 more closely resemble those of typical star-forminggalaxies at z~2-3 rather than z~7. Based on public spectroscopy of the GOODS-Nfield, we find that GOODSN-100182 resides within a significant galaxyoverdensity, and is accompanied by a spectroscopically-confirmed neighborgalaxy. GOODSN-100182 demonstrates the existence of mature, chemically-enrichedgalaxies within the first billion years of cosmic time, whose properties mustbe explained by galaxy formation models.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 16 pages, 13 figures, submitted to ApJ
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.00110v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.00110v2 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Alice E. Shapley</author><pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 19:00:06 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00110v2</guid></item><item><title>Increased Burstiness at High Redshift in Multi-Physics Models Combining  Supernova Feedback, Radiative Transfer and Cosmic Rays</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00113v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Tibor Dome, Sergio Martin-Alvarez, Sandro Tacchella, Yuxuan Yuan, Debora Sijacki
&lt;br&gt;
We study star formation variability, or burstiness, as a method to constrainand compare different galaxy formation models at high redshift using the Azaharsimulation suite. The models range from magneto-hydrodynamics with amagneto-thermo-turbulent prescription for star formation (iMHD) to moresophisticated setups incorporating radiative transfer (RTiMHD) and cosmic rayphysics (RTnsCRiMHD). Analysing a sample of galaxies at redshifts $z=4-10$, wefind that the RTnsCRiMHD model exhibits more regular star formation periodicitycompared to iMHD and RTiMHD, as revealed by the Lomb-Scargle periodogram. Whilethe RTiMHD model captures a notable degree of stochasticity in star formationwithout cosmic rays, RTnsCRiMHD galaxies display even greater scatter in theburst intensity and in the scatter around the star-forming main sequence. Toevaluate the burstiness in RTnsCRiMHD against observations, we generate a mockspectrum during a mini-quenching event at $z=7.5$. This spectrum aligns wellwith the low-mass quiescent galaxy JADES-GS-z7-01-QU observed at $z=7.3$,though some discrepancies attributed to stellar metallicity hint at a compositespectrum. Our findings highlight the importance of including complex physicalprocesses like cosmic rays and radiative transfer in simulations to accuratelycapture the bursty nature of star formation in high-redshift galaxies. FutureJWST observations, particularly regarding the scatter around the star-formingmain sequence, have the potential to refine and guide the next generation ofgalaxy formation models.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 10 pages, 4 figures, 1 table, comments welcome
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.00113v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.00113v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Tibor Dome</author><pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 19:00:10 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00113v1</guid></item><item><title>CLASSY XI: Tracing Neutral Gas Properties using UV Absorption Lines and  21-cm Observations</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00236v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Kaelee S. Parker, Danielle A. Berg, Simon Gazagnes, John Chisholm, Bethan L. James, Matthew Hayes, Timothy Heckman, Alaina Henry, Michelle A. Berg, Karla Z. Arellano-Cordova, Xinfeng Xu, Dawn K. Erb, Crystal L. Martin, Weida Hu, Evan D. Skillman, Kristen B. W. McQuinn, Zuyi Chen, Dan P. Stark
&lt;br&gt;
Rest-frame far-ultraviolet (FUV) observations from JWST are revolutionizingour understanding of the high-z galaxies that drove reionization and themechanisms by which they accomplished it. To fully interpret theseobservations, we must be able to diagnose how properties of the interstellarmedium (ISM; e.g., column density, covering fraction, outflow velocity)directly relate to the absorption features produced. Using the high-S/N andhigh-resolution FUV spectra of 45 nearby star-forming galaxies from CLASSY, wepresent the largest uniform, simultaneous characterization of neutral andlow-ionization state (LIS) interstellar UV absorption lines (OI, SiII, SII,CII, AlII) across a wide range of galaxy properties. We also present 21-cm HIobservations for 35 galaxies, multiple of which are gas-poor or non-detected,possibly indicating the onset of a post-starburst phase. We find that oursimultaneous 1-component Voigt profile fits are capable of accurately modelingthe LIS absorption for ~75% of galaxies, mitigating challenges associated withsaturation, infilling, and degeneracies. While the most massive galaxiesrequire additional components, our 1-component fits return average propertiesof the absorbing gas and follow the scaling relations described by a single gascloud. We explore connections between LIS absorption and direct tracers of theneutral ISM (OI, Ly-alpha, HI 21-cm), finding that CII most closely traces theneutral gas trends while other ions exhibit weaker correlations. Given thechallenges with directly observing HI at higher-z, we demonstrate that LISabsorption can be a powerful means to study the neutral ISM and presentempirical relationships for predicting neutral gas properties.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 25 pages with 16 figures and 2 tables. Long appendix with figure sets  and tables. Accepted to ApJ
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.00236v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.00236v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Kaelee S. Parker</author><pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 22:03:59 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00236v1</guid></item><item><title>X-Ray Weak AGNs from Super-Eddington Accretion onto Infant Black Holes</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00417v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Piero Madau, Francesco Haardt
&lt;br&gt;
A simple model for the X-ray weakness of JWST-selected broad-line AGNs isproposed under the assumption that the majority of these sources are fed atsuper-Eddington accretion rates. In these conditions, the hot inner coronaabove the geometrically thin disk that is responsible for the emission ofX-rays in "normal" AGNs will be embedded instead in a funnel-like reflectiongeometry. The coronal plasma will Compton upscatter optical/UV photons from theunderlying thick disk as well as the surrounding funnel walls, and the highsoft-photon energy density will cool down the plasma to temperatures in therange 30-40 keV. The resulting X-ray spectra are predicted to be extremelysoft, with power-law photon indices Gamma=2.8-4.0, making high-zsuper-Eddington AGNs largely undetectable by Chandra.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 7 pages, 4 figures, submitted to ApJ. Comments are welcome
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.00417v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.00417v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Piero Madau</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 06:48:52 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00417v1</guid></item><item><title>Searching for new physics using high precision absorption spectroscopy;  continuum placement uncertainties and $Δα/α$ towards the  quasar PHL957</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00684v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
John K. Webb, Chung-Chi Lee, Dinko Milaković, Darren Dougan, Vladimir A. Dzuba, Victor V. Flambaum
&lt;br&gt;
Detecting or placing upper limits on spacetime variations of fundamentalconstants requires quantifying every potential source of uncertainty. Wecontinue our previous study into the impact of continuum variations onmeasurements of the fine structure constant, here in the context of quasarabsorption systems. An automated (hence objective and reproducible) continuummodelling method is reported in an accompanying paper. We apply the method tothe $z_{abs}=1.7975$ absorption system towards the quasar PHL957. Multiplecontinuum fits are generated, and for each, we derive independent models of thesystem, each giving its own measurement of the fine structure constant$\alpha$. This process isolates and quantifies the error contributionassociated with continuum placement uncertainty. This source of uncertainty,ignored in many previous measurements, arises in two ways: (i) slight localcontinuum tilt uncertainty generates small line shifts, and (ii) differentcontinuum estimates produce slightly different kinematic structures in theabsorption system model. Taking continuum placement uncertainty into account,the new PHL957 measurement we obtain is $\Delta\alpha/\alpha=-0.53^{+5.45}_{-5.51} \times 10^{-6}$. This measurement assumes terrestrialmagnesium isotopic abundances. Recommendations are provided for future $\alpha$measurements. Finally, we also note the potential importance of the effectsidentified here for future redshift drift experiments.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 10 pages, 3 figures. Submitted to Open Journal of Astrophysics
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.00684v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.00684v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>John K. Webb</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 14:40:33 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00684v1</guid></item><item><title>Astraeus X: Indications of a top-heavy initial mass function in highly  star-forming galaxies from JWST observations at z&gt;10</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00730v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Anne Hutter, Elie R Cueto, Pratika Dayal, Stefan Gottlöber, Maxime Trebitsch, Gustavo Yepes
&lt;br&gt;
The James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) has uncovered an abundance of $z&gt;10$galaxies bright in the ultraviolet (UV) that has challenged traditionaltheoretical models at high redshifts. Recently, various new models have emergedto address this discrepancy by refining their description of star formation.Here we investigate whether modifications to the stellar initial mass function(IMF) alone can reproduce the $z&gt;10$ UV luminosity functions (UV LFs) when thestar formation rate is used as a proxy for the fraction of massive stars. Weincorporate an Evolving IMF into the {\sc astraeus} galaxy evolution andreionisation simulation framework, which becomes increasingly top-heavy as thegas density in a galaxy rises above a given threshold. Our implementationaccounts for the IMF's effects on supernova (SN) feedback, metal enrichment,and the UV and ionising emissivities. For this Evolving IMF model, we find that(i) the maximum UV luminosity enhancement is twice as large in massive galaxies($\Delta M_\mathrm{UV}\simeq2.6$) than those where star formation is stronglylimited by SN feedback ($\Delta M_\mathrm{UV}\simeq1.3$); (ii) it successfullyreproduces the observed UV LFs at $z=5-15$; (iii) galaxies with top-heavy IMFsexhibit the highest star formation rates, driven by their location in localdensity peaks, which facilitates higher gas accretion rates; (iv) the $1\sigma$variances in the UV luminosity are only slightly higher compared to whenassuming a Salpeter IMF, but the $2\sigma$ variances are significantlyincreased by a factor of $1.4-2$ boosting the abundance of UV-bright galaxiesat $z&gt;10$; (v) reionisation begins earlier with more extended large ionisedregions and fewer smaller ones during its initial stages, though thesedifferences diminish at lower redshifts, leading to a similar end ofreionisation at $z\simeq5.6$.}
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: submitted to A&amp;A, 12 pages, 8 figures, comments welcome
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.00730v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.00730v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Anne Hutter</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 15:17:44 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00730v1</guid></item><item><title>Strong rest-UV emission lines in a "little red dot" AGN at $z=7$: Early  SMBH growth alongside compact massive star formation?</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00949v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Hollis B. Akins, Caitlin M. Casey, Danielle A. Berg, John Chisholm, Maximilien Franco, Steven L. Finkelstein, Seiji Fujimoto, Vasily Kokorev, Erini Lambrides, Brant E. Robertson, Anthony J. Taylor, David A. Coulter, Ori Fox, Mitchell Karmen
&lt;br&gt;
JWST has now revealed a population of broad-line AGN at $z&gt;4$ characterizedby a distinctive SED shape, with very red rest-frame optical and very bluerest-frame UV continuum. While the optical continuum is thought to originatefrom the accretion disk, the origin of the UV continuum has been largelyunclear. We report the detection of the strong rest-frame UV emission lines ofCIII]$\lambda\lambda$1907,1909 and CIV$\lambda\lambda$1549,1551 in a "littlered dot" AGN, COS-66964. Spectroscopically confirmed at $z=7.0371$, COS-66964exhibits broad H$\alpha$ emission (FWHM $\sim 2000$ km s$^{-1}$), and weakbroad H$\beta$, implying significant dust attenuation to the BLR ($A_V =3.9^{+1.7}_{-0.9}$). The H$\alpha$ line width implies a central SMBH mass of$M_{\rm BH} = \left(1.9^{+1.6}_{-0.7}\right)\times10^{7}$ M$_\odot$, and anEddington ratio $\lambda\sim0.3$-$0.5$. While marginal HeII$\lambda4687$ and[FeX]$\lambda6376$ detections further indicate that the AGN dominates in therest-frame optical, the non-detection of HeII$\lambda1640$ in the UV despitehigh EW CIII] and CIV ($\sim 35$ {\AA}) is more consistent with photoionizationby massive stars. The non-detection of MgII$\lambda\lambda$2800 is similarlyinconsistent with an AGN scattered light interpretation. Assuming therest-frame UV is dominated by stellar light, we derive a stellar mass of $\logM_\star/M_\odot\sim8.5$, implying an elevated $M_{\rm BH}/M_\star$ ratio$\sim2$ orders of magnitude above the local relation, but consistent with otherhigh-$z$ AGN discovered by JWST. The source is unresolved in all bands,implying a very compact size $\lesssim200$ pc in the UV. This suggests that thesimultaneous buildup of compact stellar populations (i.e., galaxy bulges) andthe central SMBH is ongoing even at $z&gt;7$.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 14 pages, 6 figures; submitted to ApJL
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.00949v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.00949v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Hollis B. Akins</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 19:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00949v1</guid></item><item><title>The Tale of Two Telescopes: How Hubble Uniquely Complements the James  Webb Space Telescope: Galaxies</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01187v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Rogier A. Windhorst, Jake Summers, Timothy Carleton, Seth H. Cohen, Kevin S. Croker, Rolf A. Jansen, Rosalia O'Brien, Brent M. Smith, Christopher J. Conselice, Jose M. Diego, Simon P. Driver, Brenda Frye, Haojing Yan
&lt;br&gt;
In this paper, we present a simple but compelling argument, focusing ongalaxy science, for preserving the main imagers and operational modes of theHubble Space Telescope (HST) for as long as is technically feasible. Whilestar-formation started at redshifts z$\gtrsim$10$-$13, when the universe wasless than 300$-$500 Myr old, the CSFH did not peak until z$\simeq$1.9, and hassteadily declined since that time. Hence, at least half of all stars in theuniverse formed in the era where HST provides its unique rest-frame UV view ofunobscured young, massive stars tracing cosmic star-formation. By rendering asubset of the 556.3 hours of available HST images in 12 filters of the HubbleUltra Deep Field (HUDF) in an appropriate mix of colors, we illustrate theunique capabilities of HST for galaxy science emphasizing that rest-frameUV$-$optical wavelength range. We then contrast this with the 52.7 publiclyavailable hours of JWST/NIRCam images in 8 filters of the same HUDF area fromthe JADES project, rendering these at the redder near-IR wavelengths toillustrate the unique capabilities of JWST to detect older stellar populationsat higher redshifts, as well as very dusty stellar populations and ActiveGalactic Nuclei (AGN). HST uniquely probes (unobscured) young, hot, massivestars in galaxies, while JWST reveals more advanced stages of older stellarpopulations, as well as relatively short-lived phases where galaxies produceand shed a lot of dust from intense star-formation, and the very high redshiftuniverse (z$\gtrsim$10$-$11) not accessible by HST. We conclude that HST andJWST are highly complementary facilities that took decades to build to ensuredecades of operation. To maximize return on investment on both HST and JWST,ways will need to be found to operate HST imaging instruments in all relevantmodes for as long as possible into the JWST mission.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: White paper submitted to NASA/STScI for the HST Senior Review of  2024. The HST+JWST PDF images are too big for astro-ph. Please view their  full resolution PDF files on:  http://www.asu.edu/clas/hst/www/jwst2024/windhorst_HST_SeniorReview2024_v4.pdf
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.01187v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.01187v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Rogier A. Windhorst</author><pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 03:40:28 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01187v1</guid></item><item><title>Exploring the central region of NGC 1365 in the ultraviolet domain</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01241v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Kshama Sara Kurian, C. S. Stalin, Dominika Wylezalek, Mariya Lyubenova, Tek Prasad Adhikari, Ashish Devaraj, Ram Sagar, Markus-Kissler Patig, Santanu Mondal
&lt;br&gt;
Active galactic nuclei (AGN) feedback and its impact on their host galaxiesare critical to our understanding of galaxy evolution. Here, we present acombined analysis of new high resolution ultraviolet (UV) data from theUltraviolet Imaging Telescope (UVIT) on AstroSat and archival opticalspectroscopic data from VLT/MUSE, for the Seyfert galaxy, NGC 1365.Concentrating on the central 5 kpc region, the UVIT images in the far and nearUV show bright star forming knots in the circumnuclear ring as well as a faintcentral source. After correcting for extinction, we found the star formationrate (SFR) surface density of the circumnuclear 2 kpc ring to be similar toother starbursts, despite the presence of an AGN outflow, as seen in [OIII]5007 Angstrom. On the other hand, we found fainter UV and thus lower SFR in thedirection south-east of the AGN relative to north-west in agreement withobservations at other wavelengths from JWST and ALMA. The AGN outflow velocityis found to be lesser than the escape velocity, suggesting that the outflowinggas will rain back into the galaxy. The deep UV data has also revealed diffuseUV emission in the direction of the AGN outflow. By combining [OIII] and UVdata, we found the diffuse emission to be of AGN origin.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 12 Pages, 7 figures, Accepted for publication in ApJ
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.01241v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.01241v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Kshama Sara Kurian</author><pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 06:04:41 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01241v1</guid></item><item><title>A SPectroscopic survey of biased halos In the Reionization Era (ASPIRE):  JWST Supports Earlier Reionization around [OIII] Emitters</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01318v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Xiangyu Jin, Jinyi Yang, Xiaohui Fan, Feige Wang, Koki Kakiichi, Romain A. Meyer, George D. Becker, Siwei Zou, Eduardo Bañados, Jaclyn B. Champagne, Valentina D'Odorico, Minghao Yue, Sarah E. I. Bosman, Zheng Cai, Anna-Christina Eilers, Joseph F. Hennawi, Hyunsung D. Jun, Mingyu Li, Zihao Li, Weizhe Liu, Maria Pudoka, Sindhu Satyavolu, Fengwu Sun, Wei Leong Tee, Yunjing Wu
&lt;br&gt;
Understanding when and how reionization happened is crucial for studying theearly structure formation and the properties of first galaxies in the Universe.At $z&gt;5.5$, the observed IGM optical depth shows a significant scatter,indicating an inhomogeneous reionization process. However, the nature of theinhomogeneous reionization remains debated. ASPIRE is a JWST Cycle 1 programthat has spectroscopically identified $&gt;400$ [OIII] emitters in 25 quasarfields at $z&gt;6.5$. Combined with deep ground-based optical spectroscopy ofASPIRE quasars, ASPIRE program provides the current largest sample forIGM-galaxy connection studies during cosmic reionization. We present the firstresults of IGM effective optical depth measurements around [OIII] emittersusing 14 ASPIRE quasar fields. We find the IGM transmission is tightly relatedwith reionization-era galaxies to the extent that significant excess ofLy$\alpha$ transmission exists around [OIII] emitters. We measure the stackedIGM effective optical depth of IGM patches associated with [OIII] emitters andfind they reach the same IGM effective optical depth at least dz~0.1 ahead ofthose IGM patches where no [OIII] emitters are detected, supporting earlierreionization around [OIII] emitters. Our results indicate an enhancement in IGMLy$\alpha$ transmission around [OIII] emitters at scales beyond 25 $h^{-1}$cMpc, consistent with the predicted topology of reionization from fluctuatingUV background (UVB) models.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 27 pages, 19 figures, 1 table, accepted for publication in ApJ
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.01318v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.01318v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Xiangyu Jin</author><pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 09:22:36 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01318v1</guid></item><item><title>Proposed importance of HOCO chemistry: Inefficient formation of CO$_2$  from CO and OH reactions on ice dust</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01373v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Atsuki Ishibashi, Germán Molpeceres, Hiroshi Hidaka, Yasuhiro Oba, Thanja Lamberts, Naoki Watanabe
&lt;br&gt;
With the advent of JWST ice observations, dedicated studies on the formationreactions of detected molecules are becoming increasingly important. One of themost interesting molecules in interstellar ice is CO$_2$. Despite itssimplicity, the main formation reaction considered, CO + OH -&gt; CO$_2$ + Hthrough the energetic HOCO* intermediate on ice dust, is subject to uncertaintybecause it directly competes with the stabilization of HOCO as a final productwhich is formed through energy dissipation of HOCO* to the water ice. Whenenergy dissipation to the surface is effective during reaction, HOCO can be adominant product. In this study, we experimentally demonstrate that the majorproduct of the reaction is indeed not CO$_2$, but rather the highly reactiveradical HOCO. The HOCO radical can later evolve into CO$_2$ throughH-abstraction reactions, but these reactions compete with addition reactions,leading to the formation of carboxylic acids (R-COOH). Our results highlightthe importance of HOCO chemistry and encourage further exploration of thechemistry of this radical.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: Accepted in ApJ; 23 pages, 9 figures
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.01373v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.01373v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Atsuki Ishibashi</author><pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 10:37:41 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01373v1</guid></item><item><title>AGN -- host galaxy photometric decomposition using a fast, accurate and  precise deep learning approach</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01437v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Berta Margalef-Bentabol, Lingyu Wang, Antonio La Marca, Vicente Rodriguez-Gomez
&lt;br&gt;
Identification of active galactic nuclei (AGNs) is extremely important forunderstanding galaxy evolution and its connection with the formation andevolution of supermassive black holes (SMBH). With the advent of deep and highangular resolution imaging surveys such as those conducted with the {\it JamesWebb} Space Telescope (JWST), it is now possible to identify galaxies with acentral point source out to the very early Universe. In this study, we developa fast, accurate and precise method to identify galaxies which host AGNs andrecover the intrinsic AGN contribution to the observed total light ($f_{AGN}$).We trained a deep learning (DL) based method Zoobot to estimate the fractionalcontribution of a central point source to the total light. Our training samplecomprises realistic mock JWST images of simulated galaxies from theIllustrisTNG cosmological hydrodynamical simulations. We injected differentamounts of the real JWST point spread function (PSF) models to representgalaxies with different levels of $f_{AGN}$. We analyse the performance of ourmethod and compare it with results obtained from the traditional light profilefitting tool GALFIT. We find excellent performance of our DL method inrecovering the injected AGN fraction $f_{AGN}$, both in terms of precision andaccuracy. The mean difference between the predicted and true injected $f_{AGN}$is $-0.0006$ and the overall root mean square error (RMSE) is $0.027$. Therelative absolute error (RAE) is $0.086$ and the outlier (defined aspredictions with RAE $&gt;20\%$) fraction is $7.8\%$. In comparison, using GALFITon the same dataset, we achieve a mean difference of -$0.024$, RMSE of $0.09$,RAE of $0.19$ and outlier fraction of $19\%$. Our DL-based method to identifyAGNs and estimate $f_{AGN}$ is extremely fast and easy to use and has a hugepotential in future applications to large galaxy imaging surveys.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.01437v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.01437v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Berta Margalef-Bentabol</author><pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 12:39:15 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01437v1</guid></item><item><title>JWST Observations of Young protoStars (JOYS). Overview of gaseous  molecular emission and absorption in low-mass protostars</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01636v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
M. L. van Gelder, L. Francis, E. F. van Dishoeck, Ł. Tychoniec, T. P. Ray, H. Beuther, A. Caratti o Garatti, Y. Chen, R. Devaraj, C. Gieser, K. Justtanont, P. J. Kavanagh, P. Nazari, S. Reyes, W. R. M. Rocha, K. Slavicinska, M. Güdel, Th. Henning, P. -O. Lagage, G. Wright
&lt;br&gt;
The MIRI-MRS instrument onboard JWST allows for probing the molecular gascomposition at mid-IR wavelengths at unprecedented resolution and sensitivity.It is important to study these features in low-mass embedded protostellarsystems since the formation of planets is thought to start in this phase. Wepresent JWST/MIRI-MRS data of 18 low-mass protostellar systems in the JOYSprogram, focusing on gas-phase molecular lines in spectra extracted from thecentral protostellar positions. Besides H2, the most commonly detectedmolecules are H2O, CO2, CO, and OH. Other molecules such as 13CO2, C2H2, 13CCH,HCN, C4H2, CH4, and SO2 are detected only toward at most three of the sources.The JOYS data also yield the surprising detection of SiO gas toward two sources(BHR71-IRS1, L1448-mm) and for the first time CS and NH3 at mid-IR wavelengthstoward a low-mass protostar (B1-c). The temperatures derived for the majorityof the molecules are 100-300 K, much lower than what is typically derivedtoward more evolved Class II sources (&gt;500 K). Toward three sources (e.g.,TMC1-W), hot (~1000 K) H2O is detected, indicative of the presence of hotmolecular gas in the embedded disks, but such warm emission from othermolecules is absent. The agreement in abundance ratios with respect to H2Obetween ice and gas point toward ice sublimation in a hot core for a fewsources (e.g., B1-c) whereas their disagreement and velocity offsets hint athigh-temperature (shocked) conditions toward other sources (e.g., L1448-mm,BHR71-IRS1). The typical temperatures of the gas-phase molecules of 100-300 Kare consistent with both ice sublimation in hot cores as well ashigh-temperature gas phase chemistry. Molecular features originating from theinner embedded disks are not commonly detected, likely because they are tooextincted even at mid-IR wavelengths by small not-settled dust grains in upperlayers of the disk.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 25 pages, 11 figures, accepted for publication in A&amp;A
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.01636v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.01636v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>M. L. van Gelder</author><pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 16:08:02 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01636v1</guid></item><item><title>All the Little Things in Abell 2744: $&gt;$1000 Gravitationally Lensed  Dwarf Galaxies at $z=0-9$ from JWST NIRCam Grism Spectroscopy</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01874v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Rohan P. Naidu, Jorryt Matthee, Ivan Kramarenko, Andrea Weibel, Gabriel Brammer, Pascal A. Oesch, Peter Lechner, Lukas J. Furtak, Claudia Di Cesare, Alberto Torralba, Gauri Kotiwale, Rachel Bezanson, Rychard J. Bouwens, Vedant Chandra, Adélaïde Claeyssens, A. Lola Danhaive, Anna Frebel, Anna de Graaff, Jenny E. Greene, Kasper E. Heintz, Alexander P. Ji, Daichi Kashino, Harley Katz, Ivo Labbe, Joel Leja, Yijia Li, Michael V. Maseda, Johan Richard, Irene Shivaei, Robert A. Simcoe, David Sobral, Katherine A. Suess, Sandro Tacchella, Christina C. Williams
&lt;br&gt;
Dwarf galaxies hold the key to crucial frontiers of astrophysics, however,their faintness renders spectroscopy challenging. Here we present the JWSTCycle 2 survey, All the Little Things (ALT, PID 3516), which is designed toseek late-forming Pop III stars and the drivers of reionization at $z\sim6-7$.ALT has acquired the deepest NIRCam grism spectroscopy yet (7-27 hr), at JWST'smost sensitive wavelengths (3-4 $\mu$m), covering the powerful lensing clusterAbell 2744. Over the same 30 arcmin$^2$, ALT's ultra-deep F070W+F090W imaging($\sim$30 mag) enables selection of very faint sources at $z&gt;6$. We demonstratethe success of ALT's novel ``butterfly" mosaic to solve spectral confusion andcontamination, and introduce the ``Allegro" method for emission lineidentification. By collecting spectra for every source in the field of view,ALT has measured precise ($R\sim1600$) redshifts for 1630 sources at$z=0.2-8.5$. This includes one of the largest samples of distant dwarfgalaxies: [1015, 475, 50] sources less massive than the SMC, Fornax, andSculptor with $\log(M_{*}/M_{\odot})&lt;$[8.5, 7.5, 6.5]. We showcase ALT'sdiscovery space with: (i) spatially resolved spectra of lensed clumps ingalaxies as faint as $M_{\rm{UV}}\sim-15$; (ii) large-scale clustering --overdensities at $z$=[2.50, 2.58, 3.97, 4.30, 5.66, 5.77, 6.33] hosting massivegalaxies with striking Balmer breaks; (iii) small-scale clustering -- a systemof satellites around a Milky Way analog at $z\sim6$; (iv) spectroscopicallyconfirmed multiple images that help constrain the lensing model underlying allscience in this legacy field; (v) sensitive star-formation maps based ondust-insensitive tracers such as Pa$\alpha$; (vi) direct spectroscopicdiscovery of rare sources such as AGN with ionized outflows. These resultsprovide a powerful proof of concept for how grism surveys maximize thepotential of strong lensing fields.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: Submitted to the Open Journal of Astrophysics. Figs. 6 and 10  illustrate the quality of the spectra and imaging, while Fig. 12 summarizes  the yield of the survey. Comments warmly welcomed and greatly appreciated.  The ALT DR1 catalog is available at https://zenodo.org/records/13871850
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.01874v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.01874v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Rohan P. Naidu</author><pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 19:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01874v1</guid></item><item><title>The PANORAMIC Survey: Pure Parallel Wide Area Legacy Imaging with  JWST/NIRCam</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01875v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Christina C. Williams, Pascal A. Oesch, Andrea Weibel, Gabriel Brammer, Aidan P. Cloonan, Katherine E. Whitaker, Laia Barrufet, Rachel Bezanson, Rebecca A. A. Bowler, Pratika Dayal, Marijn Franx, Jenny E. Greene, Anne Hutter, Zhiyuan Ji, Ivo Labbé, Sinclaire M. Manning, Michael V. Maseda, Mengyuan Xiao
&lt;br&gt;
We present the PANORAMIC survey, a pure parallel extragalactic imagingprogram with NIRCam observed during JWST Cycle 1. The survey obtained $\sim$530sq arcmin of NIRCam imaging from 1-5$\mu$m, totaling $\sim$192 hours of scienceintegration time. This represents the largest on-sky time investment of anyCycle 1 GO extragalactic NIRCam imaging program by nearly a factor of 2. Thesurvey includes $\sim$432 sq arcmin of novel sky area not yet observed withJWST using at least $6$ NIRCam broad-band filters, increasing the existing areacovered by similar Cycle 1 data by $\sim$60%. 70 square arcmin was also coveredby a 7th filter (F410M). A fraction of PANORAMIC data ($\sim$200 sq arcmin) wasobtained in or around extragalactic deep-fields, enhancing their legacy value.Pure parallel observing naturally creates a wedding cake survey with both wideand ultra-deep tiers, with 5$\sigma$ point source depths at F444W ranging from27.8-29.4 (ABmag), and with minimized cosmic variance. The 6+ filter observingsetup yields remarkably good photometric redshift performance, achievingsimilar median scatter and outlier fraction as CANDELS ($\sigma_{\rmNMAD}\sim0.07$; $\eta\sim0.2$), which enables a wealth of science acrossredshift without the need for followup or ancillary data. We overview theproposed survey, the data obtained as part of this program, and document thescience-ready data products in the first data release. PANORAMIC has deliveredwide-area and deep imaging with excellent photometric performance,demonstrating that pure parallel observations with JWST are a highly efficientobserving mode that is key to acquiring a complete picture of galaxy evolutionfrom rare bright galaxies to fainter, more abundant sources at all redshifts.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: Submitted to AAS Journals; comments welcome. Initial data release  available at https://panoramic-jwst.github.io/
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.01875v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.01875v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Christina C. Williams</author><pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 19:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01875v1</guid></item><item><title>The Burstiness of Star Formation at $z\sim6$: A Huge Diversity in the  Recent Star Formation Histories of Very UV-faint Galaxies</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01905v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Ryan Endsley, John Chisholm, Daniel P. Stark, Michael W. Topping, Lily Whitler
&lt;br&gt;
IRAC data have long implied that early ($z\gtrsim6$) galaxies often have veryhigh specific star formation rates (sSFR$\gtrsim$30 Gyr$^{-1}$), but JWST datahave shown that at least some early galaxies are forming stars far lessvigorously. Here, we systematically analyze the recent star formation histories(SFHs) of a large ($N=368$) sample of $z\sim6$ Lyman-break galaxies (LBGs)spanning $-22\lesssim M_\mathrm{UV}\lesssim-16$ assembled from ACS+NIRCamimaging in the GOODS and Abell 2744 fields. We find that very lowH$\alpha$-to-UV luminosity ratios ($L_\mathrm{H\alpha}/L_\mathrm{UV}$) andstrong recent downturns in star formation rate (SFR) are $\approx$5$\times$more common among the UV-faintest subset of our sample ($\langleM_\mathrm{UV}\rangle=-17.4$) compared to the brightest subset ($\langleM_\mathrm{UV}\rangle=-20.0$). The frequency of high$L_\mathrm{H\alpha}/L_\mathrm{UV}$ and strong recent SFR upturns isapproximately constant with UV luminosity. We discuss how bursty SFHs naturallyreproduce this much greater diversity in recent SFHs among very UV-faintgalaxies. Using public NIRSpec/prism data, we newly confirm recent strong SFRdownturns among three LBGs in our sample, and validate our photometricinferences on key SFH signatures among $z\sim6$ LBGs in general. Our resultsimply that early galaxies frequently cycle through phases of rapid stellar massassembly and other periods of much slower growth. This yields huge($\gtrsim$1-2 mag) fluctuations in $M_\mathrm{UV}$ on rapid ($\sim$10-30 Myr)timescales, helping explain the surprising abundance of $z&gt;10$ galaxies.Finally, we caution that this burstiness causes all existing high-redshiftsamples (particularly line-selected samples) to be far less complete togalaxies with long recent phases of low sSFR than those currently undergoing aburst.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: Submitted to ApJ. 29 pages, 13 figures, 1 appendix
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.01905v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.01905v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Ryan Endsley</author><pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 19:03:50 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01905v1</guid></item><item><title>The formation histories of massive and quiescent galaxies in the 3 &lt; z &lt;  4.5 Universe</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.02076v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Themiya Nanayakkara, Karl Glazebrook, Corentin Schreiber, Harry Chittenden, Gabriel Brammer, James Esdaile, Colin Jacobs, Glenn G. Kacprzak, Lalitwadee Kawinwanichakij, Lucas C. Kimmig, Ivo Labbe, Claudia Lagos, Danilo Marchesini, M. Martìnez-Marìn, Z. Cemile Marsan, Pascal A. Oesch, Casey Papovich, Rhea-Silvia Remus, Kim-Vy H. Tran
&lt;br&gt;
We present the formation histories of 19 massive($\gtrsim3\times10^{10}\text{M}_\odot$) quiescent galaxy candidates at$z\sim3.0-4.5$ observed using JWST/NIRSpec. This completes the spectroscopicconfirmation of the 24 $K$-selected quiescent galaxy sample from the ZFOURGEand 3DHST surveys \citep{Schreiber2018}. Utilizing Prism $1-5\mu$mspectroscopy, we confirm that all 12 sources that eluded confirmation byground-based spectroscopy lie at $z&gt;3$, resulting in a spectroscopicallyconfirmed number density of $\sim1.4\times10^{-5}\text{Mpc}^{-3}$ between$z\sim3-4$. Rest-frame $U-V$ vs $V-J$ color selections show high effectivenessin identifying quiescent galaxies, with a purity of $\sim90\%$. Our analysisshows that parametric star-formation histories (SFHs) from FAST++ and binnedSFHs from Prospector on average yield consistent results, revealing diverseformation and quenching times. The oldest galaxy formed$\sim6\times10^{10}\text{M}_\odot$ by $z\sim10$ and has been quiescent for over1 Gyr at $z\sim3.2$. We detect two galaxies with ongoing star formation and sixwith active galactic nuclei (AGN). We demonstrate that the choice of stellarpopulation models, stellar libraries, wavelength range, and nebular or AGNcontributions does not significantly affect the derived average SFHs of thegalaxies. The assumed SFH prior, however, influences the star formation rate atearly times, where spectral diagnostic power is limited. Simulated $z\sim3$quiescent galaxies from IllustrisTNG, SHARK, and Magneticum broadly match theaverage SFHs of the observed sample but struggle to capture the full diversity,particularly at early stages. Our results emphasize the need for mechanismsthat rapidly build stellar mass and quench star formation within the firstbillion years of the Universe.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: Submitted to ApJ. Comments welcome
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.02076v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.02076v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Themiya Nanayakkara</author><pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 23:48:06 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.02076v1</guid></item><item><title>Emission-Line Ratios and Ionization Conditions of CEERS Star-Forming  Galaxies with JWST/NIRSpec</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03784v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Ansh R. Gupta, Allison Kirkpatrick, Vital Fernandez, Pablo Arrabal Haro, Bren E. Backhaus, Nikko J. Cleri, Norman A. Grogin, Anton M. Koekemoer
&lt;br&gt;
Galaxy emission-line fluxes can be analyzed to determine star formation rates(SFR) and ISM ionization. Here, we investigate rest-frame optical emissionlines of 71 star-forming galaxies at redshift 0.7 &lt; z &lt; 7 from the CosmicEvolution Early Release Science (CEERS) survey using JWST/NIRSpec. We useH${\alpha}$ line fluxes to measure SFRs. We combine these with HST CANDELSstellar mass estimates to determine the redshift evolution of specific SFR(sSFR) and compare our sample with the star-forming galaxy main sequence. Wecreate [O III]${\lambda}$5008/H${\beta}$ versus [Ne III]${\lambda}$3870/[OII]${\lambda}$3728 line ratio diagrams and correlate these ratios with sSFR andthe distance of each galaxy from the main sequence (excess sSFR). We find amodest correlation between the line ratios and sSFR, which is consistent withprevious work analyzing similar samples. However, we find a weak correlationbetween the line ratios and excess sSFR. Taken together, our results suggestthat sSFR is the parameter that governs ionization conditions rather than SFRor a galaxy's distance from the main sequence. These measurements reveal a richdiversity of ISM conditions and physical galaxy properties throughout cosmictime.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 6 pages, 1 figure. Submitted to Research Notes of the American  Astronomical Society
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.03784v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.03784v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Ansh R. Gupta</author><pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 19:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03784v1</guid></item><item><title>The Stellar Initial Mass Function of Early Dark Matter-free Gas Objects</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.02868v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
William Lake, Michael Y. Grudić, Smadar Naoz, Naoki Yoshida, Claire E. Williams, Blakesley Burkhart, Federico Marinacci, Mark Vogelsberger, Avi Chen
&lt;br&gt;
To date, JWST has detected the earliest known star clusters in our Universe(Adamo et al. 2024, Messa et al. 2024, Vanzella et al. 2024, Mowla et al.2024). They appear to be relatively compact (~few pc, Adamo et al. 2024) andhad only recently formed their stars. It was speculated that these clusters maybe the earliest progenitors of globular clusters ever detected. Globularclusters are a relic of the initial stages of star formation in the Universe.However, because they contain little to no dark matter (e.g., Heggie &amp; Hut1996, Bradford et al. 2011, Conroy et al. 2011, Ibata et al. 2013), theirformation mechanism poses a significant theoretical challenge. A recentsuggestion pointed out that the relative velocity between the gas and the darkmatter (Tseliakhovich &amp; Hirata 2010) in the early Universe could naturally formpotentially star-forming regions outside of dark matter halos. Here, for thefirst time, we follow the star formation process of these early Universeobjects using high-resolution hydrodynamical simulations, including mechanicalfeedback. Our results suggest that the first dark matter-less star clusters aretop-heavy, with a higher abundance of massive stars compared to today'sclusters and extremely high stellar mass surface densities compared to thelocal Universe.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 10 pages, 5 figures
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.02868v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.02868v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>William Lake</author><pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 19:01:18 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.02868v1</guid></item><item><title>A negligible contribution of two luminous $z$ ~ 7.5 galaxies to the  ionizing photon budget of reionization</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03337v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
S. Gazagnes, J. Chisholm, Ryan Endsley, D. A. Berg, F. Leclercq, N. Jurlin, A. Saldana-Lopez, S. L. Finkelstein, S. R. Flury, N. G. Guseva, A. Henry, Y. I. Izotov, I. Jung, J. Matthee, D. Schaerer
&lt;br&gt;
We present indirect constraints on the absolute escape fraction of ionizingphotons ($f_{\rm esc}^{\rm LyC}$) of the system GN 42912 which comprises twoluminous galaxies ($M_{\rm UV}$ magnitudes of -20.89 and -20.37) at $z\sim7.5$,GN 42912-NE and GN 42912-SW, to determine their contribution to the ionizingphoton budget of the Epoch of Reionization (EoR). The high-resolution JamesWebb Space Telescope NIRSpec and NIRCam observations reveal the two galaxiesare separated by only ~0.1$"$ (0.5 kpc) on the sky and have a 358 km s$^{-1}$velocity separation. GN 42912-NE and GN 42912-SW are relatively massive forthis redshift (log($M_\ast/M_\odot$) $\sim$ 8.4 and 8.9, respectively), withgas-phase metallicities of 18 per cent and 23 per cent solar, O$_{32}$ ratiosof 5.3 and $&gt;5.8$, and $\beta$ slopes of $-1.92$ and $-1.51$, respectively. Weuse the Mg II$\lambda\lambda$2796,2803 doublet to constrain $f_{\rm esc}^{\rmLyC}$. Mg II has an ionization potential close to that of neutral hydrogen and,in the optically thin regime, can be used as an indirect tracer of the LyCleakage. We establish realistic conservative upper limits on $f_{\rm esc}^{\rmLyC}$ of 8.5 per cent for GN 42912-NE and 14 per cent for GN 42912-SW. Theseestimates align with $f_{\rm esc}^{\rm LyC}$ trends observed with $\beta$,O$_{32}$, and the H$\beta$ equivalent width at $z&lt;4$. The small inferredionized region sizes ($&lt;0.3$ pMpc) around both galaxies indicate they have notionized a significant fraction of the surrounding neutral gas. While these$z&gt;7$ $f_{\rm esc}^{\rm LyC}$ constraints do not decisively determine aspecific reionization model, they support a minor contribution from these tworelatively luminous galaxies to the EoR.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 18 pages, submitted to MNRAS
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.03337v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.03337v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>S. Gazagnes</author><pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 12:47:51 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03337v1</guid></item><item><title>JWST/NIRCam Narrowband Survey of Pa$β$ Emitters in the Spiderweb  Protocluster at z=2.16</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03362v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Rhythm Shimakawa, J. M. Perez-Martinez, Helmut Dannerbauer, Yusei Koyama, Tadayuki Kodama, Pablo G. Perez-Gonzalez, Chiara D'Eugenio, Yuheng Zhang, Abdurrahman Naufal, Kazuki Daikuhara
&lt;br&gt;
We report the initial result of our Pa$\beta$ narrowband imaging on aprotocluster with the JWST Near Infrared Camera (NIRCam). As NIRCam enablesdeep narrowband imaging of rest-frame NIR lines at $z&gt;1$, we target one of themost studied protoclusters, the Spiderweb protocluster at $z=2.16$, in whichprevious studies have confirmed more than a hundred member galaxies. The NIRCamF405N narrowband filter covers in Pa$\beta$ line the protocluster redshiftgiven by known protocluster members, allowing the search for new membercandidates. The weight-corrected color-magnitude diagram obtained 57 sourcesshowing narrowband excesses, 41 of which satisfy further color selectioncriteria for limiting the sample to Pa$\beta$ emitter candidates at$z\sim2.16$, and 24 of them do not have H$\alpha$ emitter counterparts. ThePa$\beta$ emitter candidates appear to follow the spatial distribution of knownprotocluster members; however, follow-up spectroscopic confirmation isrequired. Only 17 out of 58 known H$\alpha$-emitting cluster members areselected as Pa$\beta$ emitters in the current data, albeit the rest fall out ofthe narrowband selection owing to their small Pa$\beta$ equivalent widths. Wederive Pa$\beta$ luminosity function in the Spiderweb protocluster, showing anormalization density of $\log{\phi^\ast}=-2.53\pm0.15$ at a characteristicPa$\beta$ luminosity of $\log{L^\ast}=42.33\pm0.17$. Furthermore, we examinethe possibility of detecting faint line emitters visible only in thenarrow-band image, but find no promising candidates.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 19 pages, 12 figures, 2 tables; Accepted for publication in ApJ
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.03362v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.03362v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Rhythm Shimakawa</author><pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 13:30:01 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03362v1</guid></item><item><title>JWST/NIRCam Pa$\mathrmβ$ narrow-band imaging reveals ordinary dust  extinction for H$\mathrmα$ emitters within the Spiderweb protocluster  at z=2.16</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03366v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Jose Manuel Pérez-Martínez, Helmut Dannerbauer, Yusei Koyama, Pablo G. Pérez-González, Rhythm Shimakawa, Tadayuki Kodama, Yuheng Zhang, Kazuki Daikuhara, Chiara D'Eugenio, Abdurrahman Naufal
&lt;br&gt;
We combine JWST/NIRCam and Subaru/MOIRCS dual Pa$\mathrm{\beta}$ +H$\mathrm{\alpha}$ narrow-band imaging to trace the dust attenuation and thestar-formation activities of a sample of 43 H$\mathrm{\alpha}$ emitters at thecore of one of the most massive and best-studied clusters in formation at thecosmic noon: the Spiderweb protocluster at $\mathrm{z=2.16}$. We find that mostH$\mathrm{\alpha}$ emitters display Pa$\mathrm{\beta}$/H$\mathrm{\alpha}$ratios compatible with Case B recombination conditions, which translates intonebular extinction values ranging at $\mathrm{A_V\approx0-3}$ magnitudes, anddust corrected $\mathrm{Pa\beta}$ star formation rates consistent with coevalmain sequence field galaxies at fixed stellar mass ($\mathrm{9.4&lt;\logM_*/M_\odot&lt;11.0}$) during this cosmic epoch. Furthermore, we investigatepossible environmental impacts on dust extinction across the protoclusterlarge-scale structure and find no correlation between the dustiness of itsmembers and environmental proxies such as phase-space position, clustercentricradius, or local density. These results support the scenario for which dustproduction within the main galaxy population of this protocluster is driven bysecular star formation activities fueled by smooth gas accretion across itslarge-scale structure. This downplays the role of gravitational interactions inboosting star formation and dust production within the Spiderweb protocluster,in contrast with observations in higher redshift and less evolved protoclustercores.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 21 pages, 8 figures. Accepted for publication in ApJ
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.03366v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.03366v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Jose Manuel Pérez-Martínez</author><pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 13:31:14 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03366v1</guid></item><item><title>Connecting the growth of galaxies to the large-scale environment in a  massive node of the Cosmic Web at z~3</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03822v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
M. Galbiati, S. Cantalupo, C. Steidel, A. Pensabene, A. Travascio, W. Wang, M. Fossati, M. Fumagalli, G. Rudie, A. Fresco, T. Lazeyras, N. Ledos, G. Quadri
&lt;br&gt;
A direct link between large-scale environment and galaxy properties is verywell established in the local universe. However, very little is known about therole of the environment for galaxy growth before the peak of the cosmic starformation history at $z&gt;3$ due to the rarity of high-redshift, overdensestructures. Using a combination of deep, multiwalength observations, includingMUSE, JWST, Chandra, HST and ground-based imaging, we detect and study theproperties of a population of star-forming galaxies in the field of ahyperluminous quasar at $z\approx3.25$ associated with the giant Ly$\alpha$nebula MQN01. We find that this region hosts one of the largest overdensity ofgalaxies found so far at $z&gt;3$, with $\rho/\bar{\rho}=53\pm17$ within$4\times4\rm\,cMpc^2$ and $|\Delta v|&lt;1000\rm\,km\,s^{-1}$ from the quasar,providing a unique laboratory to study the link between overdense regions andgalaxy properties at high redshift. Even in these rare overdense regions,galaxies are forming stars at a rate consistent with the main sequence at$z\approx3$, demonstrating that their SFR is regulated by local propertiescorrelated with their stellar mass rather than by their environment. However,the high-mass-end of the stellar mass function is significantly elevated withrespect to that of galaxies in the field at$\log(M_\star/{M_\odot})\gtrsim10.5$, suggesting that massive galaxies inoverdense regions build-up their stellar mass earlier or more efficiently thanin average regions of the universe. Finally, the overdensity of color-selectedLyman break galaxies observed on larger scales, across$\approx24\times24\rm\,cMpc^2$, is found to be aligned toward the structuretraced by the spectroscopically-confirmed galaxies identified with MUSE in theinner $4\times4\rm\,cMpc^2$, suggesting that this highly overdense region couldfurther extend up to a few tens of comoving Mpc.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 20 pages, 14 figures. Submitted to A&amp;A
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.03822v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.03822v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>M. Galbiati</author><pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 19:00:02 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03822v1</guid></item><item><title>A Quasar-Anchored Protocluster at z=6.6 in the ASPIRE Survey: I.  Properties of [OIII] Emitters in a 10 Mpc Overdensity Structure</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03826v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Jaclyn B. Champagne, Feige Wang, Haowen Zhang, Jinyi Yang, Xiaohui Fan, Joseph F. Hennawi, Fengwu Sun, Eduardo Bañados, Sarah E. I. Bosman, Tiago Costa, Anna-Christina Eilers, Ryan Endsley, Xiangyu Jin, Hyunsung D. Jun, Mingyu Li, Xiaojing Lin, Weizhe Liu, Federica Loiacono, Alessandro Lupi, Chiara Mazzucchelli, Maria Pudoka, Klaudia Protušovà, Sofia Rojas-Ruiz, Wei Leong Tee, Maxime Trebitsch, Bram P. Venemans, Ming-Yang Zhuang, Siwei Zou
&lt;br&gt;
ASPIRE (A SPectroscopic survey of bIased halos in the Reionization Era) is aquasar legacy survey primarily using JWST to target a sample of 25 $z&gt;6$quasars with NIRCam slitless spectroscopy and imaging. The first study in thisseries found evidence of a strong overdensity of galaxies around J0305-3150, aluminous quasar at $z=6.61$, within a single NIRCam pointing obtained in JWSTCycle 1. Here, we present the first results of a JWST Cycle 2 mosaic thatcovers 35 arcmin$^2$ with NIRCam imaging/WFSS of the same field to investigatethe spatial extent of the putative protocluster. The F356W grism data targets[OIII]+H$\beta$ at $5.3&lt;z&lt;7$ and reveals a population of 124 line emitters downto a flux limit of 1.2$\times$10$^{-18}$ erg s$^{-1}$ cm$^{-2}$. Fifty-three ofthese galaxies lie at $6.5&lt;z&lt;6.8$ spanning 10 cMpc on the sky, corresponding toan overdensity within a 2500 cMpc$^3$ volume of 12.5 $\pm$ 2.6, anchored by thequasar. Comparing to the [OIII] luminosity function from the Emission linegalaxies and Intergalactic Gas in the Epoch of Reionization (EIGER) project, wefind a dearth of faint [OIII] emitters at log(L/erg s$^{-1}$) $&lt;$ 42.3, whichwe suggest is consistent with either bursty star formation causing galaxies toscatter around the grism detection limit or modest suppression from quasarfeedback. While we find a strong filamentary overdensity of [OIII] emittersconsistent with a protocluster, we suggest that we could be insensitive to apopulation of older, more massive Lyman-break galaxies with weak nebularemission on scales $&gt;10$ cMpc.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: submitted to ApJ june 2024. 18 pages, 7 figures. companion paper II  by Champagne+24b is also available on arXiv today
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.03826v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.03826v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Jaclyn B. Champagne</author><pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 19:00:07 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03826v1</guid></item><item><title>A Quasar-Anchored Protocluster at z=6.6 in the ASPIRE Survey: II. An  Environmental Analysis of Galaxy Properties in an Overdense Structure</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03827v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Jaclyn B. Champagne, Feige Wang, Jinyi Yang, Xiaohui Fan, Joseph F. Hennawi, Fengwu Sun, Eduardo Bañados, Sarah E. I. Bosman, Tiago Costa, Melanie Habouzit, Xiangyu Jin, Hyunsung D. Jun, Mingyu Li, Weizhe Liu, Federica Loiacono, Alessandro Lupi, Chiara Mazzucchelli, Maria Pudoka, Sofia Rojas-Ruiz, Wei Leong Tee, Maxime Trebitsch, Haowen Zhang, Ming-Yang Zhuang, Siwei Zou
&lt;br&gt;
We present paper II comprising a 35 arcmin$^2$ JWST/NIRCam imaging andwide-field slitless spectroscopy mosaic centered on J0305$-$3150, a luminousquasar at $z=6.61$. The F356W grism data reveals 124 [OIII]+H$\beta$ emittersat $5.3&lt;z&lt;7$, 53 of which constitute a protocluster spanning (10 cMpc)$^2$across $6.5&lt;z&lt;6.8$. We find no evidence of any broad-line AGN in individualgalaxies or stacking, reporting a median H$\beta$ FWHM of 585 $\pm$ 152 kms$^{-1}$; however, the mass-excitation diagram and ``little red dot" color andcompactness criteria suggest that there are a few AGN candidates on theoutskirts of the protocluster. We fit the spectral energy distributions (SEDs)of the [OIII] emitters with Prospector and Bagpipes, and find that none of theSED-derived properties (stellar mass, age, or star formation rate) correlateswith proximity to the quasar. While there is no correlation between galaxy ageand local galaxy density, we find modest correlations between local galaxydensity with increasing stellar mass, decreasing 10-to-100 Myr star formationrate ratios and decreasing nebular line equivalent widths. We further find thatthe protocluster galaxies are consistent with being more massive, older, andhosting higher star formation rates than the field sample at the 3$\sigma$level, distributed in a filamentary structure which supports inside-outformation of the protocluster. There is modest evidence that galaxy evolutionproceeds differently as a function of the density of local environment withinprotoclusters during the epoch of reionization, and the central quasar haslittle effect on the galaxy properties of the surrounding structure.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: accepted to ApJ. 24 pages, 13 figures. Paper I by Champagne+24a is  also available on arxiv today
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.03827v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.03827v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Jaclyn B. Champagne</author><pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 19:00:09 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03827v1</guid></item><item><title>Suppressed accretion onto massive black hole binaries surrounded by thin  disks</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03830v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Christopher Tiede, Jonathan Zrake, Andrew MacFadyen, Zoltan Haiman
&lt;br&gt;
We demonstrate that gas disks around binary systems might deliver gas to thebinary components only when the circumbinary disk is relatively warm. Wepresent new grid-based hydrodynamics simulations, performed with the binary onthe grid and a locally isothermal equation of state, in which the binary isseen to functionally ``stop accreting'' if the orbital Mach number in the diskexceeds a threshold value of about 40. Above this threshold, the disk continuesto extract angular momentum from the binary orbit, but it delivers very littlemass to the black holes, and instead piles up mass in a ring surrounding thebinary. This ring will eventually become viscously relaxed and deliver mass tothe binary at the large-scale inflow rate. However we show that the timescalefor such relaxation can far exceed the implied binary lifetime. We demonstratethat the ability of a binary-disk system to equilibrate is dependent on theefficiency at which accretion streams deposit mass onto the binary; which inturn is highly sensitive to the thermodynamic conditions of the inner disk. Ifdisks around massive black hole binaries do operate in such non-accretingregimes, it suggests these systems may be dimmer than their single black holecounterparts, but could exhibit dramatic re-brightening after the black holesin-spiral and merge. This dimming occurs at high photon energies, correspondingto the effective truncation of the circumbinary disk. As a result, such systemmay be underluminous in UV bands and missing X-ray emission entirely,potentially resembling the spectra of `Little Red Dots'' recently identified inJWST observations.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 9 pages and 4 figures
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.03830v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.03830v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Christopher Tiede</author><pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 19:00:52 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03830v1</guid></item><item><title>Star formation in cosmic-dawn galaxies</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04227v2</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Sandro Tacchella
&lt;br&gt;
In the first two years of operation JWST has delivered key new insights intothe formation and evolution of galaxies in the early Universe. By combiningimaging with spectroscopy, we discovered and characterised the first generationof galaxies, probing the Universe at an age of 300 million years. While thecurrent JWST observations confirm the overall cosmological framework and theparadigm of galaxy formation, there are also surprises, including largeabundances of bright galaxies and accreting black holes in the early Universe.These observations, together with detailed measurements of the stellarpopulations and morphological structure, will help us to develop in the comingyears a more refined understanding of the baryonic physics (including starformation and feedback processes) that leads to the formation of mature systemsat later epochs, including our own Milky Way galaxy.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: To be published in "Astrophysics: The James Webb Space Telescope:  from first light to new world views", proceedings of the Pontifical Academy  of Sciences workshop February 27-29 2024, Vatican City, E.F. van Dishoeck and  G. Consolmagno (eds)
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.04227v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.04227v2 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Sandro Tacchella</author><pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2024 17:56:09 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04227v2</guid></item><item><title>Age-dating early quiescent galaxies: high star-formation efficiency, but  consistent with direct, higher-redshift observations</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05377v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Crispin Turner, Sandro Tacchella, Francesco D'Eugenio, Stefano Carniani, Mirko Curti, Karl Glazebrook, Benjamin D. Johnson, Seunghwan Lim, Tobias Looser, Roberto Maiolino, Themiya Nanayakkara, Jenny T. Wan
&lt;br&gt;
We present a detailed analysis of JWST/NIRSpec and NIRCam observations ofZF-UDS-7329, a massive, quiescent galaxy at redshift $z=3.2$, which has beenput forward to challenge cosmology and galaxy formation physics. Our studyextends previous works by focusing on the impact of different star formationhistory (SFH) priors, stellar libraries, metallicity, and initial mass functionassumptions. Our results show that ZF-UDS-7329, with a formed stellar mass of$M_{\star} \approx 10^{11.4}~M_{\odot}$ and a specific star formation rate of$\mathrm{sSFR} \approx 0.03$ Gyr$^{-1}$, formed efficiently in the firstbillion years of the Universe. In agreement with previous work, we find thatthe spectrum is consistent with mass-weighted stellar ages of $1.3-1.8$ Gyr,depending on the SFH prior used. A physically motivated rising SFH prior makesthe formation history of ZF-UDS-7329 compatible with stellar mass andstar-formation rate estimates of high-redshift ($z&gt;6$) galaxies. Using NIRCamimaging, we identify a colour gradient indicative of an old, quiescent bulgeand a younger disc component, as expected from a complex formation history. Theinferred SFH is consistent a high stellar fraction of $f_{\star}=M_{\star}/(f_b\cdot M_{\rm h}) \approx 100\%$ at $z=7-12$, implying an extremely highintegrated star-formation efficiency. However, when considering cosmic varianceand possible mergers as expected in over-dense environments - as traced byZF-UDS-7329 - the stellar fractions could be reduced to $f_{\star} \approx50\%$, which is more consistent with galaxy formation models and thestellar-to-halo mass relation at lower redshifts. We conclude that ZF-UDS-7329forms extremely efficient in the early universe, but does not necessitateunseen galaxies at higher redshifts since the inferred SFR of ancestors areconsistent with those seen in $z&gt;6$ galaxies.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 15 pages and 8 figures (+appendix), submitted to MNRAS
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.05377v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.05377v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Crispin Turner</author><pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 19:00:01 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05377v1</guid></item><item><title>Polycyclic Aromatic Hydrocarbon and CO(2-1) Emission at 50-150 pc Scales  in 66 Nearby Galaxies</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05397v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Ryan Chown, Adam K. Leroy, Karin Sandstrom, Jeremy Chastenet, Jessica Sutter, Eric W. Koch, Hannah B. Koziol, Lukas Neumann, Jiayi Sun, Thomas G. Williams, Dalya Baron, Gagandeep S. Anand, Ashley T. Barnes, Zein Bazzi, Francesco Belfiore, Alberto Bolatto, Mederic Boquien, Yixian Cao, Melanie Chevance, Dario Colombo, Daniel A. Dale, Oleg V. Egorov, Cosima Eibensteiner, Eric Emsellem, Hamid Hassani, Jonathan D. Henshaw, Hao He, Jaeyeon Kim, Kathryn Kreckel, Sharon E. Meidt, Eric J. Murphy, Elias K. Oakes, Eve C. Ostriker, Hsi-An Pan, Debosmita Pathak, Erik Rosolowsky, Sumit K. Sarbadhicary, Eva Schinnerer, Yu-Hsuan Teng
&lt;br&gt;
Combining Atacama Large Millimeter/sub-millimeter Array CO(2-1) mapping andJWST near- and mid-infrared imaging, we characterize the relationship betweenCO(2-1) and polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon (PAH) emission at ~100 pcresolution in 66 nearby star-forming galaxies, expanding the sample size fromprevious ~100 pc resolution studies by more than an order of magnitude.Focusing on regions of galaxies where most of the gas is likely to bemolecular, we find strong correlations between CO(2-1) and 3.3 micron, 7.7micron, and 11.3 micron PAH emission, estimated from JWST's F335M, F770W, andF1130W filters. We derive power law relations between CO(2-1) and PAH emission,which have indices in the range 0.8-1.2, implying relatively weak variations inthe observed CO-to-PAH ratios across the regions that we study. We find thatCO-to-PAH ratios and scaling relationships near HII regions are similar tothose in diffuse sight lines. The main difference between the two types ofregions is that sight lines near HII regions show higher intensities in alltracers. Galaxy centers, on the other hand, show higher overall intensities andenhanced CO-to-PAH ratios compared to galaxy disks. Individual galaxies show0.19 dex scatter in the normalization of CO at fixed I_PAH and thisnormalization anti-correlates with specific star formation rate (SFR/M*) andcorrelates with stellar mass. We provide a prescription that accounts for thesegalaxy-to-galaxy variations and represents our best current empirical predictorto estimate CO(2-1) intensity from PAH emission, which allows one to takeadvantage of JWST's excellent sensitivity and resolution to trace cold gas.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 21 pages, 4 figures, 3 tables. Submitted to ApJ
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.05397v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.05397v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Ryan Chown</author><pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 19:02:21 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05397v1</guid></item><item><title>Supermassive primordial black holes for the GHZ9 and UHZ1 observed by  the JWST</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05891v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Hai-Long Huang, Yu-Tong Wang, Yun-Song Piao
&lt;br&gt;
The high redshift ($z&gt;10$) galaxies GHZ9 and UHZ1 observed by the James WebbSpace Telescope (JWST) are very massive and have exceptionally high blackhole-to-star mass ratios with the central black hole masses $M\gtrsim10^7\rm~M_\odot$. In this paper, we explore the possibility that they areseeded by the supermassive primordial black holes (SMPBHs), which came intobeing in the very early universe, with initial masses $\sim 10^7\rm~M_\odot$.We present the self-similar accretion solutions for SMPBHs, and find that themass growth of SMPBHs during pregalactic era may be negligible. These SMPBHs,when the redshift $z\lesssim 20$, can accelerate seeding high-redshift galaxiesand their baryonic content, and consequently explain the central supermassiveblack holes (SMBHs) of high-redshift massive galaxies through sub-Eddingtonaccretion. According to our results, SMPBHs actually could lead to theexistence of more massive SMBHs at higher redshifts compared to other SMBH seedscenarios, specially SMBHs with masses $M\gtrsim 10^7~\rm M_\odot$ at $z&gt;20$might only origin from SMPBHs, thus the corresponding observation can serve asa potential probe to PBHs.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 14 pages, 5 figures
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.05891v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.05891v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Hai-Long Huang</author><pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 11:34:13 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05891v1</guid></item><item><title>Magnetic Fields Under Feedback: A Case Study of the Massive Star-Forming  Hub G34.26+0.15</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06178v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Zacariyya A. Khan, Kate Pattle, Sarah F. Graves
&lt;br&gt;
We present 850$\mu$m polarized observations of the molecular cloudG34.26+0.15 taken using the POL-2 polarimeter mounted on the James ClerkMaxwell Telescope (JCMT). G34.26+0.15 is a hub-filament system with ongoinghigh-mass star-formation, containing multiple HII regions. We extend theHistogram of Relative Orientations technique with an alternative applicationthat considers the alignment of the magnetic field to the filaments and a HIIregion boundary, denoted as the filament alignment factor ($\xi_{F}$) and theellipse alignment factor ($\xi_{E}$) respectively. Using these metrics, we findthat, although in general the magnetic field aligns parallel to the filamentarystructure within the system in the north-west, the magnetic field structure ofG34.26+0.15 has been radically reshaped by the expansion of an evolved HIIregion in the south-east, which itself may have triggered further high-massstar formation in the cloud. Thus, we suggest high-mass star formation is bothoccurring through mass accretion as per the hub-filament model from one side,and through compression of gas under stellar feedback from the other. We alsouse HARP observations of C$^{18}$O from the CHIMPS survey to estimate themagnetic field strength across the cloud, finding strengths of $\sim$0.5-1.4mG.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 16 pages, 15 figures, 1 table, accepted for publication in MNRAS
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.06178v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.06178v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Zacariyya A. Khan</author><pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 17:29:51 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06178v1</guid></item><item><title>Force-feeding Supermassive Black Holes with Dissipative Dark Matter</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06252v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Matthew R. Buckley, Nicolas Fernandez
&lt;br&gt;
Supermassive black holes with masses $\gtrsim 10^9\,M_\odot$ have beendiscovered by JWST at high redshifts ($z\sim 7$). It is difficult to explainsuch objects as the result of accretive growth of stellar-mass seeds, as therate at which baryons can be fed to the black hole is limited by the radiationpressure of the infalling matter. In this paper, we propose a new mechanism tocreate the early progenitors: the collapse of small dark matter halos through adissipative cooling mechanism in the dark sector. These small black holes canthen be efficiently fed with additional dissipative dark matter due to thecomparatively weak interactions between the dark radiation and dark matter,which results in a very short Eddington time and high accretion rates.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 11 pages, 3 figures
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.06252v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.06252v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Matthew R. Buckley</author><pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 19:00:01 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06252v1</guid></item><item><title>UNCOVER: 404 Error -- Models Not Found for the Triply Imaged Little Red  Dot A2744-QSO1</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06257v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Yilun Ma, Jenny E. Greene, David J. Setton, Marta Volonteri, Joel Leja, Bingjie Wang, Rachel Bezanson, Gabriel Brammer, Sam E. Cutler, Pratika Dayal, Pieter van Dokkum, Lukas J. Furtak, Karl Glazebrook, Andy D. Goulding, Anna de Graaff, Vasily Kokorev, Ivo Labbe, Richard Pan, Sedona H. Price, John R. Weaver, Christina C. Williams, Katherine E. Whitaker, Adi Zitrin
&lt;br&gt;
JWST has revealed an abundance of compact, red objects at $z\approx5-8$dubbed "little red dots" (LRDs), whose SEDs display a faint blue UV continuumfollowed by a steep rise in the optical. Despite extensive study of theircharacteristic V-shaped SEDs, the nature of LRDs remains unknown. We present anew analysis of the NIRSpec/PRISM spectrum of A2744-QSO1, a triply imaged LRDat $z=7.04$ from the UNCOVER survey. The spectrum shows a strong Balmer breakand broad Balmer emission lines, both of which are difficult to explain withmodels invoking exclusively AGN or stellar contributions. Our fiducial modeldecomposes the spectrum into a post-starburst galaxy dominating the UV-opticalcontinuum and a reddened AGN being sub-dominant at all wavelength andcontributing at $\sim20\%$ level. However, our most credible model infers astellar mass of $M_\star\approx 4\times10^9\,\mathrm{M_\odot}$ within a radiusof $r_\mathrm{e}&lt;30\,$pc, driving its central density to the highest amongobservations to date. This high central density could be explained ifA2744-QSO-1 is the early-forming core of a modern-day massive elliptical galaxythat later puffed up via the inside-out growth channel. The models alsonecessitate an unusually steep dust law to preserve the strong break strength,though this steepness may be explained by a deficit of large dust grains. It isalso probable that these challenges reflect our ignorance of A2744-QSO1's truenature. Future variability and reverberation mapping studies could helpdisentangle the galaxy and AGN contribution to the continuum, and deeper redderobservations could also unveil the dust properties in LRDs.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 19 pages, 7 figures, 2 tables. Submitted to ApJ. Comments are welcome
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.06257v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.06257v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Yilun Ma</author><pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 19:00:05 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06257v1</guid></item><item><title>JWST-IPA: Chemical Inventory and Spatial Mapping of Ices in the  Protostar HOPS370 -- Evidence for an Opacity Hole and Thermal Processing of  Ices</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06697v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Himanshu Tyagi, Manoj P., Mayank Narang, S T. Megeath, Will Robson M. Rocha, Nashanty Brunken, Adam E. Rubinstein, Robert A. Gutermuth, Neal J. Evans, Ewine van Dishoeck, Sam Federman, Dan M. Watson, David A. Neufeld, Guillem Anglada, Henrik Beuther, Alessio Caratti o Garatti, Leslie W. Looney, Pooneh Nazari, Mayra Osorio, Thomas Stanke, Yao-Lun Yang, Tyler L. Bourke, William J. Fischer, Elise Furlan, Joel D. Green, Nolan Habel, Pamela Klaassen, Nicole Karnath, Hendrik Linz, James Muzzerolle, John J. Tobin, Prabhani Atnagulov, Rohan Rahatgaonkar, Patrick D. Sheehan, Katerina Slavicinska, Amelia M. Stutz, Łukasz Tychoniec, Scott J. Wolk
&lt;br&gt;
The composition of protoplanetary disks, and hence the initial conditions ofplanet formation, may be strongly influenced by the infall and thermalprocessing of material during the protostellar phase. Composition of dust andice in protostellar envelopes, shaped by energetic processes driven by theprotostar, serves as the fundamental building material for planets and complexorganic molecules. As part of the JWST GO program, "Investigating ProtostellarAccretion" (IPA), we observed an intermediate-mass protostar HOPS 370(OMC2-FIR3) using NIRSpec/IFU and MIRI/MRS. This study presents the gas and icephase chemical inventory revealed with the JWST in the spectral range of$\sim$2.9 to 28 $\mu$m and explores the spatial variation of volatile icespecies in the protostellar envelope. We find evidence for thermal processingof ice species throughout the inner envelope. We present the first high-spatialresolution ($\sim 80$ au) maps of key volatile ice species H$_{2}$O, CO$_{2}$,$^{13}$CO$_2$, CO, and OCN$^-$, which reveal a highly structured andinhomogeneous density distribution of the protostellar envelope, with adeficiency of ice column density that coincides with the jet/outflow shockedknots. Further, we observe high relative crystallinity of H$_{2}$O ice aroundthe shocked knot seen in the H$_2$ and OH wind/outflow, which can be explainedby a lack of outer colder material in the envelope along the line of sight dueto the irregular structure of the envelope. These observations show clearevidence of thermal processing of the ices in the inner envelope, close to theoutflow cavity walls, heated by the luminous protostar.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: Submitted to ApJ. Main text:16 pages with 11 figures
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.06697v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.06697v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Himanshu Tyagi</author><pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 10:05:14 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06697v1</guid></item><item><title>Blowing star formation away in AGN Hosts (BAH) -- II. Investigating the  origin of the H2 emission excess in nearby galaxies with JWST MIRI</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06960v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Rogemar A. Riffel, Gabriel L. Souza-Oliveira, José Henrique Costa-Souza, Nadia L. Zakamska, Thaisa Storchi-Bergmann, Rogério Riffel
&lt;br&gt;
We use James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) Mid-Infrared Instrument (MIRI)medium-resolution spectrometer (MRS) observations of UGC 8782, CGCG 012-070 andNGC 3884 to investigate the origin of the H$_2$ emission. These three nearbyAGN hosts are known to present H$_2$ emission excess relative to star-forminggalaxies, as traced by the H$_2$ S(3)/PAH$_{\rm 11.3\mu m}$ line ratio. Forevery spaxel, we also measure the velocity width ($W_{\rm 80}$) of H$_2$ S(3).We find that the distribution of H$_2$ in the space of these parameters -H$_2$/PAH and its velocity width - is bimodal: one cluster of points showsapproximately constant values of $W_{\rm 80}$, while the other cluster exhibitsa strong correlation between $W_{\rm 80}$ and H$_2$/PAH. We estimated thetemperature of the H$_2$ gas assuming a power-law distribution and find flatterdistributions in regions where a correlation between $W_{\rm 80}$ and H$_2$S(3)/PAH$_{\rm 11.3\mu m}$ is observed. Additionally, we observed a correlationbetween the [Fe II]$_{\rm 5.34 \mu m}$ (a known shock tracer) and the H$_2$emission. This indicates that the excess H$_2$ emission excess is associated toshock heating of the gas, generated by outflows or by the interaction of theradio jet with the ambient gas.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 12 pages, 5 figures, submitted to ApJ. Comments are welcome
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.06960v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.06960v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Rogemar A. Riffel</author><pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 15:57:19 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06960v1</guid></item><item><title>Here There Be (Dusty) Monsters: High Redshift AGN are Dustier Than Their  Hosts</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07340v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Madisyn Brooks, Raymond C. Simons, Jonathan R. Trump, Anthony J. Taylor, Bren Backhaus, Kelcey Davis, Véronique Buat, Nikko J. Cleri, Steven L. Finkelstein, Michaela Hirschmann, Benne W. Holwerda, Dale D. Kocevski, Anton M. Koekemoer, Ray A. Lucas, Fabio Pacucci, Lise-Marie Seillé
&lt;br&gt;
JWST spectroscopy has discovered a population of $z \gtrsim 3.5$ galaxieswith broad Balmer emission lines, and narrow forbidden lines, that areconsistent with hosting active galactic nuclei (AGN). Many of these systems,now known as ``little red dots" (LRDs), are compact and have unique colors thatare very red in the optical/near-infrared and blue in the ultraviolet. Therelative contribution of galaxy starlight and AGN to these systems remainsuncertain, especially for the galaxies with unusual blue+red spectral energydistributions. In this work, we use Balmer decrements to measure theindependent dust attenuation of the broad and narrow emission-line componentsof a sample of 29 broad-line AGN identified from three public JWST spectroscopysurveys: CEERS, JADES, and RUBIES. Stacking the narrow components from thespectra of 25 sources with broad H$\rm{\alpha}$ and no broad H$\rm{\beta}$results in a median narrow H$\rm{\alpha}$/H$\rm{\beta}$ =$2.47^{+0.05}_{-0.05}$ (consistent with $A_{v} = 0$) and broadH$\rm{\alpha}$/H$\rm{\beta}$ $&gt; 8.85$ ($A_{v} &gt; 3.63$). The narrow and broadBalmer decrements imply little-to-no attenuation of the narrow emission lines,which are consistent with being powered by star formation and located on largerphysical scales. Meanwhile, the lower limit in broadH$\rm{\alpha}$/H$\rm{\beta}$ decrement, with broad H$\rm{\beta}$ undetected inthe stacked spectrum of 25 broad-H$\rm{\alpha}$ AGN, implies significant dustattenuation of the broad-line emitting region that is presumably associatedwith the central AGN. Our results indicate that these systems, on average, areconsistent with heavily dust-attenuated AGN powering the red parts of their SEDwhile their blue UV emission is powered by unattenuated star formation in thehost galaxy.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 4 figures, 3 tables
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.07340v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.07340v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Madisyn Brooks</author><pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 19:00:19 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07340v1</guid></item><item><title>Constraining Reionization with Lyα Damping-Wing Absorption in  Galaxy Spectra: A Machine Learning Model Based on Reionization Simulations</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07377v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Hyunbae Park, Intae Jung, Hidenobu Yajima, Jenny Sorce, Paul R. Shapiro, Kyungjin Ahn, Pierre Ocvirk, Romain Teyssier, Gustavo Yepes, Ilian T. Iliev, Joseph S. W. Lewis
&lt;br&gt;
Recently, NIRSpec PRISM/CLEAR observations by JWST have begun providingrest-frame UV continuum measurements of galaxies at $z\gtrsim7$, revealingsignatures of Ly$\alpha$ damping-wing (DW) absorption by the intergalacticmedium (IGM). We develop a methodology to constrain the global ionizationfraction of the IGM $(Q_{\rm HII})$ using low-resolution spectra, employing therandom forest classification (RFC) method. We construct mock spectra using thesimulated galaxies and the IGM from the Cosmic Dawn II simulation and train RFCmodels to estimate $Q_{\rm HII}$ at the redshift of the source and to detectthe presence of a damped Ly$\alpha$ absorber (DLA). We find that individualgalaxy spectra with spectral bins between 1220 and 1270 {\AA} and withsignal-to-noise ratios greater than 20 can place tight constraints on $Q_{\rmHII}$, provided the UV continuum is accurately modeled. This method isparticularly effective for the early phase of reionization ($Q_{\rmHII}&lt;50\%$), when the IGM opacity is high in the DW. As a demonstration, weapply our model to existing NIRSpec PRISM/CLEAR spectra, placing upper boundsof $Q_{\rm HII}=59.6\%$, $5.6\%$, and $18.5\%$ at $z=7.7,~9.4,$ and $10.6$,respectively, with $68\%$ confidence, though several modeling uncertaintiesremain to be discussed. These constraints favor late-starting reionizationmodels, where $\gtrsim 80\%$ of the IGM is ionized after $z=8$. We concludethat high SNR observations of carefully selected targets around $z\sim7-9$ caneffectively constrain reionization models.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 20 pages, 11 figures, submitted to ApJ
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.07377v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.07377v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Hyunbae Park</author><pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 19:47:59 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07377v1</guid></item><item><title>Comparing E-MOSAICS predictions of high-redshift proto-globular clusters  with JWST observations in lensed galaxies</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07498v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Joel Pfeffer, Duncan A. Forbes, Aaron J. Romanowsky, Nate Bastian, Robert A. Crain, J. M. Diederik Kruijssen, Kenji Bekki, Jean P. Brodie, Mélanie Chevance, Warrick J. Couch, Jonah S. Gannon
&lt;br&gt;
High-resolution imaging and strong gravitational lensing of high-redshiftgalaxies have enabled the detection of compact sources with properties similarto nearby massive star clusters. Often found to be very young, these sourcesmay be globular clusters detected in their earliest stages. In this work, wecompare predictions of high-redshift ($z \sim 1$--$10$) star cluster propertiesfrom the E-MOSAICS simulation of galaxy and star cluster formation with thoseof the star cluster candidates in strongly lensed galaxies from James Webb(JWST) and Hubble Space Telescope (HST) imaging. We select galaxies in thesimulation that match the luminosities of the majority of lensed galaxies withstar cluster candidates observed with JWST. We find that the luminosities, agesand masses of the brightest star cluster candidates in the high-redshiftgalaxies are consistent with the E-MOSAICS model. In particular, the brightestcluster ages are in excellent agreement. The results suggest that star clustersin both low- and high-redshift galaxies may form via common mechanisms.However, the brightest clusters in the lensed galaxies tend to be $\approx1$--$1.5$ mag brighter and $\approx 0.5$ dex more massive than the medianE-MOSAICS predictions. We discuss the large number of effects that couldexplain the discrepancy, including simulation and observational limitations,stellar population models, cluster detection biases and nuclear star clusters.Understanding these limitations would enable stronger tests of globular clusterformation models.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 17 pages, 9 figures, 1 table. Submitted to MNRAS
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.07498v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.07498v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Joel Pfeffer</author><pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 01:22:24 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07498v1</guid></item><item><title>COSMOS-Web: stellar mass assembly in relation to dark matter halos  across $0.2&lt;z&lt;12$ of cosmic history</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08290v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
M. Shuntov, O. Ilbert, S. Toft, R. C. Arango-Toro, H. B. Akins, C. M. Casey, M. Franco, S. Harish, J. S. Kartaltepe, A. M. Koekemoer, H. J. McCracken, L. Paquereau, C. Laigle, M. Bethermin, Y. Dubois, N. E. Drakos, A. Faisst, G. Gozaliasl, S. Gillman, C. C. Hayward, M. Hirschmann, M. Huertas-Company, C. K. Jespersen, S. Jin, V. Kokorev, E. Lambrides, D. Le Borgne, D. Liu, G. Magdis, R. Massey, C. J. R. McPartland, W. Mercier, J. E. McCleary, J. McKinney, P. A. Oesch, J. D. Rhodes, R. M. Rich, B. E. Robertson, D. Sanders, M. Trebitsch, L. Tresse, F. Valentino, A. P. Vijayan, J. R. Weaver, A. Weibel, S. M. Wilkins
&lt;br&gt;
We study the stellar mass function (SMF) and the co-evolution with darkmatter halos via abundance matching in the largest redshift range to date$0.2&lt;z&lt;12$ in $0.53 \, {\rm deg}^2$ imaged by JWST from the COSMOS-Web survey.At $z&gt;5$, we find increased abundances of massive (log$\,M_{\star}/M_{\odot}&gt;10.5$) implying integrated star formation efficiencies(SFE) $\epsilon_{\star}\equiv M_{\star}\, f_{\rm b}^{-1} M_{\rm halo}^{-1}\gtrsim 0.5$. We find a flattening of the SMF at the high-mass end that isbetter described by a double power law at $z&gt;5.5$. At $z \lesssim 5.5$ ittransitions to a Schechter law which coincides with the emergence of the firstmassive quiescent galaxies in the Universe. We trace the cosmic stellar massdensity (SMD) and infer the star formation rate density (SFRD), which at$z&gt;7.5$ agrees remarkably with recent \JWST{} UV luminosity function-derivedestimates. However, at $z \lesssim 3.5$, we find significant tension ($\sim0.3$ dex) with the cosmic star formation (SF) history from instantaneous SFmeasures, the causes of which remain poorly understood. We infer thestellar-to-halo mass relation (SHMR) and the SFE from abundance matching out to$z=12$, finding a non-monotonic evolution. The SFE has the characteristicstrong dependence with mass in the range of $0.02 - 0.2$, and mildly decreasesat the low mass end out to $z\sim3.5$. At $z\sim3.5$ the SFE increases sharplyfrom $\sim 0.1$ to approach high SFE of $0.8-1$ by $z\sim 10$ for log$(M_{\rmh}/M_{\odot})\approx11.5$, albeit with large uncertainties. Finally, we use theSHMR to track the SFE and stellar mass growth throughout the halo history andfind that they do not grow at the same rate -- from the earliest times up until$z\sim3.5$ the halo growth rate outpaces galaxy assembly, but at $z&gt;3.5$ halogrowth stagnates and accumulated gas reservoirs keep the SF going and galaxiesoutpace halos.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.08290v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.08290v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>M. Shuntov</author><pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 19:21:25 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08290v1</guid></item><item><title>RUBIES: JWST/NIRSpec resolves evolutionary phases of dusty star-forming  galaxies at $z\sim2$</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08387v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Olivia R. Cooper, Gabriel Brammer, Kasper E. Heintz, Sune Toft, Caitlin M. Casey, David J. Setton, Anna de Graaff, Leindert Boogaard, Nikko J. Cleri, Steven Gillman, Rashmi Gottumukkala, Jenny E. Greene, Bitten Gullberg, Michaela Hirschmann, Raphael E. Hviding, Erini Lambrides, Joel Leja, Arianna S. Long, Sinclaire M. Manning, Michael V. Maseda, Ian McConachie, Jed McKinney, Desika Narayanan, Sedona H. Price, Victoria Strait, Andrea Weibel, Christina C. Williams
&lt;br&gt;
The dearth of high quality spectroscopy of dusty star-forming galaxies(DSFGs) -- the main drivers of the assembly of dust and stellar mass at thepeak of activity in the Universe -- greatly hinders our ability to interprettheir physical processes and evolutionary pathways. We present JWST/NIRSpecobservations from RUBIES of four submillimeter-selected, ALMA-detected DSFGs atcosmic noon, $z\sim2.3-2.7$. While photometry uniformly suggests vigorousongoing star formation for the entire sample in line with canonical DSFGs, thespectra differ: one source has spectroscopic evidence of an evolved stellarpopulation, indicating a recent transition to a post-starburst phase, while theremainder show strong spectroscopic signatures of ongoing starbursts. All fourgalaxies are infrared-luminous (log$_{10}$$L_{\rm{IR}}$/L$_{\rm \odot}$$&gt;12.4$), massive (log$_{10}\,M_\star$/M$_{\rm \odot}$ $&gt;11$), and verydust-obscured ($A_V\sim3-4$ ABmag). Leveraging detections of multiple Balmerand Paschen lines, we derive an optical attenuation curve consistent withCalzetti overall, yet an optical extinction ratio $R_V\sim2.5$, potentiallyindicating smaller dust grains or differences in star-dust geometry. This casestudy provides some of the first detailed spectroscopic evidence that the DSFGsencompass a heterogeneous sample spanning a range of star formation propertiesand evolutionary stages, and illustrates the advantages of synergistic JWST andALMA analysis of DSFGs.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 20 pages, 4 figures; submitted to ApJ
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.08387v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.08387v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Olivia R. Cooper</author><pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 22:46:54 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08387v1</guid></item><item><title>Compact [OIII] emission-line regions ("Green Seeds") in  $\mathrm{Hα}$ emitters at Cosmic Noon from JWST Observations</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08520v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Nuo Chen, Kentaro Motohara, Lee Spitler, Matthew A. Malkan
&lt;br&gt;
We present a rest-frame optical, spatially resolved analysis of more than 100$\mathrm{H\alpha}$ emitters (HAEs) at $z\sim2.2$ in the ZFOURGE-CDFS fieldusing NIRCam imaging from the JWST Advanced Deep Extragalactic Survey (JADES).The ultra-deep, high-resolution data gives us maps of the resolved emissionline regions of HAEs with stellar mass ranging from $10^{8}\,M_{\odot}$ to$10^{10}\,M_{\odot}$. An [OIII] emission-line map of each HAE is created fromthe flux excess in the F150W filter, leading to the discovery of a populationof kiloparsec-scale compact emission line regions (``Green Seeds") with highequivalent widths ($\mathrm{EW}$). We obtain a sample of 128 Green Seeds from68 HAEs with rest-frame $\mathrm{EW_{[OIII]}}&gt;200\r{A}$. Moreover, 17 of themhave extremely large $\mathrm{EW_{[OIII]}}&gt;1000\r{A}$, suggesting the possibleLyman continuum (LyC) leakage from these emission line regions. Embedded withinthe host galaxy, many Green Seeds correspond to UV star-forming clumps andH{\sc ii} regions, indicating elevated starburst activity in them, withspecific star formation rates (sSFR) several times higher than that of the hostgalaxy. Based on theoretical frameworks, Green Seeds are expected to be formedthrough gravitational disk instability and/or galaxy mergers. Considering thestellar masses of Green Seeds, we speculate that high-mass Green Seeds maymigrate toward the galactic center to build the central bulge, while low-massGreen Seeds are easily disrupted and short-lived. Besides, we propose that someGreen Seeds could be the progenitors of globular clusters or ultracompact dwarfgalaxies observed in the local universe.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 29 pages, 18 figures, Submitted to ApJ
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.08520v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.08520v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Nuo Chen</author><pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 05:43:57 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08520v1</guid></item><item><title>The nature of low-luminosity AGNs discovered by JWST at $5&lt;z&lt;6$ based on  clustering analysis: ancestors of quasars at $z\lesssim3$?</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08707v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Junya Arita, Nobunari Kashikawa, Masafusa Onoue, Takehiro Yoshioka, Yoshihiro Takeda, Hiroki Hoshi, Shunta Shimizu
&lt;br&gt;
James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) has discovered many faint AGNs at high-$z$by detecting their broad Balmer lines. However, their high number density, lackof X-ray emission, and overly high black hole masses with respect to their hoststellar masses suggest that they are a distinct population from general type-1quasars. Here, we present clustering analysis of 28 low-luminosity broad-lineAGNs found by JWST (JWST AGNs) at $5&lt;z&lt;6$ based on cross-correlation analysiswith 679 photometrically-selected galaxies to characterize their host darkmatter halo (DMH) masses. From angular and projected cross-correlationfunctions, we find that their typical DMH mass is $\log(M_\mathrm{halo}/h^{-1}\mathrm{M}_\odot) = 11.61_{-0.24}^{+0.19},$ and $11.72_{-0.20}^{+0.17}$, respectively. This result implies that the host DMHs ofthese AGNs are $\sim1$ dex smaller than that of luminous quasars. The DMHs ofJWST AGNs at $5&lt;z&lt;6$ are predicted to grow to$10^{12\unicode{x2013}13}\,h^{-1}\mathrm{M}_\odot$, a typical mass of quasar at$z\lesssim3$. Applying the empirical stellar-to-halo mass ratio to the measuredDMH mass, their host stellar mass is evaluated as$\log(M_*/\mathrm{M}_\odot)=9.72_{-0.39}^{+0.31},$ and $ 9.90_{-0.33}^{+0.27}$,which are higher than some of those estimated by the SED fitting. We alsoevaluate their duty cycle as $f_\mathrm{duty}=0.36_{-0.14}^{+0.18}$ per cent,namely $\sim7\times10^6$ yr as the lifetime of JWST AGNs. While we cannotexclude the possibility that JWST AGNs are simply low-mass type-1 quasars,these results suggest that JWST AGNs are a different population from type-1quasars, and may be the ancestors of quasars at $z\lesssim3$.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 12 pages, 7 figures, submitted to MNRAS
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.08707v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.08707v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Junya Arita</author><pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 11:51:23 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08707v1</guid></item><item><title>JWST/NIRSpec spectroscopy of intermediate-mass quiescent galaxies at $z  \sim 3-4$</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08745v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Riku A. Sato, Akio K. Inoue, Yuichi Harikane, Rhythm Shimakawa, Yuma Sugahara, Yoichi Tamura, Takuya Hashimoto, Kei Ito, Satoshi Yamanaka, Ken Mawatari, Yoshinobu Fudamoto, Yi W. Ren
&lt;br&gt;
We present the analysis of three intermediate-mass quiescent galaxies (QGs)with stellar masses of $\sim10^{10}M_{\rm \odot}$ at redshifts $z\sim 3 - 4$using NIRSpec low-resolution spectroscopy. Utilising the SED fitting codeBAGPIPES, we confirm these target galaxies are consistent with quiescentpopulation, with their specific star formation rates (sSFR) falling below 2-dexthe star-forming main sequence at the same redshifts. Additionally, we identifythese QGs to be less massive than those discovered in previous works,particularly prior to the JWST era. Two of our target galaxies exhibit thepotentially-blended H${\alpha}$+[NII] emission line within their spectra with$S/N&gt;5$. We discuss whether this feature comes from an Active Galactic Nucleus(AGN) or star formation although future high-resolution spectroscopy isrequired to reach a conclusion. One of the target galaxies is covered byJWST/NIRCam imaging of the PRIMER survey. Using the 2D profile fitting codeGalfit, we examine its morphology, revealing a disc-like profile with aS\'{e}rsic index of $n=1.1 \pm 0.1$. On the size-mass relation, we find apotential distinction between less-massive ($\log_{10}{(M_*/M_\odot)}&lt;10.3$)and massive ($\log_{10}{(M_*/M_\odot)}&gt;10.3$) QGs in their evolutionarypathways. The derived quenching timescales for our targets are less than 1 Gyr.This may result from these galaxies being quenched by AGN feedback, supportingthe AGN scenario of the emission line features.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: MNRAS accepted
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.08745v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.08745v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Riku A. Sato</author><pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 13:02:56 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08745v1</guid></item><item><title>The JWST Emission Line Survey (JELS): Extending rest-optical narrow-band  emission line selection into the Epoch of Reionization</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09000v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
K. J. Duncan, D. J. McLeod, P. N. Best, C. A. Pirie, M. Clausen, R. K. Cochrane, J. S. Dunlop, S. R. Flury, J. E. Geach, C. L. Hale, E. Ibar, R. Kondapally, Zefeng Li, J. Matthee, R. J. McLure, Luis Ossa-Fuentes, A. L. Patrick, Ian Smail, D. Sobral, H. M. O. Stephenson, J. P. Stott, A. M. Swinbank
&lt;br&gt;
We present the JWST Emission Line Survey (JELS), a Cycle 1 JWST imagingprogramme exploiting the wavelength coverage and sensitivity of NIRCam toextend narrow-band rest-optical emission line selection into the epoch ofreionization (EoR) for the first time, and to enable unique studies of theresolved ionised gas morphology in individual galaxies across cosmic history.The primary JELS observations comprise $\sim4.7\mu$m narrow-band imaging over$\sim63$ arcmin$^{2}$ designed to enable selection of H$\alpha$ emitters at$z\sim6.1$, as well as the selection of a host of novel emission-line samplesincluding [OIII] at $z\sim8.3$ and Pa $\alpha/\beta$ at $z\sim1.5/2.8$. For theprime F466N and F470N narrow-band observations, the emission-line sensitivitiesachieved are up to $\sim2\times$ more sensitive than current slitlessspectroscopy surveys (5$\sigma$ limits of 1.1-1.6$\times10^{-18}\text{ergs}^{-1}\text{cm}^{-2}$), corresponding to unobscured H$\alpha$ star-formationrates (SFRs) of 1-1.6 $\text{M}_{\odot}\,\text{yr}^{-1}$ at $z\sim6.1$ andextending emission-line selections in the EoR to fainter populations.Simultaneously, JELS also obtained F200W broadband and F212N narrow-bandimaging (H$\alpha$ at $z\sim2.23$) that probes SFRs $\gtrsim5\times$ fainterthan previous ground-based narrow-band studies ($\sim0.2\text{M}_{\odot}\text{yr}^{-1}$), offering an unprecedented resolved view ofstar formation at cosmic noon. In this paper we describe the detailed JELSsurvey design, key data processing steps specific to the survey observations,and demonstrate the exceptional data quality and imaging sensitivity achieved.We then summarise the key scientific goals of JELS and present some earlyscience results, including examples of spectroscopically confirmed H$\alpha$and [OIII] emitters discovered by JELS that illustrate the novel parameterspace probed.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: Submitted to MRNAS; 13 pages, 8 figures. Accompanying data will be  publicly released upon acceptance of this and companion paper (Pirie et al.,  subm.)
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09000v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09000v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>K. J. Duncan</author><pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 18:13:39 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09000v1</guid></item><item><title>A JWST/MIRI View of the ISM in M83: I. Resolved Molecular Hydrogen  Properties, Star Formation, and Feedback</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09020v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Logan H. Jones, Svea Hernandez, Linda J. Smith, Aditya Togi, Tanio Diaz-Santos, Alessandra Aloisi, William Blair, Alec S. Hirschauer, Leslie K. Hunt, Bethan L. James, Nimisha Kumari, Vianney Lebouteiller, Matilde Mingozzi, Lise Ramambason
&lt;br&gt;
We present a spatially-resolved (~3 pc pix$^{-1}$) analysis of thedistribution, kinematics, and excitation of warm H2 gas in the nuclearstarburst region of M83. Our JWST/MIRI IFU spectroscopy reveals a clumpyreservoir of warm H2 (&gt; 200 K) with a mass of ~2.3 x 10$^{5}$ Msun in the areacovered by all four MRS channels. We additionally use the [Ne II] 12.8 ${\mu}$mand [Ne III] 15.5 ${\mu}$m lines as tracers of the star formation rate,ionizing radiation hardness, and kinematics of the ionized ISM, findingtantalizing connections to the H2 properties and to the ages of the underlyingstellar populations. Finally, qualitative comparisons to the trove of public,high-spatial-resolution multiwavelength data available on M83 shows that ourMRS spectroscopy potentially traces all stages of the process of creatingmassive star clusters, from the embedded proto-cluster phase through thedispersion of ISM from stellar feedback.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 21 pages, 11+1 figures; submitted to ApJ
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09020v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09020v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Logan H. Jones</author><pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 18:37:09 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09020v1</guid></item><item><title>JWST/MIRI Observations of Newly Formed Dust in the Cold, Dense Shell of  the Type IIn SN 2005ip</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09142v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Melissa Shahbandeh, Ori D. Fox, Tea Temim, Eli Dwek, Arkaprabha Sarangi, Nathan Smith, Luc Dessart, Bryony Nickson, Michael Engesser, Alexei V. Filippenko, Thomas G. Brink, Weikang Zheng, Tamás Szalai, Joel Johansson, Armin Rest, Schuyler D. Van Dyk, Jennifer Andrews, Chris Ashall, Geoffrey C. Clayton, Ilse De Looze, James M. Derkacy, Michael Dulude, Ryan J. Foley, Suvi Gezari, Sebastian Gomez, Shireen Gonzaga, Siva Indukuri, Jacob Jencson, Mansi Kasliwal, Zachary G. Lane, Ryan Lau, David Law, Anthony Marston, Dan Milisavljevic, Richard O'Steen, Justin Pierel, Matthew Siebert, Michael Skrutskie, Lou Strolger, Samaporn Tinyanont, Qinan Wang, Brian Williams, Lin Xiao, Yi Yang, Szanna Zsíros
&lt;br&gt;
Dust from core-collapse supernovae (CCSNe), specifically Type IIP SNe, hasbeen suggested to be a significant source of the dust observed in high-redshiftgalaxies. CCSNe eject large amounts of newly formed heavy elements, which cancondense into dust grains in the cooling ejecta. However, infrared (IR)observations of typical CCSNe generally measure dust masses that are too smallto account for the dust production needed at high redshifts. Type IIn SNe,classified by their dense circumstellar medium (CSM), are also known to exhibitstrong IR emission from warm dust, but the dust origin and heating mechanismhave generally remained unconstrained because of limited observationalcapabilities in the mid-IR. Here, we present a JWST/MIRI Medium ResolutionSpectrograph (MRS) spectrum of the Type IIn SN 2005ip nearly 17 yearspost-explosion. The Type IIn SN 2005ip is one of the longest-lasting and mostwell-studied SNe observed to date. Combined with a Spitzer mid-IR spectrum ofSN 2005ip obtained in 2008, this data set provides a rare 15-year baseline,allowing for a unique investigation of the evolution of dust. The JWST spectrumshows a new high-mass dust component ($\gtrsim0.08$ M$_{\odot}$) that is notpresent in the earlier Spitzer spectrum. Our analysis shows dust likely formedover the past 15 years in the cold, dense shell (CDS), between the forward andreverse shocks. There is also a smaller mass of carbonaceous dust($\gtrsim0.005$ M$_{\odot}$) in the ejecta. These observations provide newinsights into the role of SN dust production, particularly within the CDS, andits potential contribution to the rapid dust enrichment of the early Universe.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09142v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09142v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Melissa Shahbandeh</author><pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 19:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09142v1</guid></item><item><title>Extending the cosmic distance ladder two orders of magnitude with  strongly lensed Cepheids, carbon AGB, and RGB stars</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09162v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
J. M. Diego, S. P. Willner, J. M. Palencia
&lt;br&gt;
Extreme magnification of stars near the caustics of clusters allow to detectindividual luminous stars at high redshift. We show how deep exposures ofcaustic crossing galaxies at $z\lesssim1$ with IR telescopes such as JWST, candetect non-explosive distance calibrators, such as Cepheids, carbon stars inthe asymptotic giant branch or stars in the tip of the red giant branch. Alarge number of such detections, combined with careful modelling of themagnification affecting these stars (including microlensing), opens the door tousing them as alternative standard candles to SNe in a redshift range thatwould extend the cosmic distance ladder two orders of magnitude for thesedistance calibrators. As a bonus, strongly lensed stars detected in deepexposures provide also a robust method of mapping small dark mattersubstructures since they cluster around the critical curves of small scale darkmatter halos.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 6 pages and 6 figures
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09162v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09162v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>J. M. Diego</author><pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 19:09:55 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09162v1</guid></item><item><title>From UV-bright Galaxies to Early Disks: the Importance of Turbulent Star  Formation in the Early Universe</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09205v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Vadim A. Semenov, Charlie Conroy, Lars Hernquist
&lt;br&gt;
Bursty star formation at early times can explain the surprising abundance ofearly UV-bright galaxies revealed by JWST but can also be a reason for thedelayed formation of galactic disks in high-resolution cosmologicalsimulations. We investigate this interplay in a cosmological simulation of anearly-forming Milky Way analog with detailed modeling of cold turbulentinterstellar medium (ISM), star formation, and feedback. We find that themodeling of locally variable star formation efficiency (SFE) coupled with theISM turbulence on the scales of star-forming regions is important for producingboth early bursty evolution and early formation and survival of galactic disks.Such a model introduces a qualitatively new channel of the global starformation rate (SFR) burstiness caused by chaotic fluctuations in the averageSFE due to changes in the ISM turbulence, which, in our simulation, dominatesthe short-term SFR variability. The average SFE stays low, close to $\sim 1\%$per freefall time, and its variation decreases when the gas disk forms, leadingto only mild effects of stellar feedback on the early disk, enabling itssurvival. By rerunning our simulation with fixed SFE values, we explicitly showthat low SFEs lead to smoother SFR histories and disk survival, while high SFEslead to bursty SFRs and hinder disk formation. The model with variable SFEswitches between these two regimes at the moment of disk formation. Thesetrends are missing in more commonly used star formation prescriptions withfixed SFE; in particular, the prescriptions tying star formation to moleculargas should be interpreted with caution because the two are decoupled at earlytimes, as we also show in this paper.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 16 pages, 10 figures; to be submitted; comments are welcome. For  visualizations, see https://vadimsemenov.com/visualizations/
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09205v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09205v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Vadim A. Semenov</author><pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 20:21:08 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09205v1</guid></item><item><title>The JWST-NIRCam View of Sagittarius C. I. Massive Star Formation and  Protostellar Outflows</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09253v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Samuel Crowe, Rubén Fedriani, Jonathan C. Tan, Alva Kinman, Yichen Zhang, Morten Andersen, Lucía Bravo Ferres, Francisco Nogueras-Lara, Rainer Schödel, John Bally, Adam Ginsburg, Yu Cheng, Yao-Lun Yang, Sarah Kendrew, Chi-Yan Law, Joseph Armstrong, Zhi-Yun Li
&lt;br&gt;
We present James Webb Space Telescope (JWST)-NIRCam observations of themassive star-forming molecular cloud Sagittarius C (Sgr C) in the CentralMolecular Zone (CMZ). In conjunction with ancillary mid-IR and far-IR data, wecharacterize the two most massive protostars in Sgr C via spectral energydistribution (SED) fitting, estimating that they each have current masses of$m_* \sim 20\:M_\odot$ and surrounding envelope masses of $\sim 100\:M_\odot$.We report a census of lower-mass protostars in Sgr C via a search for infraredcounterparts to mm continuum dust cores found with ALMA. We identify 88molecular hydrogen outflow knot candidates originating from outflows fromprotostars in Sgr C, the first such unambiguous detections in the infrared inthe CMZ. About a quarter of these are associated with flows from the twomassive protostars in Sgr C; these extend for over 1 pc and are associated withoutflows detected in ALMA SiO line data. An additional $\sim 40$ featureslikely trace shocks in outflows powered by lower-mass protostars throughout thecloud. We report the discovery of a new star-forming region hosting twoprominent bow shocks and several other line-emitting features driven by atleast two protostars. We infer that one of these is forming a high-mass stargiven an SED-derived mass of $m_* \sim 9\:M_\odot$ and associated massive($\sim 90\:M_\odot$) mm core and water maser. Finally, we identify a populationof miscellaneous Molecular Hydrogen Objects (MHOs) that do not appear to beassociated with protostellar outflows.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: Appendix figures B1 and B2 will be made into online-only figure sets  for the eventual ApJ publication
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09253v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09253v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Samuel Crowe</author><pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 21:59:21 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09253v1</guid></item><item><title>Measuring Star Formation Histories from Asymptotic Giant Branch Stars: A  Demonstration in M31</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09256v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Abigail J. Lee, Daniel R. Weisz, Yi Ren, Alessandro Savino, Andrew E. Dolphin
&lt;br&gt;
We demonstrate how near infrared (NIR) imaging of resolved luminousasymptotic giant branch (AGB) stars can be used to measure well-constrainedstar formation histories (SFHs) across cosmic time. Using UKIRT J and K-bandimaging of M31, we first show excellent agreement over the past $\sim8$ Gyrbetween the PHAT SFH of M31's outer disk derived from a deep opticalcolor-magnitude diagram (CMD; $\sim3.3\times10^{7}$ stars with $M_{F814W}\lesssim +2$), and our spatially-matched SFH based only on modeling AGB starson a NIR CMD ($\sim2.3\times10^{4}$ stars with $M_{J} \lesssim -5$). We findthat only hundreds of AGB stars are needed for reliable SFH recovery, owing totheir excellent age sensitivity in the NIR. We then measure the spatiallyresolved SFH of M31's inner stellar halo ($D_{M31, projected} \sim20-30$ kpc)using $\sim10^5$ AGB stars. We find: (i) a dominant burst of star formationacross M31's inner stellar halo from $4-5$ Gyr ago and lower level, spatiallydistributed star formation $\sim1-2$ Gyr ago; (ii) a younger 'quenching time'in the vicinity of NGC 205 ($\sim1$ Gyr ago) than near M32 ($\sim1.1$ Gyr ago);(iii) $M_{\star}\sim4\pm0.5\times10^9 M_{\odot}$ formed over the past $\sim8$Gyr. We discuss some caveats and the enormous potential of resolved AGB starsin the NIR for measuring SFHs back to ancient epochs ($\sim13$ Gyr ago) ingalaxies to large distances ($D\gtrsim20$ Mpc) with JWST, Roman, and Euclid.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 25 pages, 19 figures, submitted to AAS Journals
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09256v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09256v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Abigail J. Lee</author><pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 22:11:46 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09256v1</guid></item><item><title>The effects of super-Eddington accretion and feedback on the growth of  early supermassive black holes and galaxies</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09450v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Filip Huško, Cedric G. Lacey, William J. Roper, Joop Schaye, Jemima Mae Briggs, Matthieu Schaller
&lt;br&gt;
We present results of cosmological zoom-in simulations of a massiveprotocluster down to redshift $z\approx4$ (when the halo mass is$\approx10^{13}$ M$_\odot$) using the SWIFT code and the EAGLE galaxy formationmodel, focusing on supermassive black hole (BH) physics. The BH was seeded witha mass of $10^4$ M$_\odot$ at redshift $z\approx17$. We compare the base modelthat uses an Eddington limit on the BH accretion rate and thermal isotropicfeedback by the AGN, with one where super-Eddington accretion is allowed, aswell as two other models with BH spin and jets. In the base model, the BH growsat the Eddington limit from $z=9$ to $z=5.5$, when it becomes massive enough tohalt its own and its host galaxy's growth through feedback. We find thatallowing super-Eddington accretion leads to drastic differences, with the BHgoing through an intense but short super-Eddington growth burst around$z\approx7.5$, during which it increases its mass by orders of magnitude,before feedback stops further growth (of both the BH and the galaxy). By$z\approx4$ the galaxy is only half as massive in the super-Eddington cases,and an order of magnitude more extended, with the half-mass radius reachingvalues of a few physical kpc instead of a few hundred pc. The BH masses in oursimulations are consistent with the intrinsic BH mass$-$stellar mass relationinferred from high-redshift observations by JWST. This shows that galaxyformation models using the $\Lambda$CDM cosmology are capable of reproducingthe observed massive BHs at high redshift. Allowing jets, either at super- orsub-Eddington rates, has little impact on the host galaxy properties, but leadsto lower BH masses as a result of stronger self-regulation, which is itself aconsequence of higher feedback efficiencies.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: Submitted to MNRAS
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09450v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09450v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Filip Huško</author><pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 10:06:10 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09450v1</guid></item><item><title>JWST/NIRSpec Observations of Brown Dwarfs in the Orion Nebula Cluster</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10000v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
K. L. Luhman, C Alves de Oliveira, I. Baraffe, G. Chabrier, E. Manjavacas, R. J. Parker, P. Tremblin
&lt;br&gt;
We have used the multiobject mode of the Near-Infrared Spectrograph (NIRSpec)on board the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) to obtain low-resolution 1-5umspectra of 22 brown dwarf candidates in the Orion Nebula Cluster, which wereselected with archival images from the Hubble Space Telescope. One of thetargets was previously classified as a Herbig-Haro (HH) object and exhibitsstrong emission in H I, H2, and the fundamental band of CO, furtherdemonstrating that HH objects can have bright emission in that CO band. Theremaining targets have late spectral types (M6.5 to early L) and are youngbased on gravity sensitive features, as expected for low-mass members of thecluster. According to theoretical evolutionary models, these objects shouldhave masses that range from the hydrogen burning limit to 0.003-0.007 Msun. Twoof the NIRSpec targets were identified as proplyds in earlier analysis ofHubble images. They have spectral types of M6.5 and M7.5, making them two ofthe coolest and least massive known proplyds. Another brown dwarf showsabsorption bands at 3-5um from ices containing H2O, CO2, OCN-, and CO,indicating that it is either an edge-on class II system or a class I protostar.It is the coolest and least massive object that has detections of these icefeatures. In addition, it appears to be the first candidate for a protostellarbrown dwarf that has spectroscopy confirming its late spectral type.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: Astronomical Journal, in press
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10000v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10000v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>K. L. Luhman</author><pubDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2024 21:45:26 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10000v1</guid></item><item><title>Candidates for Substellar Members of the Orion Nebula Cluster from  JWST/NIRCam</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10406v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
K. L. Luhman
&lt;br&gt;
In 2022, the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) obtained 1-5um images of thecenter of the Orion Nebula Cluster (ONC). I have analyzed these data in anattempt to search for substellar members of the cluster. Using a pair ofcolor-color diagrams, I have identified &gt;200 brown dwarf candidates that lackspectral classifications. Some of the candidates could be protostars (eitherstellar or substellar) given their very red colors. Based on the age of the ONCand the photometry predicted by theoretical evolutionary models, the faintestcandidates could have masses of 1-2 Mjup. This sample of candidates may proveto be valuable for studying various aspects of young brown dwarfs, includingtheir mass function and minimum mass. However, spectroscopy is needed toconfirm the membership (via signatures of youth) and late spectral types of thecandidates. Finally, I note that most of the "Jupiter-mass binary objects" thathave been previously identified with these JWST images are absent from mysample of candidates because their colors are indicative of reddened backgroundsources rather than young brown dwarfs or their photometry is inadequate forassessing their nature because of very low signal-to-noise ratios and/ordetections in only a few bands.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: Astronomical Journal, in press
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10406v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10406v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>K. L. Luhman</author><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 12:58:37 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10406v1</guid></item><item><title>Hidden Cooling Flows IV: More Details on Centaurus and the Efficiency of  AGN Feedback in Clusters</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10675v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
A. C. Fabian, G. J. Ferland, J. S. Sanders, H. R. Russell, B. R. McNamara, C. Pinto, J. Hlavacek-Larrondo, S. A. Walker, L. R. Ivey, M. McDonald
&lt;br&gt;
Cooling flows are common in galaxy clusters which have cool cores. The softX-ray emission below 1 keV from the flows is mostly absorbed by cold dusty gaswithin the central cooling sites. Further evidence for this process ispresented here through a more detailed analysis of the nearby Centaurus clusterand some additional clusters. Predictions of JWST near and mid-infrared spectrafrom cooling gas are presented. [NeVI] emission at 7.65 micron should be animportant diagnostic of gas cooling between 6 and 1.5 times 10^5 K. Theemerging overall picture of hidden cooling flows is explored. The efficiency ofAGN feedback in reducing the total cooling rate in cool cores is shown to beabove 50 percent for many clusters but is rarely above 90 per cent. Thereduction is mostly in outer gas. Cooling dominates in elliptical galaxies andgalaxy groups which have mass flow rates below about 15M/yr and in some massiveclusters where rates can exceed 1000M/yr.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 17 pages, 49 figures submitted to MNRAS
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10675v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10675v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>A. C. Fabian</author><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 17:17:20 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10675v1</guid></item><item><title>Spectroscopic confirmation of a dust-obscured, metal-rich dwarf galaxy  at z~5</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10954v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
L. Bisigello, G. Gandolfi, A. Feltre, P. Arrabal Haro, A. Calabrò, N. J. Cleri, L. Costantin, G. Girardi, M. Giulietti, A. Grazian, C. Gruppioni, N. P. Hathi, B. W. Holwerda, M. Llerena, R. A. Lucas, F. Pacucci, I. Prandoni, G. Rodighiero, L. -M. Seillé, S. M. Wilkins, M. Bagley, M. Dickinson., S. L. Finkelstein, J. Kartaltepe, A. M. Koekemoer, C. Papovich, N. Pirzkal
&lt;br&gt;
We present the first spectroscopic confirmation of a dust-obscured dwarfgalaxy, CEERS-14821.  The analysis is performed combining JWST NIRCam broad-band photometry andNIRSpec/PRISM spectroscopic data. From the detection of multiple rest-frameoptical lines, we derive that CEERS-14821 is located at $z=4.883\pm0.003$.Moreover, from a secure detection of the $H_{\alpha}$ and $H_{\beta}$ wederived that the galaxy has a dust extinction ranging from Av=2.2 to Av=3.3,depending on the assumed reddening law. This value is extremely large giventhat we estimated a low stellar mass around log(M/Mo)=8.0-8.2. Moreover, usingdifferent metallicity tracers, we verify that the galaxy is also metal-rich,with 12+log(O/H)&gt;8.3. This is well above the expectation from both themass-metallicity relation and the fundamental mass-metalliticy relation.CEERS-14821 is going through a burst of star formation, there are noindications of a strong contribution from an active galactic nuclei (f(AGN)&lt;0.5with respect to the total dust luminosity). Based on the rest-frame opticalimages, this source has a size compatible with galaxies of similar stellar massand redshift. Finally, with the current data, it seems that there are galaxiesclosely interacting with CEERS-14821.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 14 pages, 11 figures. Submitted to A&amp;A
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10954v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10954v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>L. Bisigello</author><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 19:00:02 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10954v1</guid></item><item><title>Seven wonders of Cosmic Dawn: JWST confirms a high abundance of galaxies  and AGNs at z $\simeq$ 9-11 in the GLASS field</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10967v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
L. Napolitano, M. Castellano, L. Pentericci, P. Arrabal Haro, A. Fontana, T. Treu, P. Bergamini, A. Calabro, S. Mascia, T. Morishita, G. Roberts-Borsani, P. Santini, E. Vanzella, B. Vulcani, D. Zakharova, T. Bakx, M. Dickinson, C. Grillo, N. Leethochawalit, M. Llerena, E. Merlin, D. Paris, S. Rojas-Ruiz, P. Rosati, X. Wang, I. Yoon, J. Zavala
&lt;br&gt;
We present JWST/NIRSpec PRISM follow-up of candidate galaxies at z=9-11selected from deep JWST/NIRCam photometry in GLASS-JWST Early Release Sciencedata. We spectroscopically confirm six sources with secure redshifts at z =9.52-10.43, each showing multiple emission lines. An additional object islikely at z = 10.66, based on its Lya-break and a single emission feature,while one source is a lower redshift interloper. The sample includes the firstJWST-detected candidate at z=10, GHZ1/GLASS-z10, which we confirm at z = 9.875,and the X-ray detected AGN GHZ9 confirmed at z = 10.145. Three objects in oursample, including GHZ9, have EW(CIII])&gt;20A and occupy a region compatible withAGN emission in the EW(CIII]) vs CIV/CIII] diagram. The spectroscopic sampleconfirms a high abundance of galaxies at z &gt; 9. We measure a number density ofz=10 galaxies in the GLASS-JWST ERS field that is a factor of &gt;3 higher thanother JWST-based estimates at demagnified rest-frame magnitudes of -21 &lt; Muv &lt;-19. We find that the positions of these galaxies in redshift and angular spaceare not consistent with all of them being part of a unique progenitor ofpresent-day galaxy clusters. The high density of objects in the GLASS regioncan be explained either by clustering on large scales or by a superposition ofdifferent forming structures of which we observe only the brightest members. Byconsidering all the spectroscopic z=10 sources in the Abell-2744 field, weidentify two potential galaxy proto-clusters centered around GHZ9 and JD1, withrelative separations between their members of 1-2 pMpc. The potential AGNnature of three of the sources in our sample lends support to a scenario inwhich the high abundance of bright sources determined by JWST surveys at cosmicdawn may be affected by AGN contribution to their UV luminosity.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: Submitted to A&amp;A
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10967v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10967v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>L. Napolitano</author><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 19:00:22 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10967v1</guid></item><item><title>Tracing star formation across cosmic time at tens of parsec-scales in  the lensing cluster field Abell 2744</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10974v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Adélaïde Claeyssens, Angela Adamo, Matteo Messa, Miroslava Dessauges-Zavadsky, Johan Richard, Ivan Kramarenko, Jorryt Matthee, Rohan P. Naidu
&lt;br&gt;
We present a sample of 1956 individual stellar clumps at redshift 0.7&lt;z&lt;10,detected with JWST/NIRCam in 476 galaxies lensed by the galaxy clusterAbell2744. The lensed clumps present magnifications ranging between $\mu$=1.8and $\mu$=300. We perform simultaneous size-photometry estimates in 20JWST/NIRCam median and broad-band filters from 0.7 to 5 $\mu$m. Spectral energydistribution (SED) fitting analyses enable us to recover the physicalproperties of the clumps. The majority of the clumps are spatially resolved andhave effective radii in the range R_eff = 10 - 700 pc. We restrict this firststudy to the 1751 post-reionisation era clumps with redshift &lt;5.5. We find asignificant evolution of the average clump ages, SFR, SFR surface densities andmetallicity with increasing redshift, while median stellar mass and stellarmass surface densities are similar in the probed redshift range. We observe astrong correlation between the clump properties and the properties of theirhost galaxies, with more massive galaxies hosting more massive and olderclumps. We find that clumps closer to their host galactic center are on averagemore massive, while their ages do not show clear sign of migration. We findthat clumps at cosmic noon sample the upper-mass end of the mass function tohigher masses than at z&gt;3, reflecting the rapid increase towards the peak ofthe cosmic star formation history. We conclude that the results achieved overthe studied redshift range are in agreement with expectation of in-situ clumpformation scenario from large-scale disk fragmentation.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: Submitted to MNRAS, comments welcome
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10974v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10974v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Adélaïde Claeyssens</author><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 19:02:21 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10974v1</guid></item><item><title>The evolution of [OIII]$+\rm{H}β$ equivalent width from  $\mathbf{z\simeq3-8}$: implications for the production and escape of ionizing  photons during reionization</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10988v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
R. Begley, R. J. McLure, F. Cullen, D. J. McLeod, J. S. Dunlop, A. C. Carnall, T. M. Stanton, A. E. Shapley, R. Cochrane, C. T. Donnan, R. S. Ellis, A. Fontana, N. A. Grogin, A. M. Koekemoer
&lt;br&gt;
Accurately quantifying the ionizing photon production efficiency($\xi_\rm{ion}$) of $z&gt;6$ star-forming galaxies (SFGs) is necessary tounderstand their contribution to reionization. We investigate the ionizingproperties of N=289 SFGs selected at $z=6.9-7.6$ from the JWST Cycle-1 imagingprogrammes; PRIMER and JADES. We use BAGPIPES to consistently infer theequivalent widths of their [OIII]+$\rm{H\beta}$ emission lines ($W_\lambda$)and their physical properties. To supplement our high-redshift galaxies, wemeasure $W_\lambda$ photometrically for a sample of N=253 $z=3.2-3.6$ SFGsselected from the VANDELS spectroscopic survey. Comparing these samples, wefind a strong apparent redshift evolution in their median $W_\lambda$,increasing from $W_\lambda =310\pm25\,\r{A}$ in VANDELS to $W_\lambda=630\pm30\,\r{A}$ in our JWST-based sample. In the JWST sample at $z&gt;7$, wefind that $W_\lambda$ correlates with both stellar mass and UV luminosity, withhigh-mass, $M_{ UV}-$faint galaxies producing systematically weaker emissionlines. Moreover, we discover a departure from the standard log-normal shape ofthe $W_\lambda$ distribution, characterised by a more pronounced tail at lower$W_\lambda$, consistent with increasingly bursty star formation. Using$W_\lambda$ as a proxy for $\xi_\rm{ion}$, and UV spectral slope as a proxy forLyC escape fraction ($f_\rm{esc}$), we find a minority of galaxies with high$\xi_\rm{ion}$ and $f_\rm{esc}$ (e.g., $\rm{log(\xi_{ion}/erg^{-1}Hz})\sim25.6$and $f_\rm{esc}\sim0.15$). However, we find that the LyC photon budget at $z&gt;7$is dominated by galaxies with more moderate output, close to the sample medianof $\rm{log(\xi_{ion}/erg^{-1}Hz})\sim25.3$ and $f_\rm{esc}\sim0.05$. This isconsistent with estimates for the number of LyC photons required to powerreionization at $z&gt;7$, with no evidence for over or under-production.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 18 pages, 9 figures + 1 appendix. Submitted to MNRAS
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10988v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10988v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>R. Begley</author><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 19:15:54 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10988v1</guid></item><item><title>Direct High-resolution Observation of Feedback and Chemical Enrichment  in the Circumgalactic Medium at Redshift 2.8</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10993v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Bo Peng, Fabrizio Arrigoni Battaia, Amit Vishwas, Mingyu Li, Eduardo Iani, Fengwu Sun, Qiong Li, Carl Ferkinhoff, Gordon Stacey, Zheng Cai
&lt;br&gt;
Although the circumgalactic medium (CGM) plays a vital role in galaxyevolution, studying the emission from CGM is challenging due to its low surfacebrightness and the complexities involved in interpreting resonant lines likeLy$\alpha$. The near-infrared coverage, unprecedented sensitivity, and highspatial resolution of the JWST enable us to study the optical strong linesassociated with the extended Ly$\alpha$ "nebulae" at redshift 2-3. These linesserve as diagnostic tools to infer the physical conditions in the massive CGMgas reservoir of these systems. In deep medium-band images taken by the JWST,we serendipitously discover the [O III] emission from the CGM surrounding amassive interacting galaxy system at redshift z ~ 2.8, known to be embedded ina bright extended (100 kpc) Ly$\alpha$ "nebula". This is the first time thatthe [O III] lines are detected from a Ly$\alpha$ "nebula", and the JWST imagesreveal that the CGM gas actually resides in narrow (~ 2.5 kpc) filamentarystructures with strong [O III] emission, tracing the same extent as theLy$\alpha$ emission. Analysis of the [O III] suggests that the emitting CGM isfully ionized and is energetically dominated by mechanical heating. We alsofind that the inferred density and pressure are higher than those commonlypredicted by simulations of the CGM. We conclude that the observed CGM emissionoriginates from the gas expelled by the episodic feedback processes, coolingdown and enriching the CGM, while travelling to a distance of at least 60 kpc.These observations demonstrate how fierce feedback processes shape gasdistribution and properties in the CGM around massive halos. While the deephigh-resolution imaging opens up a new discovery space for investigating theCGM, it also challenges numerical simulations to explain and reproduce theexquisitely complex structures revealed by the observations.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 13 pages, 6 figures, 1 table, submitted to A&amp;A Letter
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10993v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10993v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Bo Peng</author><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 19:20:01 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10993v1</guid></item><item><title>GA-NIFS &amp; EIGER: A merging quasar host at z=7 with an overmassive black  hole</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11035v2</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Madeline A. Marshall, Minghao Yue, Anna-Christina Eilers, Jan Scholtz, Michele Perna, Chris J. Willott, Roberto Maiolino, Hannah Übler, Santiago Arribas, Andrew J. Bunker, Stephane Charlot, Bruno Rodríguez Del Pino, Torsten Böker, Stefano Carniani, Giovanni Cresci, Francesco D'Eugenio, Gareth C. Jones, Giacomo Venturi, Rongmon Bordoloi, Daichi Kashino, Ruari Mackenzie, Jorryt Matthee, Rohan Naidu, Robert A. Simcoe
&lt;br&gt;
The James Webb Space Telescope is revolutionising our ability to understandthe host galaxies and local environments of high-z quasars. Here we obtain acomprehensive understanding of the host galaxy of the z=7.08 quasar J1120+0641by combining NIRSpec integral field spectroscopy with NIRCam photometry of thehost continuum emission. Our emission line maps reveal that this quasar host isundergoing a merger with a bright companion galaxy. The quasar host and thecompanion have similar dynamical masses of $\sim10^{10}M_\odot$, suggestingthat this is a major galaxy interaction. Through detailed quasar subtractionand SED fitting using the NIRCam data, we obtain an estimate of the hoststellar mass of $M_{\ast}\simeq2.6\times10^9M_\odot$, with$M_{*}\simeq5.0\times10^9M_\odot$ for the companion galaxy. Using the H$\beta$Balmer line we estimate a virial black hole mass of$M_{\rm{BH}}\simeq1.4\times10^9 M_\odot$. Thus, J1120+0641 has an extreme blackhole - stellar mass ratio of $M_{\rm{BH}}/M_\ast\simeq0.54$, which is ~3 dexlarger than expected by the local scaling relations between black hole andstellar mass. J1120+0641 is powered by an overmassive black hole with thehighest reported black hole - stellar mass ratio, in a quasar host that iscurrently undergoing a major merger -- these new insights highlight the powerof JWST for measuring and understanding these extreme first quasars.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: Submitted to A&amp;A, comments welcome
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11035v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11035v2 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Madeline A. Marshall</author><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 20:36:02 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11035v2</guid></item><item><title>Unveiling two deeply embedded young protostars in the S68N Class 0  protostellar core with JWST/NIRSpec</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11095v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Valentin J. M. Le Gouellec, Ben W. P. Lew, Thomas P. Greene, Doug Johnstone, Antoine Gusdorf, Logan Francis, Curtis DeWitt, Michael Meyer, Łukasz Tychoniec, Ewine F. van Dishoeck, Mary Barsony, Klaus W. Hodapp, Massimo Robberto
&lt;br&gt;
The near-infrared (NIR) emission of the youngest protostars still needs to becharacterized to better understand the evolution of their accretion andejection activity. We analyze James Webb Space Telescope NIRSpec 1.7 -- 5.3$\mu$m observations of two deeply embedded sources in the S68N protostellarcore in Serpens. The North Central (NC) source exhibits a highly obscuredspectrum (A_K ~ 4.8 mag) that is modeled with a pre-main-sequence photosphereand a hot disk component. The photospheric parameters are consistent with ayoung, low-mass photosphere, as suggested by the low surface gravity, log g of1.94 $\pm$ 0.15 cm s$^{-2}$. The hot disk suggests that accretion onto thecentral protostellar embryo is ongoing, although prototypical accretion-tracingemission lines HI are not detected. The South Central (SC) source, which iseven more embedded (A_K ~ 8 mag; no continuum is detected shortward of 3.6$\mu$m) appears to be driving the large-scale S68N protostellar outflow, andlaunches a collimated hot molecular jet detected in \Ht and CO ro-vibrationallines. Shock modeling of the \Ht (ro)vibrational lines establishes that fast$C$-type shocks ($\geq$ 30 km s$^{-1}$), with high pre-shock density ($\geq$$10^7$ cm$^{-3}$), and strong magnetic field (b ~ 3--10, where $B =b\,\times\,\sqrt{\textrm{n}_{\textrm{H}} (\textrm{cm}^{-3})}\,\mu\textrm{G}$)best match the data. The bright CO fundamental line forest suggests energeticexcitation, with the contribution of non-LTE effects, ie irradiation pumping.Detected OH and CH$^{+}$ ro-vibrational lines support this hypothesis. Thesetwo Class 0 protostars seem to be in very young evolutionary stages and stillhave to acquire the bulk of their final stellar masses. These resultsdemonstrate that JWST enables unprecedented diagnostics of these first stagesof the protostellar evolutionary phase.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11095v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11095v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Valentin J. M. Le Gouellec</author><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 22:16:10 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11095v1</guid></item><item><title>Spider-Webb: JWST Near Infrared Camera resolved galaxy star formation  and nuclear activities in the Spiderweb protocluster at z=2.16</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11174v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Rhythm Shimakawa, Yusei Koyama, Tadayuki Kodama, Helmut Dannerbauer, J. M. Perez-Martinez, Huub J. A. Röttgering, Ichi Tanaka, Chiara D'Eugenio, Abdurrahman Naufal, Kazuki Daikuhara, Yuheng Zhang
&lt;br&gt;
Near-infrared (NIR) emission is less affected by dust than UV and opticalemission and is therefore useful for studying the properties of dust-obscuredgalaxies. Although rest-frame NIR observations of high-redshift galaxies havelong been made using space telescopes, their structures were unresolved due tothe lack of angular resolution. This letter reports the early results from theanalysis of high-resolution Pa$\beta$ imaging of the Spiderweb protocluster at$z=2.16$ with the JWST Near Infrared Camera. We investigate radial profiles ofPa$\beta$ lines and rest-frame NIR continua from luminous H$\alpha$-emittinggalaxies (HAEs) in the protocluster. Particularly, we compare those of 11 HAEs(N-HAEs) on the star-forming main sequence with those of 8 HAEs (X-HAEs) withX-ray AGNs. Resultant composite Pa$\beta$ line images of N-HAEs indicatesignificant star formation in galactic disks. In contrast, X-HAEs are dominatedby point source components rather than outer star formation, as inferred fromour earlier work based on multi-wavelength SED fitting. Given their higherstellar potentials suggested from their rest-frame NIR images, the differentcharacteristics may be driven by the impact of AGN feedback.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 6 pages, 6 figures; Accepted for publication in MNRAS Letters
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11174v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11174v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Rhythm Shimakawa</author><pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 02:25:51 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11174v1</guid></item><item><title>Exploring the effect of different cosmologies on the Epoch of  Reionization 21-cm signal with POLAR</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11620v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Anshuman Acharya, Qing-bo Ma, Sambit K. Giri, Benedetta Ciardi, Raghunath Ghara, Garrelt Mellema, Saleem Zaroubi, Ian Hothi, Ilian T. Iliev, Léon V. E. Koopmans, Michele Bianco
&lt;br&gt;
A detection of the 21-cm signal power spectrum from the Epoch of Reionizationis imminent, thanks to consistent advancements from telescopes such as LOFAR,MWA, and HERA, along with the development of SKA. In light of this progress, itis crucial to expand the parameter space of simulations used to inferastrophysical properties from this signal. In this work, we explore the role ofcosmological parameters such as the Hubble constant $H_0$ and the matterclustering amplitude $\sigma_8$, whose values as provided by measurements atdifferent redshifts are in tension. We run $N$-body simulations using GADGET-4,and post-process them with the reionization simulation code POLAR, that usesL-GALAXIES to include galaxy formation and evolution properties and GRIZZLY toexecute 1-D radiative transfer of ionizing photons in the intergalactic medium(IGM). We compare our results with the latest JWST observations and explorewhich astrophysical properties for different cosmologies are necessary to matchthe observed UV luminosity functions at redshifts $z = 10$ and 9. Additionally,we explore the impact of these parameters on the observed 21-cm signal powerspectrum, focusing on the redshifts within the range of LOFAR 21-cm signalobservations ($z \approx 8.5-10$). Despite differences in cosmological andastrophysical parameters, the 21-cm power spectrum at these redshifts agreeswith presently observed upper limits. This suggests the need for broaderphysical parameter spaces for inference modeling to account for all models thatagree with observations. However, we also propose stronger constraining powerby using a combination of galactic and IGM observables.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 16 pages, 8 figures, 2 tables. Submitted to the Monthly Notices of  the Royal Astronomical Society (MNRAS)
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11620v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11620v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Anshuman Acharya</author><pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 14:58:39 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11620v1</guid></item><item><title>Population synthesis and astrophysical inference for high-$z$ JWST  galaxies</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11680v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Trey Driskell, Ethan O. Nadler, Andrew Benson, Vera Gluscevic
&lt;br&gt;
Observations of the high-$z$ Universe from JWST have revealed a newpopulation of bright, early galaxies. A robust statistical interpretation ofthis data requires fast forward models that account for uncertainties in galaxyevolution and incorporate observational systematic effects. We present aprobabilistic framework for population synthesis of high-$z$ galaxies andinference of their properties. Our framework is based on the semi-analyticgalaxy-formation model Galacticus. To infer the astrophysical parametersgoverning high-$z$ galaxy evolution, we analyze JWST data from the CEERS andNGDEEP surveys and calculate the likelihood of observing individual objects inapparent magnitude--redshift space, for $z\geq8.5$ galaxy candidates. Weinclude observational selection effects due to limited survey volume and depth,as well as photometric redshift uncertainties. We recover the posteriorprobability distribution for parameters describing star formation and outflowrates. We place an upper limit on the star formation timescale of$500~\mathrm{Myr}$ at a disk velocity of $50~\mathrm{km\ s}^{-1}$, and we infera characteristic velocity at which the outflow mass-loading factor is $\sim 1$of $150^{+280}_{-60}~\mathrm{km\ s}^{-1}$, both at $95\%$ confidence.Marginalizing over our astrophysical model, we find that galaxies in CEERS andNGDEEP data occupy halos with virial masses $10^{10\pm 0.5}~M_{\mathrm{\odot}}$at $8.5\leq z\leq 12$, at $95\%$ confidence. The star formation timescalepreferred by our fit is relatively short compared to typical values at lowerredshifts, consistent with previous findings. The modeling and analysisframework presented here can enable systematic tests of high-$z$ galaxies' dustcontent, initial mass functions, and star formation burstiness in the future.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 14 pages, 10 figures
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11680v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11680v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Trey Driskell</author><pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 16:18:46 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11680v1</guid></item><item><title>The JWST Emission Line Survey (JELS): An untargeted search for H$α$  emission line galaxies at $z &gt; 6$ and their physical properties</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11808v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
C. A. Pirie, P. N. Best, K. J. Duncan, D. J. McLeod, R. K. Cochrane, M. Clausen, J. S. Dunlop, S. R. Flury, J. E. Geach, C. L. Hale, E. Ibar, R. Kondapally, Zefeng Li, J. Matthee, R. J. McLure, L. Ossa-Fuentes, A. L. Patrick, Ian Smail, D. Sobral, H. M. O. Stephenson, J. P. Stott, A. M. Swinbank
&lt;br&gt;
We present the first results of the JWST Emission Line Survey (JELS).Utilising the first NIRCam narrow-band imaging at 4.7$\mu$m, over 63arcmin$^{2}$ in the PRIMER/COSMOS field, we have identified 609 emission linegalaxy candidates. From these, we robustly selected 35 H$\alpha$ star-forminggalaxies at $z \sim 6.1$, with H$\alpha$ star-formation rates($\rm{SFR_{H\alpha}}$) of $\sim0.9-15\ \rm{M_{\odot} yr^{-1}}$. Combining ourunique H$\alpha$ sample with the exquisite panchromatic data in the field, weexplore their physical properties and star-formation histories, and comparethese to a broad-band selected sample at $z\sim 6$ to offer vital new insightinto the nature of high-redshift galaxies. UV-continuum slopes ($\beta$) areconsiderably redder for our H$\alpha$ sample ($\langle\beta\rangle\sim-1.92$)compared to the broad-band sample ($\langle\beta\rangle\sim-2.35$). This is notdue to dust attenuation as our H$\alpha$ sample is relatively dust-poor (median$A_V=0.23$); instead, we argue that the reddened slopes could be due to nebularcontinuum. We compared $\rm{SFR_{H\alpha}}$ and the UV-continuum-derived$\rm{SFR_{UV}}$ to SED-fitted measurements averaged over canonical timescalesof 10 and 100 Myr ($\rm{SFR_{10}}$ and $\rm{SFR_{100}}$). We find an increasein recent SFR for our sample of H$\alpha$ emitters, particularly at lowerstellar masses ($&lt;10^9 \rm{M_{\odot}}$). We also find that $\rm{SFR_{H\alpha}}$strongly traces SFR averaged over 10 Myr timescales, whereas the UV-continuumover-predicts SFR on 100 Myr timescales at low stellar masses. These resultspoint to our H$\alpha$ sample undergoing `bursty' star formation. Our F356W $z\sim 6$ sample show a larger scatter in $\rm{SFR_{10}/SFR_{100}}$ across allstellar masses, highlighting how narrow-band photometric selections ofH$\alpha$ emitters are key to quantifying the burstiness of star-formationactivity.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: Submitted to MRNAS; 27 pages, 19 figures. Accompanying data will be  publicly released upon acceptance of this manuscript
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11808v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11808v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>C. A. Pirie</author><pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 18:35:19 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11808v1</guid></item><item><title>A First-look at Spatially-resolved Infrared Supernova Remnants in M33  with JWST</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11821v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Sumit K. Sarbadhicary, Erik Rosolowsky, Adam K. Leroy, Thomas G. Williams, Eric W. Koch, Joshua Peltonen, Adam Smercina, Julianne J. Dalcanton, Simon C. O. Glover, Margaret Lazzarini, Ryan Chown, Jennifer Donovan Meyer, Karin Sandstrom, Benjamin F. Williams, Elizabeth Tarantino
&lt;br&gt;
We present the first spatially-resolved infrared images of supernova remnants(SNRs) in M33 with the unprecedented sensitivity and resolution of JWST. Weanalyze 43 SNRs in four JWST fields: two covering central and southern M33 withseparate NIRCam (F335M, F444W) and MIRI (F560W, F2100W) observations, one$\sim$5 kpc-long radial strip observed with MIRI F770W, and one covering thegiant HII region NGC 604 with multiple NIRCam and MIRI broad/narrowbandfilters. Of the 21 SNRs in the MIRI field, we found three clear detections(i.e., identical infrared and \ha morphologies), and six partial-detections,implying a detection fraction of 43\% in these bands. In contrast, only one SNR(out of 16) is detectable in the NIRCam field. One of the SNRs, L10-080, is apotential candidate for having freshly-formed ejecta dust, based on its sizeand centrally-concentrated 21 \mum emission. Two SNRs near NGC 604 have strongevidence of molecular (H$_2$) emission at 4.7 \mum, making them the farthestknown SNRs with visible molecular shocks. Five SNRs have F770W observations,with the smaller younger objects showing tentative signs of emission, while theolder, larger ones have voids. Multi-wavelength data indicate that theclearly-detected SNRs are also among the smallest, brightest at otherwavelengths (\ha, radio and X-ray), have the broadest line widths (H$\alpha$FWHM$\sim$250-350 km/s), and the densest environments. No strong correlationwith star-formation histories are seen, with the clearly-detected SNRs havingboth high-mass ($\sim$35 \Msun) and low-mass ($\lesssim$10 \Msun) progenitors.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 33 pages, 17 figures, 2 tables, submitted to ApJ
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11821v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11821v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Sumit K. Sarbadhicary</author><pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 18:49:07 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11821v1</guid></item><item><title>Discovery of a 25 parsec-long precessing jet emanating from the old nova  GK Persei</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12103v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Michael M. Shara, Kenneth M. Lanzetta, James T. Garland, David Valls-Gabaud, Stefan Gromoll, Mikita Misiura, Frederick M. Walter, John K. Webb, Barrett Martin
&lt;br&gt;
Classical nova eruptions result from thermonuclear-powered runaways in, andejection of, the hydrogen-rich envelopes of white dwarf stars accreted fromtheir close binary companions. Novae brighten to up to 1,000,000 solarluminosities, and recur thousands of times over their lifetimes spanningseveral billion years. Between eruptions, mass transfer from the donor star tothe white dwarf proceeds via an accretion disk unless the white dwarf possessesa strong magnetic field which can partially or totally disrupt the disk. Inthat case, accretion is focussed by the white dwarf's magnetic field towardsits magnetic poles. Optical spectroscopy and interferometric radio mapsdemonstrate the presence of bipolar jets, typically arcsec in angular size, andorders of magnitude smaller than one parsec in linear size, during the days tomonths after nova eruptions. These jets expel collimated matter from the whitedwarfs in nova binary stars, but well-resolved images of them are lacking. Herewe report the Condor telescope's detection of a hitherto unknown, highlyresolved and braided jet, three degrees (at least 25 parsecs) in length. Thejet originates at the white dwarf of the old nova GK Persei (nova Per 1901 CE).It precesses on a ~ 3600 yr timescale, and must be at least 7200 years old.Detected across four decades of wavelength, the jet's ultimate energy source islikely the strong accretion shocks near the white dwarf's magnetic poles.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 18 pages, 4 figures
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.12103v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.12103v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Michael M. Shara</author><pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 23:59:42 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12103v1</guid></item><item><title>The Physical Origin of Extreme Emission Line Galaxies at High redshifts:  Strong {\sc [Oiii]} Emission Lines Produced by Obscured AGNs</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12198v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Chenghao Zhu, Yuichi Harikane, Masami Ouchi, Yoshiaki Ono, Masato Onodera, Shenli Tang, Yuki Isobe, Yoshiki Matsuoka, Toshihiro Kawaguchi, Hiroya Umeda, Kimihiko Nakajima, Yongming Liang, Yi Xu, Yechi Zhang, Dongsheng Sun, Kazuhiro Shimasaku, Jenny Greene, Kazushi Iwasawa, Kotaro Kohno, Tohru Nagao, Andreas Schulze, Takatoshi Shibuya, Miftahul Hilmi, Malte Schramm
&lt;br&gt;
We present deep Subaru/FOCAS spectra for two extreme emission line galaxies(EELGs) at $z\sim 1$ with strong {\sc[Oiii]}$\lambda$5007 emission lines,exhibiting equivalent widths (EWs) of $2905^{+946}_{-578}$ \AA\ and$2000^{+188}_{-159}$ \AA, comparable to those of EELGs at high redshifts thatare now routinely identified with JWST spectroscopy. Adding a similarly large{\sc [Oiii]} EW ($2508^{+1487}_{-689}$ \AA) EELG found at $z\sim 2$ in the JWSTCEERS survey to our sample, we explore for the physical origins of the large{\sc [Oiii]} EWs of these three galaxies with the Subaru spectra and variouspublic data including JWST/NIRSpec, NIRCam, and MIRI data. While there are noclear signatures of AGN identified by the optical line diagnostics, we findthat two out of two galaxies covered by the MIRI data show strong near-infraredexcess in the spectral energy distributions (SEDs) indicating obscured AGN.Because none of the three galaxies show clear broad H$\beta$ lines, the upperlimits on the flux ratios of broad-H$\beta$ to {\sc [Oiii]} lines are small,$\lesssim 0.15$ that are comparable with Seyfert $1.8-2.0$ galaxies. We conduct\texttt{Cloudy} modeling with the stellar and AGN incident spectra, allowing awide range of parameters including metallicities and ionization parameters. Wefind that the large {\sc [Oiii]} EWs are not self-consistently reproduced bythe spectra of stars or unobscured AGN, but obscured AGN that efficientlyproduces O$^{++}$ ionizing photons with weak nuclear and stellar continua thatare consistent with the SED shapes.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: submitted to ApJ
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.12198v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.12198v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Chenghao Zhu</author><pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 04:43:49 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12198v1</guid></item><item><title>Infrared Spectra of Solid-State Ethanolamine: Laboratory Data in Support  of JWST Observations</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12235v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
T. Suhasaria, S. M. Wee, R. Basalgète, S. A. Krasnokutski, C. Jäger, G. Perotti, Th. Henning
&lt;br&gt;
Ethanolamine (NH$_2$CH$_2$CH$_2$OH, EA) has been identified in the gas phaseof the ISM within molecular clouds. Although EA has not been directly observedin the molecular ice phase, a solid state formation mechanism has beenproposed. However, the current literature lacks an estimation of the infraredband strengths of EA ices. We conducted an experimental investigation of solidEA ice at low temperatures to ascertain its infrared band strengths, phasetransition temperature, and multilayer binding energy. The commonly used laserinterferometry method was not applied. Infrared band strengths were determinedusing three distinct methods. The obtained lab spectrum of EA was compared withthe publicly available MIRI MRS James Webb Space Telescope observations towarda low mass protostar. The phase transition temperature for EA ice falls withinthe range of 175 to 185 K. Among the discussed methods, the simple pressuregauge method provides a reasonable estimate of band strength. We derive a bandstrength value of about $1\times10^{-17}$ cm molecule$^{-1}$ for the NH$_2$bending mode in the EA molecules. Additionally, temperature-programmeddesorption analysis yielded a multilayer desorption energy of 0.61$\pm$0.01 eV.By comparing the laboratory data documented in this study with the JWSTspectrum of the low mass protostar IRAS 2A, an upper-limit for the EA iceabundances was derived.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 8 pages, 5 figures
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.12235v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.12235v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>T. Suhasaria</author><pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 05:53:26 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12235v1</guid></item><item><title>Galaxy Mass Modelling from Multi-Wavelength JWST Strong Lens Analysis:  Dark Matter Substructure, Angular Mass Complexity, or Both?</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12987v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Samuel C. Lange, Aristeidis Amvrosiadis, James W. Nightingale, Qiuhan He, Carlos S. Frenk, Andrew Robertson, Shaun Cole, Richard Massey, Xiaoyue Cao, Ran Li, Kaihao Wang
&lt;br&gt;
We analyze two galaxy-scale strong gravitational lenses, SPT0418-47 andSPT2147-50, using JWST NIRCam imaging across multiple filters. To account forangular complexity in the lens mass distribution, we introduce multipoleperturbations with orders $m=1, 3, 4$. Our results show strong evidence forangular mass complexity in SPT2147, with multipole strengths of 0.3-1.7 $\%$for $m=3, 4$ and 2.4-9.5 $\%$ for $m=1$, while SPT0418 shows no suchpreference. We also test lens models that include a dark matter substructure,finding a strong preference for a substructure in SPT2147-50 with a Bayesfactor (log-evidence change) of $\sim 60$ when multipoles are not included.Including multipoles reduces the Bayes factor to $\sim 11$, still correspondingto a $5\sigma$ detection of a subhalo with an NFW mass of$\log_{10}(M_{200}/M_{\odot}) = 10.87\substack{+0.53\\ -0.71}$. WhileSPT2147-50 may represent the fourth detection of a dark matter substructure ina strong lens, further analysis is needed to confirm that the signal is not dueto systematics associated with the lens mass model.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 16 pages, 11 figures, submitted to MNRAS
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.12987v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.12987v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Samuel C. Lange</author><pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 20:32:47 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12987v1</guid></item><item><title>Lyman Continuum leakage from massive leaky starbursts: A different class  of emitters?</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13254v1</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
Namrata Roy, Timothy Heckman, Alaina Henry, John Chisholm, Sophia Flury, Claus Leitherer, Matthew J. Hayes, Anne Jaskot, Zhiyuan Ji, Daniel Schaerer, Bingjie Wang, Sanchayeeta Borthakur, Xinfeng Xu, Göran Östlin
&lt;br&gt;
The origin of Lyman Continuum (LyC) photons responsible for reionizing theuniverse remains a mystery, with the fraction of escaping LyC photons fromgalaxies at z$\sim$ 6 to 12 being highly uncertain. While direct detection ofLyC photons from this epoch is hindered by absorption from the intergalacticmedium, lower redshift analogs offer a promising avenue to study LyC leakage.We present Hubble Space Telescope Cosmic Origins Spectrograph (HST COS)observations of five low redshift (z$\sim$ 0.3) massive starburst galaxies,selected for their high stellar mass and weak [SII] nebular emission - anindirect tracer of LyC escape. Three of the five galaxies show LyC leakage,highlighting the reliability of weak [SII] as a tracer, especially in light ofrecent JWST discoveries of z $&gt;$ 5 galaxies with similarly weak [SII] emission.The dust corrected LyC escape fractions, which represent the LyC photons thatwould escape in the absence of dust, range from 33% to 84%. However, theabsolute escape fractions, which show the LyC photons escaping after passingthrough both neutral hydrogen absorption and dust attenuation, aresignificantly lower, ranging between 1% and 3%. This suggests that while thegalaxies are nearly optically thin to HI, their high dust content significantlysuppresses LyC photon escape. These [SII] weak, massive leakers are distinctfrom typical low-redshift LyC emitters, showing higher metallicity, lowerionization states, more dust extinction and higher star formation surfacedensities. This suggests that these galaxies constitute a distinct population,likely governed by a different mechanism facilitating LyC photon escape. Wepropose that the feedback-driven winds in these compact starbursts createionized channels through which LyC photons escape, aligning with a picket-fencemodel.
&lt;br&gt;
Comments: 16 pages, 10 figures, 1 Table
&lt;br&gt; PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.13254v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.13254v1 &lt;/a&gt;
]]</description><author>Namrata Roy</author><pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 07:21:22 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13254v1</guid></item></channel></rss>