<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>JWST arXiv Feed (feed)</title><link>https://github.com/gbrammer/arxiv-to-rss</link><description>Custom arXiv Query of JWST articles</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2024 18:07:37 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.1.1</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Dark Energy Black Holes with Intermediate Masses at High Redshifts: an  earlier generation of Quasars and observations</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2207.02143v3</link><description>Anupam Singh
    &lt;p&gt;
    Dark Energy is the largest fraction of the energy density of our Universe -yet it remains one of the enduring enigmas of our times. Here we show that DarkEnergy can be used to solve 2 tantalizing mysteries of the observable universe.We build on existing models of Dark Energy linked to neutrino masses. In thesemodels Dark Energy can undergo Phase Transitions and form Black Holes. Here welook at the implications of the family structure of neutrinos for the phasetransitions in dark energy and associated peaks in black hole formation. It hasbeen previously shown that one of these peaks in Black Hole formation isassociated with the observed peak in Quasar formation. Here, we predict thatthere will also be an earlier peak in the Dark Energy Black Holes at highredshifts. These Dark Energy Black Holes formed at high redshifts areIntermediate Mass Black Holes (IMBHs).These Dark Energy Black Holes at largeredshift can help explain both the EDGES observations and the observations oflarge Supermassive Black Holes (SMBHs) at redshifts $z \sim 7$. The existenceof an earlier phase of Dark Energy Black Holes take care of some currentchallenges to theory implied by existing astronomical data and also helps uslook for these Dark Energy Black Holes at high redshifts as predicted herethrough targeted searches for these Black Holes at the redshifts $z \sim 18$.There is a slight dependence of the location of the peak on the lightestneutrino mass - so the peak may be located at a slightly lower value of theredshift. This may actually enable a measurement of the lightest neutrino mass.Finding these Dark Energy Black Holes of Intermediate Mass should be within thereach of upcoming observations - particularly with the James Webb SpaceTelescope - but perhaps also through the use of other innovative techniquesfocusing specifically on the redshifts around $z \sim 18$.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: As embargo period is over - this version corresponds to the final  published version
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.02143v3" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.02143v3 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Anupam Singh</author><pubDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2022 05:04:17 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2207.02143v3</guid></item><item><title>JADES + JEMS: A Detailed Look at the Buildup of Central Stellar Cores  and Suppression of Star Formation in Galaxies at Redshifts 3 &lt; z &lt; 4.5</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.18518v2</link><description>Zhiyuan Ji, Christina C. Williams, Sandro Tacchella, Katherine A. Suess, William M. Baker, Stacey Alberts, Andrew J. Bunker, Benjamin D. Johnson, Brant Robertson, Fengwu Sun, Daniel J. Eisenstein, Marcia Rieke, Michael V. Maseda, Kevin Hainline, Ryan Hausen, George Rieke, Christopher N. A. Willmer, Eiichi Egami, Irene Shivaei, Stefano Carniani, Stephane Charlot, Jacopo Chevallard, Emma Curtis-Lake, Tobias J. Looser, Roberto Maiolino, Chris Willott, Zuyi Chen, Jakob M. Helton, Jianwei Lyu, Erica Nelson, Rachana Bhatawdekar, Kristan Boyett, Lester Sandles
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present a spatially resolved study of stellar populations in 6 galaxieswith stellar masses $M_*\sim10^{10}M_\odot$ at $z\sim3.7$ using 14-filterJWST/NIRCam imaging from the JADES and JEMS surveys. The 6 galaxies arevisually selected to have clumpy substructures with distinct colors overrest-frame $3600-4100\r{A}$, including a red, dominant stellar core that isclose to their stellar-light centroids. With 23-filter photometry from HST toJWST, we measure the stellar-population properties of individual structuralcomponents via SED fitting using Prospector. We find that the central stellarcores are $\gtrsim2$ times more massive than the Toomre mass, indicating theymay not form via single in-situ fragmentation. The stellar cores have stellarages of $0.4-0.7$ Gyr that are similar to the timescale of clump inwardmigration due to dynamical friction, suggesting that they likely instead formedthrough the coalescence of giant stellar clumps. While they have not yetquenched, the 6 galaxies are below the star-forming main sequence by $0.2-0.7$dex. Within each galaxy, we find that the specific star formation rate is lowerin the central stellar core, and the stellar-mass surface density of the coreis already similar to quenched galaxies of the same masses and redshifts.Meanwhile, the stellar ages of the cores are either comparable to or youngerthan the extended, smooth parts of the galaxies. Our findings are consistentwith model predictions of the gas-rich compaction scenario for the buildup ofgalaxies' central regions at high redshifts. We are likely witnessing thecoeval formation of dense central cores, along with the onset of galaxy-widequenching at $z&gt;3$.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 34 pages, 18 figures, ApJ in press
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2305.18518v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2305.18518v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Zhiyuan Ji</author><pubDate>Mon, 29 May 2023 18:00:01 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2305.18518v2</guid></item><item><title>Enhanced Early Galaxy Formation in JWST from Axion Dark Matter?</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2307.10302v2</link><description>Simeon Bird, Chia-Feng Chang, Yanou Cui, Daneng Yang
    &lt;p&gt;
    We demonstrate that enhanced early galaxy formation can generically arise inaxion-like particle (ALP) dark matter (DM) models with a delayed onset of axionfield oscillation. In these models, the formation of localized massive objectsenhances structure formation, potentially addressing the excess recentlyobserved by the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST), while remaining consistentwith existing constraints. We identify viable parameter space with the ALP massin the range of $10^{-22}~{\rm eV}&lt;m_a&lt;10^{-19}~\rm eV$. In addition, we showthat the ALP parameter regions of interest can lead to intriguing complementarysignatures in the small-scale structure of DM halos and existing experimentalsearches for ALPs.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 6 pages, 4 figures
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2307.10302v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2307.10302v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Simeon Bird</author><pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2023 18:00:05 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2307.10302v2</guid></item><item><title>El Gordo needs El Anzuelo: Probing the structure of cluster members with  multi-band extended arcs in JWST data</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2402.18636v2</link><description>A. Galan, G. B. Caminha, J. Knollmüller, J. Roth, S. H. Suyu
    &lt;p&gt;
    Gravitational lensing by galaxy clusters involves hundreds of galaxies over alarge redshift range and increases the likelihood of rare phenomena(supernovae, dark substructures, etc.). We present the detailed analysis of\elanz, a prominent quintuply imaged dusty star-forming galaxy ($\zs=2.29$),mainly lensed by three members of the massive galaxy clusterACT-CL\,J0102$-$4915, also known as \elgor ($z_{\rm d}=0.87$). We leverageJWST/NIRCam images, which contain lensing features that were unseen in previousHST images, using a Bayesian, multi-wavelength, differentiable andGPU-accelerated modeling framework that combines \herculens (lens modeling) and\nifty (field model and inference) software packages. For one of thedeflectors, we complement lensing constraints with stellar kinematics measuredfrom VLT/MUSE data. In our lens model, we explicitly include the massdistribution of the cluster, locally corrected by a constant shear field. Wefind that the two main deflectors (L1 and L2) have logarithmic mass densityslopes steeper than isothermal, with $\gamma_{\rm L1} = 2.23\pm0.05$ and$\gamma_{\rm L2} = 2.21\pm0.04$. We argue that such steep density profiles canarise due to tidally truncated mass distributions, which we probe thanks to thecluster lensing boost and the strong asymmetry of the lensing configuration.Moreover, our three-dimensional source model captures most of the surfacebrightness of the lensed galaxy, revealing a clump with a maximum diameter of$400$ parsecs at the source redshift, visible at wavelengths $\lambda_{\rmrest}\gtrsim0.6$ $\mu$m. Finally, we caution on using point-like featureswithin extended arcs to constrain galaxy-scale lens models before securing themwith extended arc modeling.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 27 pages, published in Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics (September 2024)
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2402.18636v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2402.18636v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>A. Galan</author><pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2024 19:00:01 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2402.18636v2</guid></item><item><title>HELLO project: High-$z$ Evolution of Large and Luminous Objects</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2403.03985v2</link><description>Stefan Waterval, Andrea V. Macciò, Tobias Buck, Aura Obreja, Changhyun Cho, Zehao Jin, Benjamin L. Davis, Keri L. Dixon, Xi Kang
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present the High-$z$ Evolution of Large and Luminous Objects (HELLO)project, a set of $\sim\!30$ high-resolution cosmological simulations aimed tostudy Milky Way analogues ($M_\star\sim10^{10-11}$\,\Msun) at high redshift($z\sim [2-4]$). Based on the Numerical Investigation of a HundredAstrophysical Objects (NIHAO), HELLO features an updated scheme for chemicalenrichment and the addition of local photoionization feedback. Independently ofredshift and mass, our galaxies exhibit a smooth progression along the starformation main sequence until $M_\star \sim\!10^{10.5}$, around which oursample at $z \sim 4$ remains mostly unperturbed while the most massive galaxiesat $z \sim 2$ reach their peak star formation rate (SFR) and its subsequentdecline, due to a mix of gas consumption and stellar feedback. While AGNfeedback remains subdominant with respect to stellar feedback for energydeposition, its localised nature likely adds to the physical processes leadingto declining SFRs. The phase in which a galaxy in our mass range can be foundat a given redshift is set by its gas reservoir and assembly history. Finally,our galaxies are in excellent agreement with various scaling relations observedwith the \textit{Hubble Space Telescope} and the \textit{James Webb SpaceTelescope}, and hence can be used to provide the theoretical framework tointerpret current and future observations from these facilities and shed lighton the transition from star-forming to quiescent galaxies.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 21 pages, 15 figures, 3 tables, published in MNRAS
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2403.03985v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2403.03985v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Stefan Waterval</author><pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2024 19:00:14 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2403.03985v2</guid></item><item><title>A unified model for the clustering of quasars and galaxies at  $z\approx6$</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2403.12140v2</link><description>Elia Pizzati, Joseph F. Hennawi, Joop Schaye, Matthieu Schaller, Anna-Christina Eilers, Feige Wang, Carlos S. Frenk, Willem Elbers, John C. Helly, Ruari Mackenzie, Jorryt Matthee, Rongmon Bordoloi, Daichi Kashino, Rohan P. Naidu, Minghao Yue
    &lt;p&gt;
    Recent observations from the EIGER JWST program have measured for the firsttime the quasar-galaxy cross-correlation function at $z\approx6$. Theauto-correlation function of faint $z\approx6$ quasars was also recentlyestimated. These measurements provide key insights into the properties ofquasars and galaxies at high redshift and their relation with the host darkmatter halos. In this work, we interpret these data building upon an empiricalquasar population model that has been applied successfully to quasar clusteringand demographic measurements at $z\approx2-4$. We make use of a new,large-volume N-body simulation with more than a trillion particles,FLAMINGO-10k, to model quasars and galaxies simultaneously. We successfullyreproduce observations of $z\approx6$ quasars and galaxies (i.e., theirclustering properties and luminosity functions), and infer key quantities suchas their luminosity-halo mass relation, the mass function of their host halos,and their duty cycle/occupation fraction. Our key findings are: (i) quasarsreside on average in $\approx10^{12.5}\,{\rm M}_\odot$ halos (corresponding to$\approx5\sigma$ fluctuations in the initial conditions of the linear densityfield), but the distribution of host halo masses is quite broad; (ii) the dutycycle of (UV-bright) quasar activity is relatively low ($\approx1\%$); (iii)galaxies (that are bright in [OIII]) live in much smaller halos($\approx10^{10.9}\,{\rm M}_\odot$) and have a larger duty cycle (occupationfraction) of $\approx13\%$. Finally, we focus on the inferred properties ofquasars and present a homogeneous analysis of their evolution with redshift.The picture that emerges reveals a strong evolution of the host halo mass andduty cycle of quasars at $z\approx2-6$, and calls for new investigations of therole of quasar activity across cosmic time.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Accepted for publication in MNRAS; 15 pages, 4 figures
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2403.12140v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2403.12140v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Elia Pizzati</author><pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2024 18:00:17 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2403.12140v2</guid></item><item><title>GA-NIFS: An extremely nitrogen-loud and chemically stratified galaxy at  $z\sim 5.55$</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04148v2</link><description>Xihan Ji, Hannah Übler, Roberto Maiolino, Francesco D'Eugenio, Santiago Arribas, Andrew J. Bunker, Stéphane Charlot, Michele Perna, Bruno Rodríguez Del Pino, Torsten Böker, Giovanni Cresci, Mirko Curti, Nimisha Kumari, Isabella Lamperti
    &lt;p&gt;
    We report the chemical abundance pattern of GS\_3073, a galaxy at $z=5.55$which was previously confirmed to host an overmassive active black hole, byleveraging the detection of about 40 emission lines, combining JWST/NIRSpecobservations and ground-based (VLT/VIMOS) data. Based on the rest-frame UVemission lines, which trace high-density ($\sim 10^5~{\rm cm}^{-3}$) and highlyionized gas, we derived an abundance ratio of $\rm log(N/O) =0.42^{+0.13}_{-0.10}$. At an estimated metallicity of $0.2~Z_{\odot}$, this isthe most extreme nitrogen-rich object found by JWST thus far. In comparison,the relative carbon abundance derived from the rest-frame UV emission lines is$\rm log(C/O) = -0.38^{+0.13}_{-0.11}$, which is not significantly higher thanthose in local galaxies and stars with similar metallicities. We also foundpotential detection of coronal lines including [FeVII]$\lambda 6087$ and[FeXIV]$\lambda 5303$, both blended with [CaV]. We inferred a range of Feabundances compatible with those in local stars and galaxies. Overall, thechemical abundance pattern of GS\_3073 is compatible with enrichment bysuper-massive stars with $M_* \gtrsim 1000~M_\odot$, asymptotic giant branch(AGB) stars, or Wolf-Rayet (WR) stars. Interestingly, when using opticalemission lines which trace lower density ($\sim 10^3~{\rm cm}^{-3}$) and lowerionization gas, we found a sub-solar N/O ratio. We interpret the difference inN/O derived from UV lines and optical lines as evidence for a stratifiedsystem, where the inner and denser region is both more chemically enriched andmore ionized. Taking this luminous, well-studied system as a benchmark, ourresults suggest that nitrogen loudness in high-$z$ galaxies is confined to thecentral, dense, and highly ionized region of the galaxies, while the bulk ofthe galaxies evolves more normally.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 28 pages, 15 figures, accepted for publication in MNRAS
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.04148v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.04148v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Xihan Ji</author><pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2024 14:51:03 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04148v2</guid></item><item><title>JWST MIRI detections of H$α$ and [O III] and direct metallicity  measurement of the $z=10.17$ lensed galaxy MACS0647$-$JD</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.16200v4</link><description>Tiger Yu-Yang Hsiao, Javier Álvarez-Márquez, Dan Coe, Alejandro Crespo Gómez, Abdurro'uf, Pratika Dayal, Rebecca L. Larson, Arjan Bik, Carmen Blanco-Prieto, Luis Colina, Pablo Guillermo Pérez-González, Luca Costantin, Carlota Prieto-Jiménez, Angela Adamo, Larry D. Bradley, Christopher J. Conselice, Seiji Fujimoto, Lukas J. Furtak, Taylor A. Hutchison, Bethan L. James, Yolanda Jiménez-Teja, Intae Jung, Vasily Kokorev, Matilde Mingozzi, Colin Norman, Massimo Ricotti, Jane R. Rigby, Keren Sharon, Eros Vanzella, Brian Welch, Xinfeng Xu, Erik Zackrisson, Adi Zitrin
    &lt;p&gt;
    JWST spectroscopy has revolutionized our understanding of galaxies in theearly universe. Covering wavelengths up to $5.3\,{\rm \mu m}$, NIRSpec candetect rest-frame optical emission lines H$\alpha$ out to $z = 7$ and [O III]to $z = 9.5$. Observing these lines in more distant galaxies requires longerwavelength spectroscopy with MIRI. Here we present MIRI MRS IFU observations ofthe lensed galaxy merger MACS0647$-$JD at $z = 10.165$. With exposure times of4.2 hours in each of two bands, we detect H$\alpha$ at $9\sigma$, [OIII]$\,\lambda5008$ at $11\sigma$, and [O III]$\,\lambda4960$ at $3\sigma$.Combined with previously reported NIRSpec spectroscopy that yields sevenemission lines including the auroral line [O III]$\,\lambda4363$, we presentthe first direct metallicity measurement of a $z &gt; 10$ galaxy: $12+{\rmlog(O/H)}= 7.79\pm0.09$, or $0.13^{+0.02}_{-0.03}\,Z_{\odot}$. This is similarto galaxies at $z \sim 4 - 9$ with direct metallicity measurements, thoughhigher than expected given the high specific star formation rate ${\rm log(sSFR/ yr^{-1})} = -7.4 \pm 0.3$. We further constrain the ionization parameter${\rm log}(U)$ = $-1.9 \pm 0.1$, ionizing photon production efficiency ${\rmlog}(\xi_{\rm ion})$ = $25.3\pm0.1$, and star formation rate$5.0\pm0.6\,M_{\odot}/{\rm yr}$ within the past $10\,{\rm Myr}$. Theseobservations demonstrate the combined power of JWST NIRSpec and MIRI forstudying galaxies in the first $500$ million years.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 16 pages, 8 figures, accepted for publication in ApJ
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.16200v4" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.16200v4 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Tiger Yu-Yang Hsiao</author><pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2024 20:53:16 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.16200v4</guid></item><item><title>Dynamics of a Galaxy at z &gt; 10 Explored by JWST Integral Field  Spectroscopy: Hints of Rotating Disk Suggesting Weak Feedback</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.16963v3</link><description>Yi Xu, Masami Ouchi, Hidenobu Yajima, Hajime Fukushima, Yuichi Harikane, Yuki Isobe, Kimihiko Nakajima, Minami Nakane, Yoshiaki Ono, Hiroya Umeda, Hiroto Yanagisawa, Yechi Zhang
    &lt;p&gt;
    We investigate the dynamics of GN-z11, a luminous galaxy at $z=10.60$,carefully analyzing the public deep integral field spectroscopy (IFS) datataken with JWST NIRSpec IFU. While the observations of the IFS data originallytargeted a He II clump near GN-z11, we find that CIII]$\lambda\lambda$1907,1909emission from ionized gas at GN-z11 is bright and spatially extendedsignificantly beyond the point-spread function (PSF). The spatially extendedCIII emission of GN-z11 shows a velocity gradient, red- and blue-shiftedcomponents in the north and south directions, respectively, which cannot beexplained by the variation of [CIII]$\lambda$1907/CIII]$\lambda$1909 lineratios. Assuming the velocity gradient is produced by disk rotation, we performforward modeling with GalPak$^{3D}$, including the effects of PSF smearing andline blending, and obtain a rotation velocity of $v_{rot}=257^{+138}_{-117}$ kms$^{-1}$, a velocity dispersion of $\sigma_v=91^{+18}_{-32}$ km s$^{-1}$, and aratio of $v_{rot}/\sigma_v=2.83^{+1.82}_{-1.41}$. The $v_{rot}/\sigma_v$ valuewould suggest a rotation-dominated disk existing at $z&gt;10$ albeit with thelarge uncertainties. The rotation velocity agrees with those of numericalsimulations predicting a rotating disk formed in the early universe under thecondition of mass compaction and weak feedback. While the velocity gradient isconsistent with the rotating disk solution, we recognize that galactic outflowscan also explain the velocity gradient as well as the extended morphology andthe high velocity dispersion found in the outskirt. Higher S/N and resolutiondata are necessary to conclude the physical origin of the velocity gradient inGN-z11.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Accepted for publication in ApJ
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.16963v3" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.16963v3 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Yi Xu</author><pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2024 18:24:03 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.16963v3</guid></item><item><title>JWST FRESCO: a comprehensive census of H$β$+[OIII] emitters at  6.8&lt;z&lt;9.0 in the GOODS fields</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05111v3</link><description>R. A. Meyer, P. A. Oesch, E. Giovinazzo, A. Weibel, G. Brammer, J. Matthee, R. P. Naidu, R. J. Bouwens, J. Chisholm, A. Covelo-Paz, Y. Fudamoto, M. Maseda, E. Nelson, I. Shivaei, M. Xiao, T. Herard-Demanche, G. D. Illingworth, J. Kerutt, I. Kramarenko, I. Labbe, E. Leonova, D. Magee, J. Matharu, G. Prieto Lyon, N. Reddy, D. Schaerer, A. Shapley, M. Stefanon, M. A. Wozniak, S. Wuyts
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present the census of H$\beta$+[OIII] 4960,5008 \AA emitters at 6.8&lt;z&lt;9.0from the JWST FRESCO survey over 124 arcmin$^2$ in the GOODS-North andGOODS-South fields. Our unbiased spectroscopic search results in 137spectroscopically-confirmed galaxies at $6.8&lt;z&lt;9.0$ with observed [OIII] fluxes$f_{[OIII]}\gtrsim 1\times 10^{-18}\ \rm{ergs}\ \rm{s}^{-1} \ \rm{cm}^{-2}$.The rest-frame optical line ratios of the median stacked spectrum (median$M_{\rm{UV}}=-19.65^{+0.59}_{-1.05}$) indicate negligible dust attenuation, lowmetallicity ($12+\log(\rm{O/H})= 7.2-7.7$) and a high ionisation parameter$\log_{10}U \simeq -2.5$. We find a factor $\times 1.3$ difference in thenumber density of $6.8&lt;z&lt;9.0$ galaxies between GOODS-South and GOODS-North,which is caused by a single overdensity at $7.0&lt;z&lt;7.2$ in GOODS-North. Thebright end of the UV luminosity function of spectroscopically-confirmed [OIII]emitters is in good agreement with HST dropout-selected samples. Discrepanciesbetween the observed [OIII] LF, [OIII]/UV ratio and [OIII] equivalent widths,and that predicted by theoretical models, suggest burstier star-formationhistories and/or more heterogeneous metallicity and ionising conditions in$z&gt;7$ galaxies. We report a rapid decline of the [OIII] luminosity density at$z\gtrsim 6-7$ which cannot be explained by the evolution of the cosmicstar-formation rate density. Finally we find that FRESCO detects in only 2hgalaxies likely accounting for $\sim 10-20\%$ of the ionising budget at $z=7-8$(assuming an escape fraction of 10%), raising the prospect of directlydetecting a significant fraction of the sources of reionisation with JWST.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 20 pages + appendices. Accepted in MNRAS. Public catalogue release at  https://github.com/rameyer/fresco. V3: matching accepted version
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2405.05111v3" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2405.05111v3 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>R. A. Meyer</author><pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2024 15:07:57 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05111v3</guid></item><item><title>JADES -- The Rosetta Stone of JWST-discovered AGN: deciphering the  intriguing nature of early AGN</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.08643v2</link><description>Ignas Juodžbalis, Xihan Ji, Roberto Maiolino, Francesco D'Eugenio, Jan Scholtz, Guido Risaliti, Andrew C. Fabian, Giovanni Mazzolari, Roberto Gilli, Isabella Prandoni, Santiago Arribas, Andrew J. Bunker, Stefano Carniani, Stéphane Charlot, Emma Curtis-Lake, Anna de Graaff, Kevin Hainline, Eleonora Parlanti, Michele Perna, Pablo G. Pérez-González, Brant Robertson, Sandro Tacchella, Hannah Übler, Christina C. Williams, Chris Willott, Joris Witstok
    &lt;p&gt;
    JWST has discovered a large population of Active Galactic Nuclei (AGN) athigh redshift. Many of these newly discovered AGN have broad permitted lines(typically H$\alpha$), but are extremely weak in the X-rays. Here we presentthe NIRSpec spectrum of the most extreme of these objects, GN-28074, an AGN at$z=2.26$ with prominent Balmer, Paschen and \HeI broad lines, and with thehighest limit on the bolometric to X-ray luminosity ratio among allspectroscopically confirmed AGN in GOODS. This source is also characterized bya mid-IR excess, most likely associated with the AGN torus' hot dust. The highbolometric luminosity and moderate redshift of this AGN allow us to explore itsproperties more in depth relative to other JWST-discovered AGN. The NIRSpecspectrum reveals prominent, slightly blueshifted absorption of H$\alpha$,H$\beta$ and \HeI$\lambda$10830. The Balmer absorption lines require gas withdensities of $n_{\rm H}&gt; 10^8~{\rm cm}^{-3}$, inconsistent with an ISM origin,but fully consistent with clouds in the Broad Line Region (BLR). This findingsuggests that at least part of the X-ray weakness is due to high (Comptonthick) X-ray absorption by (dust-free) clouds in the BLR, or in its outer,slowly outflowing regions. GN-28074 is also extremely radio-weak. The radioweakness can also be explained in terms of absorption, as the inferred densityof the clouds responsible for H$\alpha$ absorption makes them optically thickto radio emission through free-free absorption. Alternatively, in this andother JWST-discovered AGN, the nuclear magnetic field may have not developedproperly yet, resulting both in intrinsically weak radio emission and also lackof hot corona, hence intrinsic X-ray weakness. Finally, we show that recentlyproposed scenarios, invoking hyper-dense and ultra-metal-poor outflows or Ramanscattering to explain the broad H$\alpha$, are completely ruled out.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 21 pages 8 figures in main text. Accepted by MNRAS, updated to  accepted version
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2407.08643v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2407.08643v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Ignas Juodžbalis</author><pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2024 16:23:28 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.08643v2</guid></item><item><title>Low [O/Fe] Ratio in a Luminous Galaxy at the Early Cosmic Epoch  ($z&gt;10$): Signature of Short Delay Time or Bright Hypernovae/Pair-Instability  Supernovae?</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14470v3</link><description>Minami Nakane, Masami Ouchi, Kimihiko Nakajima, Yuichi Harikane, Nozomu Tominaga, Koh Takahashi, Daichi Kashino, Hiroto Yanagisawa, Kuria Watanabe, Ken'ichi Nomoto, Yuki Isobe, Moka Nishigaki, Miho N. Ishigaki, Yoshiaki Ono, Yui Takeda
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present an [O/Fe] ratio of a luminous galaxy GN-z11 at $z=10.60$ derivedwith the deep public JWST/NIRSpec data. We fit the medium-resolution grating(G140M, G235M, and G395M) data with the model spectra consisting ofBPASS-stellar and CLOUDY-nebular spectra in the rest-frame UV wavelength rangeswith Fe absorption lines, carefully masking out the other emission andabsorption lines in the same manner as previous studies conducted for lowerredshift ($z\sim 2-6$) galaxies with oxygen abundance measurements. We obtainan Fe-rich abundance ratio $\mathrm{[O/Fe]}=-0.37^{+0.43}_{-0.22}$, which isconfirmed with the independent deep prism data as well as by the classic 1978index method. This [O/Fe] measurement is lower than measured for star-forminggalaxies at $z\sim 2-3$. Because $z=10.60$ is an early epoch after the Big Bang($\sim 430$ Myr) and the first star formation (likely $\sim 200$ Myr), it isdifficult to produce Fe by Type Ia supernovae (SNeIa) requiring sufficientdelay time for white-dwarf formation and gas accretion. The Fe-rich abundanceratio in GN-z11 suggests that the delay time is short, or that the major Feenrichment is not accomplished by SNeIa but bright hypernovae (BrHNe) and/orpair-instability supernovae (PISNe), where the yield models of BrHNe and PISNeexplain Fe, Ne, and O abundance ratios of GN-z11. The [O/Fe] measurement is nottoo low to rule out the connection between GN-z11 and globular clusters (GCs)previously suggested by the nitrogen abundance, but rather supports theconnection with a GC population at high [N/O] if a metal dilution processexists.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 13 pages, 11 figures, accepted for publication in ApJ
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2407.14470v3" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2407.14470v3 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Minami Nakane</author><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 17:16:46 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14470v3</guid></item><item><title>Mildly Super-Eddington Accretion Onto Slowly-Spinning Black Holes  Explains the X-Ray Weakness of the Little Red Dots</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.15915v2</link><description>Fabio Pacucci, Ramesh Narayan
    &lt;p&gt;
    JWST has revealed a population of low-luminosity AGN at $z&gt;4$ in compact, redhosts (the "Little Red Dots", or LRDs), which are largely undetected in X-rays.We investigate this phenomenon using GRRMHD simulations of super-Eddingtonaccretion onto a SMBH with $M_\bullet=10^7 \,\rm M_\odot$ at $z\sim6$,representing the median population; the SEDs that we obtain are intrinsicallyX-ray weak. The highest levels of X-ray weakness occur in SMBHs accreting atmildly super-Eddington rates ($1.4&lt;f_{\rm Edd}&lt;4$) with zero spin, viewed atangles $&gt;30^\circ$ from the pole. X-ray bolometric corrections in the observed$2-10$ keV band reach $\sim10^4$ at $z=6$, $\sim5$ times higher than thehighest constraint from X-ray stacking. Most SEDs are extraordinarily steep andsoft in the X-rays (median photon index $\Gamma=3.1$, mode of $\Gamma=4.4$).SEDs strong in the X-rays have harder spectra with a high-energy bump whenviewed near the hot ($&gt;10^8$ K) and highly-relativistic jet, whereas X-ray weakSEDs lack this feature. Viewing a SMBH within $10^\circ$ of its pole, wherebeaming enhances the X-ray emission, has a $\sim1.5\%$ probability, matchingthe LRD X-ray detection rate. Next-generation observatories like AXIS willdetect X-ray weak LRDs at $z\sim6$ from any viewing angle. Although many SMBHsin the LRDs are already estimated to accrete at super-Eddington rates, ourmodel explains $50\%$ of their population by requiring that their masses areoverestimated by a mere factor of $\sim3$. In summary, we suggest that LRDshost slowly spinning SMBHs accreting at mildly super-Eddington rates, withlarge covering factors and broad emission lines enhanced by strong winds,providing a self-consistent explanation for their X-ray weakness andcomplementing other models.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Accepted for publication in The Astrophysical Journal. 18 pages, 7  figures
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2407.15915v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2407.15915v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Fabio Pacucci</author><pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2024 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.15915v2</guid></item><item><title>Type Ia Supernovae from First-generation Stars</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19357v2</link><description>Zhenwei Li, Lifan Wang, Zhanwen Han, Xuefei Chen
    &lt;p&gt;
    Type Ia Supernovae (SNe Ia) discovered at redshift $z\lesssim2.5$ arepresumed to be produced from Population (Pop) I/II stars. {In this work, weinvestigate the production of SNe Ia from Pop III binaries in the cosmologicalframework. We derive the SN Ia rate as a function of redshift under atheoretical context for the production of first generation stars and emanatethe likelihood of their detection by the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST).}{Assuming the initial stellar mass function (IMF) favors low-mass stars as fromrecent numerical simulations, we found Pop III stars may give rise to aconsiderable amount of SNe Ia at high redshift and Pop III stars may even bethe dominant SN Ia producer at z $\gtrsim 6$.} {In an optimistic scenario, weexpect $\sim 1(2)$ SNe Ia from Pop III stars at $z\approx 4(5)$ for a survey ofarea $300 \;\rm arcmin^2$ during a $3\;\rm yr$ period with JWST. The samesurvey may record more than $\sim 400$ SNe Ia at lower redshift ($z\lesssim2.5$) but with only about one of them from Pop III progenitors. There will be$\sim 6$ Pop III SNe Ia in the same field of view at redshifts of $5-10$.}Observational constraints on SN Ia rates at the redshift range of $5-10$ canplace crucial constraints on the IMF of Pop III stars.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 19 pages, 7 Figures. Minor updates to match the published version
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2407.19357v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2407.19357v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Zhenwei Li</author><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2024 01:06:02 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19357v2</guid></item><item><title>MSA-3D: dissecting galaxies at z~1 with high spatial and spectral  resolution</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08350v2</link><description>Ivana Barišić, Tucker Jones, Kris Mortensen, Themiya Nanayakkara, Yuguang Chen, Ryan Sanders, James S. Bullock, Kevin Bundy, Claude-André Faucher-Giguère, Karl Glazebrook, Alaina Henry, Mengting Ju, Matthew Malkan, Takahiro Morishita, Danail Obreschkow, Namrata Roy, Juan M. Espejo Salcedo, Alice E. Shapley, Tommaso Treu, Xin Wang, Kyle B. Westfall
    &lt;p&gt;
    Integral field spectroscopy (IFS) is a powerful tool for understanding theformation of galaxies across cosmic history. We present the observing strategyand first results of MSA-3D, a novel JWST program using multi-objectspectroscopy in a slit-stepping strategy to produce IFS data cubes. The programobserved 43 normal star-forming galaxies at redshifts $0.5 \lesssim z \lesssim1.5$, corresponding to the epoch when spiral thin-disk galaxies of the modernHubble sequence are thought to emerge, obtaining kpc-scale maps of rest-frameoptical nebular emission lines with spectral resolution $R\simeq2700$. Here wedescribe the multiplexed slit-stepping method which is $&gt;15$ times moreefficient than the NIRSpec IFS mode for our program. As an example of the dataquality, we present a case study of an individual galaxy at $z=1.104$ (stellarmass $M_{*} = 10^{10.3}~M_{\odot}$, star formation rate~$=3~M_{\odot}$yr$^{-1}$) with prominent face-on spiral structure. We show that the galaxyexhibits a rotationally supported disk with moderate velocity dispersion($\sigma = 36^{+5}_{-4}$~\kms), a negative radial metallicity gradient($-0.020\pm0.002$~dex\,kpc$^{-1}$), a dust attenuation gradient, and anexponential star formation rate density profile which closely matches thestellar continuum. These properties are characteristic of local spirals,indicating that mature galaxies are in place at $z\sim1$. We also describe thecustomized data reduction and original cube-building software pipelines whichwe have developed to exploit the powerful slit-stepping technique. Our resultsdemonstrate the ability of JWST slit-stepping to study galaxy populations atintermediate to high redshifts, with data quality similar to current surveys ofthe $z\sim0.1$ universe.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 24 pages, 12 figures, 1 table; submitted to ApJ, comments welcome.  Our custom designed data reduction pipeline (MSA3D) and example processed  data-cube will be publicly released before the JWST Cycle 4 deadline. MSA3D  package on GitHub: https://github.com/barisiciv/msa3d.git
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2408.08350v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2408.08350v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Ivana Barišić</author><pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2024 18:00:01 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08350v2</guid></item><item><title>On the kinematic nature of apparent discs at high redshifts: Local  counterparts are not dominated by ordered rotation but by tangentially  anisotropic random motion</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10735v2</link><description>Bitao Wang, Yingjie Peng, Michele Cappellari, Hua Gao, Houjun Mo
    &lt;p&gt;
    It is not straightforward to physically interpret the apparent morphology ofgalaxies. Recent observations by James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) revealed adominant galaxy population at high redshifts ($z&gt;2$) that were visuallyclassified as discs for their flattened shapes and/or exponential lightprofiles. The extensively accepted interpretation is that they are dynamicallycold discs supported by bulk rotation. However, it is long known that flattenedshapes and exponential profiles are not exclusive for rotating disc structure.To break degeneracy and assess the rotational support of typical high-$z$galaxies in the JWST samples, those with active star formation and stellarmasses $\mathrm{lg}(\mathcal{M}_{\star}/\mathcal{M}_{\odot})\sim9$, we studythe kinematics of their equal-mass counterparts at $z=0$. While these localstar-forming low-mass galaxies are photometrically similar to real dynamicallycold discs, they are not supported by ordered rotation but primarily by randommotion, and their flattened shapes result largely from tangential orbitalanisotropy. Given the empirical and theoretical evidence that young galaxiesare dynamically hotter at higher redshifts, our results suggest that thehigh-$z$ JWST galaxies may not be cold discs but are dynamically warm/hotgalaxies with flattened shapes driven by anisotropy. While both having lowrotational support, local low-mass galaxies possess oblate shapes, contrastingthe prolate shapes (i.e. cigar-like) of low-mass systems at high redshifts.Such shape transition (prolate$\Rightarrow$oblate) indicates an associatedchange in orbital anisotropy (radial$\Rightarrow$tangential), with roots likelyin the assembly of their host dark matter halos.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 11 pages, 4 figures. ApJL accepted
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2408.10735v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2408.10735v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Bitao Wang</author><pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2024 11:06:39 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10735v2</guid></item><item><title>ASTRODEEP-JWST: NIRCam-HST multiband photometry and redshifts for half a  million sources in six extragalactic deep fields</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.00169v2</link><description>E. Merlin, P. Santini, D. Paris, M. Castellano, A. Fontana, T. Treu, S. L. Finkelstein, J. S. Dunlop, P. Arrabal Haro, M. Bagley, K. Boyett, A. Calabrò, M. Correnti, K. Davis, M. Dickinson, C. T. Donnan, H. C. Ferguson, F. Fortuni, M. Giavalisco, K. Glazebrook, A. Grazian, N. A. Grogin, N. Hathi, M. Hirschmann, J. S. Kartaltepe, L. J. Kewley, A. Kirkpatrick, D. D. Kocevski, A. M. Koekemoer, G. Leung, J. M. Lotz, R. A. Lucas, D. K. Magee, D. Marchesini, S. Mascia, D. J. McLeod, R. J. McLure, T. Nanayakkara, L. Napolitano, M. Nonino, C. Papovich, L. Pentericci, P. G. Pérez-González, N. Pirzkal, S. Ravindranath, G. Roberts-Borsani, R. S. Somerville, M. Trenti, J. R. Trump, B. Vulcani, X. Wang, P. J. Watson, S. M. Wilkins, G. Yang, L. Y. A. Yung
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present a set of photometric catalogs primarily aimed at providing thecommunity with a comprehensive database for the study of galaxy populations inthe high redshift Universe. The set gathers data from eight JWST NIRCamobservational programs, targeting the Abell 2744 (GLASS-JWST, UNCOVER, DDT2756and GO3990), EGS (CEERS), COSMOS and UDS (PRIMER), and GOODS North and South(JADES and NGDEEP) deep fields, for a total area of $\sim$0.2 sq. degrees.Photometric estimates are obtained by means of well-established techniques,including tailored improvements designed to enhance the performance on thespecific dataset. We also include new measurements from HST archival data, thuscollecting 16 bands spanning from 0.44 to 4.44 $\mu$m. A grand total of$\sim$530 thousand sources is detected on stacks of NIRCam 3.56 and 4.44 $\mu$mmosaics. We assess the photometric accuracy by comparing fluxes and colorsagainst archival catalogs. We also provide photometric redshift estimates,statistically validated against a large set of robust spectroscopic data. Thecatalogs are publicly available on the Astrodeep website.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 28 pages, 16 figures; accepted for publication on Astronomy &amp;  Astrophysics
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.00169v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.00169v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>E. Merlin</author><pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.00169v2</guid></item><item><title>JWST Reveals Bulge-dominated Star-forming Galaxies at Cosmic Noon</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08328v2</link><description>Chloë E. Benton, Erica J. Nelson, Tim B. Miller, Rachel Bezanson, Justus Gibson, Abigail I Hartley, Marco Martorano, Sedona H. Price, Katherine A. Suess, Arjen van der Wel, Pieter van Dokkum, John R. Weaver, Katherine E. Whitaker
    &lt;p&gt;
    Hubble Space Telescope imaging shows that most star-forming galaxies atcosmic noon -- the peak of cosmic star formation history -- appeardisk-dominated, leaving the origin of the dense cores in their quiescentdescendants unclear. With the James Webb Space Telescope's (JWST)high-resolution imaging to 5 {\mu}m, we can now map the rest-framenear-infrared emission, a much closer proxy for stellar mass distribution, inthese massive galaxies. We selected 70 star-forming galaxies with10$&lt;$log(M)$&lt;$12 and 1.5$&lt;$z$&lt;$3 in the CEERS survey and compare theirmorphologies in the rest-frame optical to those in the rest-frame near-IR.While the bulk of these galaxies are disk-dominated in 1.5 {\mu}m (rest-frameoptical) imaging, they appear more bulge-dominated at 4.4 {\mu}m (rest-framenear-infrared). Our analysis reveals that in massive star-forming galaxies atz$\sim$2, the radial surface brightness profiles steepen significantly, from aslope of $\sim$0.3/dex at 1.5 {\mu}m to $\sim$1.4/dex at 4.4 {\mu}m withinradii $&lt;$ 1 kpc. Additionally, we find their total flux contained within thecentral 1 kpc is approximately 7 times higher in F444W than in F150W. Inrest-optical emission, a galaxy's central surface density appears to be thestrongest indicator of whether it is quenched or star-forming. Our mostsignificant finding is that at redder wavelengths, the central surface densityratio between quiescent and star-forming galaxies dramatically decreases from$\sim$10 to $\sim$1. This suggests the high central densities associated withgalaxy quenching are already in place during the star-forming phase, imposingnew constraints on the transition from star formation to quiescence.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 9 pages, 5 figures, published in ApJL
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.08328v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.08328v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Chloë E. Benton</author><pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2024 18:00:05 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08328v2</guid></item><item><title>Suppressed accretion onto massive black hole binaries surrounded by thin  disks</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03830v1</link><description>Christopher Tiede, Jonathan Zrake, Andrew MacFadyen, Zoltan Haiman
    &lt;p&gt;
    We demonstrate that gas disks around binary systems might deliver gas to thebinary components only when the circumbinary disk is relatively warm. Wepresent new grid-based hydrodynamics simulations, performed with the binary onthe grid and a locally isothermal equation of state, in which the binary isseen to functionally ``stop accreting'' if the orbital Mach number in the diskexceeds a threshold value of about 40. Above this threshold, the disk continuesto extract angular momentum from the binary orbit, but it delivers very littlemass to the black holes, and instead piles up mass in a ring surrounding thebinary. This ring will eventually become viscously relaxed and deliver mass tothe binary at the large-scale inflow rate. However we show that the timescalefor such relaxation can far exceed the implied binary lifetime. We demonstratethat the ability of a binary-disk system to equilibrate is dependent on theefficiency at which accretion streams deposit mass onto the binary; which inturn is highly sensitive to the thermodynamic conditions of the inner disk. Ifdisks around massive black hole binaries do operate in such non-accretingregimes, it suggests these systems may be dimmer than their single black holecounterparts, but could exhibit dramatic re-brightening after the black holesin-spiral and merge. This dimming occurs at high photon energies, correspondingto the effective truncation of the circumbinary disk. As a result, such systemmay be underluminous in UV bands and missing X-ray emission entirely,potentially resembling the spectra of `Little Red Dots'' recently identified inJWST observations.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 9 pages and 4 figures
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.03830v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.03830v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Christopher Tiede</author><pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 18:00:52 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03830v1</guid></item><item><title>Star formation in cosmic-dawn galaxies</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04227v2</link><description>Sandro Tacchella
    &lt;p&gt;
    In the first two years of operation JWST has delivered key new insights intothe formation and evolution of galaxies in the early Universe. By combiningimaging with spectroscopy, we discovered and characterised the first generationof galaxies, probing the Universe at an age of 300 million years. While thecurrent JWST observations confirm the overall cosmological framework and theparadigm of galaxy formation, there are also surprises, including largeabundances of bright galaxies and accreting black holes in the early Universe.These observations, together with detailed measurements of the stellarpopulations and morphological structure, will help us to develop in the comingyears a more refined understanding of the baryonic physics (including starformation and feedback processes) that leads to the formation of mature systemsat later epochs, including our own Milky Way galaxy.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: To be published in "Astrophysics: The James Webb Space Telescope:  from first light to new world views", proceedings of the Pontifical Academy  of Sciences workshop February 27-29 2024, Vatican City, E.F. van Dishoeck and  G. Consolmagno (eds)
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.04227v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.04227v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Sandro Tacchella</author><pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2024 16:56:09 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04227v2</guid></item><item><title>Age-dating early quiescent galaxies: high star-formation efficiency, but  consistent with direct, higher-redshift observations</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05377v1</link><description>Crispin Turner, Sandro Tacchella, Francesco D'Eugenio, Stefano Carniani, Mirko Curti, Karl Glazebrook, Benjamin D. Johnson, Seunghwan Lim, Tobias Looser, Roberto Maiolino, Themiya Nanayakkara, Jenny T. Wan
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present a detailed analysis of JWST/NIRSpec and NIRCam observations ofZF-UDS-7329, a massive, quiescent galaxy at redshift $z=3.2$, which has beenput forward to challenge cosmology and galaxy formation physics. Our studyextends previous works by focusing on the impact of different star formationhistory (SFH) priors, stellar libraries, metallicity, and initial mass functionassumptions. Our results show that ZF-UDS-7329, with a formed stellar mass of$M_{\star} \approx 10^{11.4}~M_{\odot}$ and a specific star formation rate of$\mathrm{sSFR} \approx 0.03$ Gyr$^{-1}$, formed efficiently in the firstbillion years of the Universe. In agreement with previous work, we find thatthe spectrum is consistent with mass-weighted stellar ages of $1.3-1.8$ Gyr,depending on the SFH prior used. A physically motivated rising SFH prior makesthe formation history of ZF-UDS-7329 compatible with stellar mass andstar-formation rate estimates of high-redshift ($z&gt;6$) galaxies. Using NIRCamimaging, we identify a colour gradient indicative of an old, quiescent bulgeand a younger disc component, as expected from a complex formation history. Theinferred SFH is consistent a high stellar fraction of $f_{\star}=M_{\star}/(f_b\cdot M_{\rm h}) \approx 100\%$ at $z=7-12$, implying an extremely highintegrated star-formation efficiency. However, when considering cosmic varianceand possible mergers as expected in over-dense environments - as traced byZF-UDS-7329 - the stellar fractions could be reduced to $f_{\star} \approx50\%$, which is more consistent with galaxy formation models and thestellar-to-halo mass relation at lower redshifts. We conclude that ZF-UDS-7329forms extremely efficient in the early universe, but does not necessitateunseen galaxies at higher redshifts since the inferred SFR of ancestors areconsistent with those seen in $z&gt;6$ galaxies.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 15 pages and 8 figures (+appendix), submitted to MNRAS
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.05377v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.05377v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Crispin Turner</author><pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 18:00:01 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05377v1</guid></item><item><title>Polycyclic Aromatic Hydrocarbon and CO(2-1) Emission at 50-150 pc Scales  in 66 Nearby Galaxies</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05397v1</link><description>Ryan Chown, Adam K. Leroy, Karin Sandstrom, Jeremy Chastenet, Jessica Sutter, Eric W. Koch, Hannah B. Koziol, Lukas Neumann, Jiayi Sun, Thomas G. Williams, Dalya Baron, Gagandeep S. Anand, Ashley T. Barnes, Zein Bazzi, Francesco Belfiore, Alberto Bolatto, Mederic Boquien, Yixian Cao, Melanie Chevance, Dario Colombo, Daniel A. Dale, Oleg V. Egorov, Cosima Eibensteiner, Eric Emsellem, Hamid Hassani, Jonathan D. Henshaw, Hao He, Jaeyeon Kim, Kathryn Kreckel, Sharon E. Meidt, Eric J. Murphy, Elias K. Oakes, Eve C. Ostriker, Hsi-An Pan, Debosmita Pathak, Erik Rosolowsky, Sumit K. Sarbadhicary, Eva Schinnerer, Yu-Hsuan Teng
    &lt;p&gt;
    Combining Atacama Large Millimeter/sub-millimeter Array CO(2-1) mapping andJWST near- and mid-infrared imaging, we characterize the relationship betweenCO(2-1) and polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon (PAH) emission at ~100 pcresolution in 66 nearby star-forming galaxies, expanding the sample size fromprevious ~100 pc resolution studies by more than an order of magnitude.Focusing on regions of galaxies where most of the gas is likely to bemolecular, we find strong correlations between CO(2-1) and 3.3 micron, 7.7micron, and 11.3 micron PAH emission, estimated from JWST's F335M, F770W, andF1130W filters. We derive power law relations between CO(2-1) and PAH emission,which have indices in the range 0.8-1.2, implying relatively weak variations inthe observed CO-to-PAH ratios across the regions that we study. We find thatCO-to-PAH ratios and scaling relationships near HII regions are similar tothose in diffuse sight lines. The main difference between the two types ofregions is that sight lines near HII regions show higher intensities in alltracers. Galaxy centers, on the other hand, show higher overall intensities andenhanced CO-to-PAH ratios compared to galaxy disks. Individual galaxies show0.19 dex scatter in the normalization of CO at fixed I_PAH and thisnormalization anti-correlates with specific star formation rate (SFR/M*) andcorrelates with stellar mass. We provide a prescription that accounts for thesegalaxy-to-galaxy variations and represents our best current empirical predictorto estimate CO(2-1) intensity from PAH emission, which allows one to takeadvantage of JWST's excellent sensitivity and resolution to trace cold gas.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 21 pages, 4 figures, 3 tables. Submitted to ApJ
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.05397v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.05397v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Ryan Chown</author><pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 18:02:21 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05397v1</guid></item><item><title>Supermassive primordial black holes for the GHZ9 and UHZ1 observed by  the JWST</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05891v1</link><description>Hai-Long Huang, Yu-Tong Wang, Yun-Song Piao
    &lt;p&gt;
    The high redshift ($z&gt;10$) galaxies GHZ9 and UHZ1 observed by the James WebbSpace Telescope (JWST) are very massive and have exceptionally high blackhole-to-star mass ratios with the central black hole masses $M\gtrsim10^7\rm~M_\odot$. In this paper, we explore the possibility that they areseeded by the supermassive primordial black holes (SMPBHs), which came intobeing in the very early universe, with initial masses $\sim 10^7\rm~M_\odot$.We present the self-similar accretion solutions for SMPBHs, and find that themass growth of SMPBHs during pregalactic era may be negligible. These SMPBHs,when the redshift $z\lesssim 20$, can accelerate seeding high-redshift galaxiesand their baryonic content, and consequently explain the central supermassiveblack holes (SMBHs) of high-redshift massive galaxies through sub-Eddingtonaccretion. According to our results, SMPBHs actually could lead to theexistence of more massive SMBHs at higher redshifts compared to other SMBH seedscenarios, specially SMBHs with masses $M\gtrsim 10^7~\rm M_\odot$ at $z&gt;20$might only origin from SMPBHs, thus the corresponding observation can serve asa potential probe to PBHs.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 14 pages, 5 figures
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.05891v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.05891v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Hai-Long Huang</author><pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 10:34:13 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05891v1</guid></item><item><title>Magnetic Fields Under Feedback: A Case Study of the Massive Star-Forming  Hub G34.26+0.15</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06178v1</link><description>Zacariyya A. Khan, Kate Pattle, Sarah F. Graves
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present 850$\mu$m polarized observations of the molecular cloudG34.26+0.15 taken using the POL-2 polarimeter mounted on the James ClerkMaxwell Telescope (JCMT). G34.26+0.15 is a hub-filament system with ongoinghigh-mass star-formation, containing multiple HII regions. We extend theHistogram of Relative Orientations technique with an alternative applicationthat considers the alignment of the magnetic field to the filaments and a HIIregion boundary, denoted as the filament alignment factor ($\xi_{F}$) and theellipse alignment factor ($\xi_{E}$) respectively. Using these metrics, we findthat, although in general the magnetic field aligns parallel to the filamentarystructure within the system in the north-west, the magnetic field structure ofG34.26+0.15 has been radically reshaped by the expansion of an evolved HIIregion in the south-east, which itself may have triggered further high-massstar formation in the cloud. Thus, we suggest high-mass star formation is bothoccurring through mass accretion as per the hub-filament model from one side,and through compression of gas under stellar feedback from the other. We alsouse HARP observations of C$^{18}$O from the CHIMPS survey to estimate themagnetic field strength across the cloud, finding strengths of $\sim$0.5-1.4mG.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 16 pages, 15 figures, 1 table, accepted for publication in MNRAS
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.06178v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.06178v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Zacariyya A. Khan</author><pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 16:29:51 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06178v1</guid></item><item><title>Force-feeding Supermassive Black Holes with Dissipative Dark Matter</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06252v1</link><description>Matthew R. Buckley, Nicolas Fernandez
    &lt;p&gt;
    Supermassive black holes with masses $\gtrsim 10^9\,M_\odot$ have beendiscovered by JWST at high redshifts ($z\sim 7$). It is difficult to explainsuch objects as the result of accretive growth of stellar-mass seeds, as therate at which baryons can be fed to the black hole is limited by the radiationpressure of the infalling matter. In this paper, we propose a new mechanism tocreate the early progenitors: the collapse of small dark matter halos through adissipative cooling mechanism in the dark sector. These small black holes canthen be efficiently fed with additional dissipative dark matter due to thecomparatively weak interactions between the dark radiation and dark matter,which results in a very short Eddington time and high accretion rates.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 11 pages, 3 figures
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.06252v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.06252v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Matthew R. Buckley</author><pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 18:00:01 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06252v1</guid></item><item><title>UNCOVER: 404 Error -- Models Not Found for the Triply Imaged Little Red  Dot A2744-QSO1</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06257v1</link><description>Yilun Ma, Jenny E. Greene, David J. Setton, Marta Volonteri, Joel Leja, Bingjie Wang, Rachel Bezanson, Gabriel Brammer, Sam E. Cutler, Pratika Dayal, Pieter van Dokkum, Lukas J. Furtak, Karl Glazebrook, Andy D. Goulding, Anna de Graaff, Vasily Kokorev, Ivo Labbe, Richard Pan, Sedona H. Price, John R. Weaver, Christina C. Williams, Katherine E. Whitaker, Adi Zitrin
    &lt;p&gt;
    JWST has revealed an abundance of compact, red objects at $z\approx5-8$dubbed "little red dots" (LRDs), whose SEDs display a faint blue UV continuumfollowed by a steep rise in the optical. Despite extensive study of theircharacteristic V-shaped SEDs, the nature of LRDs remains unknown. We present anew analysis of the NIRSpec/PRISM spectrum of A2744-QSO1, a triply imaged LRDat $z=7.04$ from the UNCOVER survey. The spectrum shows a strong Balmer breakand broad Balmer emission lines, both of which are difficult to explain withmodels invoking exclusively AGN or stellar contributions. Our fiducial modeldecomposes the spectrum into a post-starburst galaxy dominating the UV-opticalcontinuum and a reddened AGN being sub-dominant at all wavelength andcontributing at $\sim20\%$ level. However, our most credible model infers astellar mass of $M_\star\approx 4\times10^9\,\mathrm{M_\odot}$ within a radiusof $r_\mathrm{e}&lt;30\,$pc, driving its central density to the highest amongobservations to date. This high central density could be explained ifA2744-QSO-1 is the early-forming core of a modern-day massive elliptical galaxythat later puffed up via the inside-out growth channel. The models alsonecessitate an unusually steep dust law to preserve the strong break strength,though this steepness may be explained by a deficit of large dust grains. It isalso probable that these challenges reflect our ignorance of A2744-QSO1's truenature. Future variability and reverberation mapping studies could helpdisentangle the galaxy and AGN contribution to the continuum, and deeper redderobservations could also unveil the dust properties in LRDs.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 19 pages, 7 figures, 2 tables. Submitted to ApJ. Comments are welcome
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.06257v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.06257v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Yilun Ma</author><pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 18:00:05 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06257v1</guid></item><item><title>JWST-IPA: Chemical Inventory and Spatial Mapping of Ices in the  Protostar HOPS370 -- Evidence for an Opacity Hole and Thermal Processing of  Ices</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06697v1</link><description>Himanshu Tyagi, Manoj P., Mayank Narang, S T. Megeath, Will Robson M. Rocha, Nashanty Brunken, Adam E. Rubinstein, Robert A. Gutermuth, Neal J. Evans, Ewine van Dishoeck, Sam Federman, Dan M. Watson, David A. Neufeld, Guillem Anglada, Henrik Beuther, Alessio Caratti o Garatti, Leslie W. Looney, Pooneh Nazari, Mayra Osorio, Thomas Stanke, Yao-Lun Yang, Tyler L. Bourke, William J. Fischer, Elise Furlan, Joel D. Green, Nolan Habel, Pamela Klaassen, Nicole Karnath, Hendrik Linz, James Muzzerolle, John J. Tobin, Prabhani Atnagulov, Rohan Rahatgaonkar, Patrick D. Sheehan, Katerina Slavicinska, Amelia M. Stutz, Łukasz Tychoniec, Scott J. Wolk
    &lt;p&gt;
    The composition of protoplanetary disks, and hence the initial conditions ofplanet formation, may be strongly influenced by the infall and thermalprocessing of material during the protostellar phase. Composition of dust andice in protostellar envelopes, shaped by energetic processes driven by theprotostar, serves as the fundamental building material for planets and complexorganic molecules. As part of the JWST GO program, "Investigating ProtostellarAccretion" (IPA), we observed an intermediate-mass protostar HOPS 370(OMC2-FIR3) using NIRSpec/IFU and MIRI/MRS. This study presents the gas and icephase chemical inventory revealed with the JWST in the spectral range of$\sim$2.9 to 28 $\mu$m and explores the spatial variation of volatile icespecies in the protostellar envelope. We find evidence for thermal processingof ice species throughout the inner envelope. We present the first high-spatialresolution ($\sim 80$ au) maps of key volatile ice species H$_{2}$O, CO$_{2}$,$^{13}$CO$_2$, CO, and OCN$^-$, which reveal a highly structured andinhomogeneous density distribution of the protostellar envelope, with adeficiency of ice column density that coincides with the jet/outflow shockedknots. Further, we observe high relative crystallinity of H$_{2}$O ice aroundthe shocked knot seen in the H$_2$ and OH wind/outflow, which can be explainedby a lack of outer colder material in the envelope along the line of sight dueto the irregular structure of the envelope. These observations show clearevidence of thermal processing of the ices in the inner envelope, close to theoutflow cavity walls, heated by the luminous protostar.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Submitted to ApJ. Main text:16 pages with 11 figures
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.06697v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.06697v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Himanshu Tyagi</author><pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 09:05:14 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06697v1</guid></item><item><title>Blowing star formation away in AGN Hosts (BAH) -- II. Investigating the  origin of the H2 emission excess in nearby galaxies with JWST MIRI</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06960v1</link><description>Rogemar A. Riffel, Gabriel L. Souza-Oliveira, José Henrique Costa-Souza, Nadia L. Zakamska, Thaisa Storchi-Bergmann, Rogério Riffel
    &lt;p&gt;
    We use James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) Mid-Infrared Instrument (MIRI)medium-resolution spectrometer (MRS) observations of UGC 8782, CGCG 012-070 andNGC 3884 to investigate the origin of the H$_2$ emission. These three nearbyAGN hosts are known to present H$_2$ emission excess relative to star-forminggalaxies, as traced by the H$_2$ S(3)/PAH$_{\rm 11.3\mu m}$ line ratio. Forevery spaxel, we also measure the velocity width ($W_{\rm 80}$) of H$_2$ S(3).We find that the distribution of H$_2$ in the space of these parameters -H$_2$/PAH and its velocity width - is bimodal: one cluster of points showsapproximately constant values of $W_{\rm 80}$, while the other cluster exhibitsa strong correlation between $W_{\rm 80}$ and H$_2$/PAH. We estimated thetemperature of the H$_2$ gas assuming a power-law distribution and find flatterdistributions in regions where a correlation between $W_{\rm 80}$ and H$_2$S(3)/PAH$_{\rm 11.3\mu m}$ is observed. Additionally, we observed a correlationbetween the [Fe II]$_{\rm 5.34 \mu m}$ (a known shock tracer) and the H$_2$emission. This indicates that the excess H$_2$ emission excess is associated toshock heating of the gas, generated by outflows or by the interaction of theradio jet with the ambient gas.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 12 pages, 5 figures, submitted to ApJ. Comments are welcome
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.06960v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.06960v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Rogemar A. Riffel</author><pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 14:57:19 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06960v1</guid></item><item><title>Here There Be (Dusty) Monsters: High Redshift AGN are Dustier Than Their  Hosts</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07340v1</link><description>Madisyn Brooks, Raymond C. Simons, Jonathan R. Trump, Anthony J. Taylor, Bren Backhaus, Kelcey Davis, Véronique Buat, Nikko J. Cleri, Steven L. Finkelstein, Michaela Hirschmann, Benne W. Holwerda, Dale D. Kocevski, Anton M. Koekemoer, Ray A. Lucas, Fabio Pacucci, Lise-Marie Seillé
    &lt;p&gt;
    JWST spectroscopy has discovered a population of $z \gtrsim 3.5$ galaxieswith broad Balmer emission lines, and narrow forbidden lines, that areconsistent with hosting active galactic nuclei (AGN). Many of these systems,now known as ``little red dots" (LRDs), are compact and have unique colors thatare very red in the optical/near-infrared and blue in the ultraviolet. Therelative contribution of galaxy starlight and AGN to these systems remainsuncertain, especially for the galaxies with unusual blue+red spectral energydistributions. In this work, we use Balmer decrements to measure theindependent dust attenuation of the broad and narrow emission-line componentsof a sample of 29 broad-line AGN identified from three public JWST spectroscopysurveys: CEERS, JADES, and RUBIES. Stacking the narrow components from thespectra of 25 sources with broad H$\rm{\alpha}$ and no broad H$\rm{\beta}$results in a median narrow H$\rm{\alpha}$/H$\rm{\beta}$ =$2.47^{+0.05}_{-0.05}$ (consistent with $A_{v} = 0$) and broadH$\rm{\alpha}$/H$\rm{\beta}$ $&gt; 8.85$ ($A_{v} &gt; 3.63$). The narrow and broadBalmer decrements imply little-to-no attenuation of the narrow emission lines,which are consistent with being powered by star formation and located on largerphysical scales. Meanwhile, the lower limit in broadH$\rm{\alpha}$/H$\rm{\beta}$ decrement, with broad H$\rm{\beta}$ undetected inthe stacked spectrum of 25 broad-H$\rm{\alpha}$ AGN, implies significant dustattenuation of the broad-line emitting region that is presumably associatedwith the central AGN. Our results indicate that these systems, on average, areconsistent with heavily dust-attenuated AGN powering the red parts of their SEDwhile their blue UV emission is powered by unattenuated star formation in thehost galaxy.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 4 figures, 3 tables
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.07340v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.07340v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Madisyn Brooks</author><pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 18:00:19 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07340v1</guid></item><item><title>Constraining Reionization with Lyα Damping-Wing Absorption in  Galaxy Spectra: A Machine Learning Model Based on Reionization Simulations</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07377v1</link><description>Hyunbae Park, Intae Jung, Hidenobu Yajima, Jenny Sorce, Paul R. Shapiro, Kyungjin Ahn, Pierre Ocvirk, Romain Teyssier, Gustavo Yepes, Ilian T. Iliev, Joseph S. W. Lewis
    &lt;p&gt;
    Recently, NIRSpec PRISM/CLEAR observations by JWST have begun providingrest-frame UV continuum measurements of galaxies at $z\gtrsim7$, revealingsignatures of Ly$\alpha$ damping-wing (DW) absorption by the intergalacticmedium (IGM). We develop a methodology to constrain the global ionizationfraction of the IGM $(Q_{\rm HII})$ using low-resolution spectra, employing therandom forest classification (RFC) method. We construct mock spectra using thesimulated galaxies and the IGM from the Cosmic Dawn II simulation and train RFCmodels to estimate $Q_{\rm HII}$ at the redshift of the source and to detectthe presence of a damped Ly$\alpha$ absorber (DLA). We find that individualgalaxy spectra with spectral bins between 1220 and 1270 {\AA} and withsignal-to-noise ratios greater than 20 can place tight constraints on $Q_{\rmHII}$, provided the UV continuum is accurately modeled. This method isparticularly effective for the early phase of reionization ($Q_{\rmHII}&lt;50\%$), when the IGM opacity is high in the DW. As a demonstration, weapply our model to existing NIRSpec PRISM/CLEAR spectra, placing upper boundsof $Q_{\rm HII}=59.6\%$, $5.6\%$, and $18.5\%$ at $z=7.7,~9.4,$ and $10.6$,respectively, with $68\%$ confidence, though several modeling uncertaintiesremain to be discussed. These constraints favor late-starting reionizationmodels, where $\gtrsim 80\%$ of the IGM is ionized after $z=8$. We concludethat high SNR observations of carefully selected targets around $z\sim7-9$ caneffectively constrain reionization models.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 20 pages, 11 figures, submitted to ApJ
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.07377v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.07377v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Hyunbae Park</author><pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 18:47:59 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07377v1</guid></item><item><title>Comparing E-MOSAICS predictions of high-redshift proto-globular clusters  with JWST observations in lensed galaxies</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07498v1</link><description>Joel Pfeffer, Duncan A. Forbes, Aaron J. Romanowsky, Nate Bastian, Robert A. Crain, J. M. Diederik Kruijssen, Kenji Bekki, Jean P. Brodie, Mélanie Chevance, Warrick J. Couch, Jonah S. Gannon
    &lt;p&gt;
    High-resolution imaging and strong gravitational lensing of high-redshiftgalaxies have enabled the detection of compact sources with properties similarto nearby massive star clusters. Often found to be very young, these sourcesmay be globular clusters detected in their earliest stages. In this work, wecompare predictions of high-redshift ($z \sim 1$--$10$) star cluster propertiesfrom the E-MOSAICS simulation of galaxy and star cluster formation with thoseof the star cluster candidates in strongly lensed galaxies from James Webb(JWST) and Hubble Space Telescope (HST) imaging. We select galaxies in thesimulation that match the luminosities of the majority of lensed galaxies withstar cluster candidates observed with JWST. We find that the luminosities, agesand masses of the brightest star cluster candidates in the high-redshiftgalaxies are consistent with the E-MOSAICS model. In particular, the brightestcluster ages are in excellent agreement. The results suggest that star clustersin both low- and high-redshift galaxies may form via common mechanisms.However, the brightest clusters in the lensed galaxies tend to be $\approx1$--$1.5$ mag brighter and $\approx 0.5$ dex more massive than the medianE-MOSAICS predictions. We discuss the large number of effects that couldexplain the discrepancy, including simulation and observational limitations,stellar population models, cluster detection biases and nuclear star clusters.Understanding these limitations would enable stronger tests of globular clusterformation models.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 17 pages, 9 figures, 1 table. Submitted to MNRAS
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.07498v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.07498v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Joel Pfeffer</author><pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:22:24 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07498v1</guid></item><item><title>COSMOS-Web: stellar mass assembly in relation to dark matter halos  across $0.2&lt;z&lt;12$ of cosmic history</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08290v1</link><description>M. Shuntov, O. Ilbert, S. Toft, R. C. Arango-Toro, H. B. Akins, C. M. Casey, M. Franco, S. Harish, J. S. Kartaltepe, A. M. Koekemoer, H. J. McCracken, L. Paquereau, C. Laigle, M. Bethermin, Y. Dubois, N. E. Drakos, A. Faisst, G. Gozaliasl, S. Gillman, C. C. Hayward, M. Hirschmann, M. Huertas-Company, C. K. Jespersen, S. Jin, V. Kokorev, E. Lambrides, D. Le Borgne, D. Liu, G. Magdis, R. Massey, C. J. R. McPartland, W. Mercier, J. E. McCleary, J. McKinney, P. A. Oesch, J. D. Rhodes, R. M. Rich, B. E. Robertson, D. Sanders, M. Trebitsch, L. Tresse, F. Valentino, A. P. Vijayan, J. R. Weaver, A. Weibel, S. M. Wilkins
    &lt;p&gt;
    We study the stellar mass function (SMF) and the co-evolution with darkmatter halos via abundance matching in the largest redshift range to date$0.2&lt;z&lt;12$ in $0.53 \, {\rm deg}^2$ imaged by JWST from the COSMOS-Web survey.At $z&gt;5$, we find increased abundances of massive (log$\,M_{\star}/M_{\odot}&gt;10.5$) implying integrated star formation efficiencies(SFE) $\epsilon_{\star}\equiv M_{\star}\, f_{\rm b}^{-1} M_{\rm halo}^{-1}\gtrsim 0.5$. We find a flattening of the SMF at the high-mass end that isbetter described by a double power law at $z&gt;5.5$. At $z \lesssim 5.5$ ittransitions to a Schechter law which coincides with the emergence of the firstmassive quiescent galaxies in the Universe. We trace the cosmic stellar massdensity (SMD) and infer the star formation rate density (SFRD), which at$z&gt;7.5$ agrees remarkably with recent \JWST{} UV luminosity function-derivedestimates. However, at $z \lesssim 3.5$, we find significant tension ($\sim0.3$ dex) with the cosmic star formation (SF) history from instantaneous SFmeasures, the causes of which remain poorly understood. We infer thestellar-to-halo mass relation (SHMR) and the SFE from abundance matching out to$z=12$, finding a non-monotonic evolution. The SFE has the characteristicstrong dependence with mass in the range of $0.02 - 0.2$, and mildly decreasesat the low mass end out to $z\sim3.5$. At $z\sim3.5$ the SFE increases sharplyfrom $\sim 0.1$ to approach high SFE of $0.8-1$ by $z\sim 10$ for log$(M_{\rmh}/M_{\odot})\approx11.5$, albeit with large uncertainties. Finally, we use theSHMR to track the SFE and stellar mass growth throughout the halo history andfind that they do not grow at the same rate -- from the earliest times up until$z\sim3.5$ the halo growth rate outpaces galaxy assembly, but at $z&gt;3.5$ halogrowth stagnates and accumulated gas reservoirs keep the SF going and galaxiesoutpace halos.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.08290v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.08290v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>M. Shuntov</author><pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 18:21:25 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08290v1</guid></item><item><title>RUBIES: JWST/NIRSpec resolves evolutionary phases of dusty star-forming  galaxies at $z\sim2$</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08387v1</link><description>Olivia R. Cooper, Gabriel Brammer, Kasper E. Heintz, Sune Toft, Caitlin M. Casey, David J. Setton, Anna de Graaff, Leindert Boogaard, Nikko J. Cleri, Steven Gillman, Rashmi Gottumukkala, Jenny E. Greene, Bitten Gullberg, Michaela Hirschmann, Raphael E. Hviding, Erini Lambrides, Joel Leja, Arianna S. Long, Sinclaire M. Manning, Michael V. Maseda, Ian McConachie, Jed McKinney, Desika Narayanan, Sedona H. Price, Victoria Strait, Andrea Weibel, Christina C. Williams
    &lt;p&gt;
    The dearth of high quality spectroscopy of dusty star-forming galaxies(DSFGs) -- the main drivers of the assembly of dust and stellar mass at thepeak of activity in the Universe -- greatly hinders our ability to interprettheir physical processes and evolutionary pathways. We present JWST/NIRSpecobservations from RUBIES of four submillimeter-selected, ALMA-detected DSFGs atcosmic noon, $z\sim2.3-2.7$. While photometry uniformly suggests vigorousongoing star formation for the entire sample in line with canonical DSFGs, thespectra differ: one source has spectroscopic evidence of an evolved stellarpopulation, indicating a recent transition to a post-starburst phase, while theremainder show strong spectroscopic signatures of ongoing starbursts. All fourgalaxies are infrared-luminous (log$_{10}$$L_{\rm{IR}}$/L$_{\rm \odot}$$&gt;12.4$), massive (log$_{10}\,M_\star$/M$_{\rm \odot}$ $&gt;11$), and verydust-obscured ($A_V\sim3-4$ ABmag). Leveraging detections of multiple Balmerand Paschen lines, we derive an optical attenuation curve consistent withCalzetti overall, yet an optical extinction ratio $R_V\sim2.5$, potentiallyindicating smaller dust grains or differences in star-dust geometry. This casestudy provides some of the first detailed spectroscopic evidence that the DSFGsencompass a heterogeneous sample spanning a range of star formation propertiesand evolutionary stages, and illustrates the advantages of synergistic JWST andALMA analysis of DSFGs.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 20 pages, 4 figures; submitted to ApJ
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.08387v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.08387v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Olivia R. Cooper</author><pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 21:46:54 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08387v1</guid></item><item><title>Compact [OIII] emission-line regions ("Green Seeds") in  $\mathrm{Hα}$ emitters at Cosmic Noon from JWST Observations</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08520v1</link><description>Nuo Chen, Kentaro Motohara, Lee Spitler, Matthew A. Malkan
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present a rest-frame optical, spatially resolved analysis of more than 100$\mathrm{H\alpha}$ emitters (HAEs) at $z\sim2.2$ in the ZFOURGE-CDFS fieldusing NIRCam imaging from the JWST Advanced Deep Extragalactic Survey (JADES).The ultra-deep, high-resolution data gives us maps of the resolved emissionline regions of HAEs with stellar mass ranging from $10^{8}\,M_{\odot}$ to$10^{10}\,M_{\odot}$. An [OIII] emission-line map of each HAE is created fromthe flux excess in the F150W filter, leading to the discovery of a populationof kiloparsec-scale compact emission line regions (``Green Seeds") with highequivalent widths ($\mathrm{EW}$). We obtain a sample of 128 Green Seeds from68 HAEs with rest-frame $\mathrm{EW_{[OIII]}}&gt;200\r{A}$. Moreover, 17 of themhave extremely large $\mathrm{EW_{[OIII]}}&gt;1000\r{A}$, suggesting the possibleLyman continuum (LyC) leakage from these emission line regions. Embedded withinthe host galaxy, many Green Seeds correspond to UV star-forming clumps andH{\sc ii} regions, indicating elevated starburst activity in them, withspecific star formation rates (sSFR) several times higher than that of the hostgalaxy. Based on theoretical frameworks, Green Seeds are expected to be formedthrough gravitational disk instability and/or galaxy mergers. Considering thestellar masses of Green Seeds, we speculate that high-mass Green Seeds maymigrate toward the galactic center to build the central bulge, while low-massGreen Seeds are easily disrupted and short-lived. Besides, we propose that someGreen Seeds could be the progenitors of globular clusters or ultracompact dwarfgalaxies observed in the local universe.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 29 pages, 18 figures, Submitted to ApJ
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.08520v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.08520v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Nuo Chen</author><pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 04:43:57 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08520v1</guid></item><item><title>The nature of low-luminosity AGNs discovered by JWST at $5&lt;z&lt;6$ based on  clustering analysis: ancestors of quasars at $z\lesssim3$?</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08707v1</link><description>Junya Arita, Nobunari Kashikawa, Masafusa Onoue, Takehiro Yoshioka, Yoshihiro Takeda, Hiroki Hoshi, Shunta Shimizu
    &lt;p&gt;
    James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) has discovered many faint AGNs at high-$z$by detecting their broad Balmer lines. However, their high number density, lackof X-ray emission, and overly high black hole masses with respect to their hoststellar masses suggest that they are a distinct population from general type-1quasars. Here, we present clustering analysis of 28 low-luminosity broad-lineAGNs found by JWST (JWST AGNs) at $5&lt;z&lt;6$ based on cross-correlation analysiswith 679 photometrically-selected galaxies to characterize their host darkmatter halo (DMH) masses. From angular and projected cross-correlationfunctions, we find that their typical DMH mass is $\log(M_\mathrm{halo}/h^{-1}\mathrm{M}_\odot) = 11.61_{-0.24}^{+0.19},$ and $11.72_{-0.20}^{+0.17}$, respectively. This result implies that the host DMHs ofthese AGNs are $\sim1$ dex smaller than that of luminous quasars. The DMHs ofJWST AGNs at $5&lt;z&lt;6$ are predicted to grow to$10^{12\unicode{x2013}13}\,h^{-1}\mathrm{M}_\odot$, a typical mass of quasar at$z\lesssim3$. Applying the empirical stellar-to-halo mass ratio to the measuredDMH mass, their host stellar mass is evaluated as$\log(M_*/\mathrm{M}_\odot)=9.72_{-0.39}^{+0.31},$ and $ 9.90_{-0.33}^{+0.27}$,which are higher than some of those estimated by the SED fitting. We alsoevaluate their duty cycle as $f_\mathrm{duty}=0.36_{-0.14}^{+0.18}$ per cent,namely $\sim7\times10^6$ yr as the lifetime of JWST AGNs. While we cannotexclude the possibility that JWST AGNs are simply low-mass type-1 quasars,these results suggest that JWST AGNs are a different population from type-1quasars, and may be the ancestors of quasars at $z\lesssim3$.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 12 pages, 7 figures, submitted to MNRAS
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.08707v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.08707v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Junya Arita</author><pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 10:51:23 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08707v1</guid></item><item><title>JWST/NIRSpec spectroscopy of intermediate-mass quiescent galaxies at $z  \sim 3-4$</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08745v1</link><description>Riku A. Sato, Akio K. Inoue, Yuichi Harikane, Rhythm Shimakawa, Yuma Sugahara, Yoichi Tamura, Takuya Hashimoto, Kei Ito, Satoshi Yamanaka, Ken Mawatari, Yoshinobu Fudamoto, Yi W. Ren
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present the analysis of three intermediate-mass quiescent galaxies (QGs)with stellar masses of $\sim10^{10}M_{\rm \odot}$ at redshifts $z\sim 3 - 4$using NIRSpec low-resolution spectroscopy. Utilising the SED fitting codeBAGPIPES, we confirm these target galaxies are consistent with quiescentpopulation, with their specific star formation rates (sSFR) falling below 2-dexthe star-forming main sequence at the same redshifts. Additionally, we identifythese QGs to be less massive than those discovered in previous works,particularly prior to the JWST era. Two of our target galaxies exhibit thepotentially-blended H${\alpha}$+[NII] emission line within their spectra with$S/N&gt;5$. We discuss whether this feature comes from an Active Galactic Nucleus(AGN) or star formation although future high-resolution spectroscopy isrequired to reach a conclusion. One of the target galaxies is covered byJWST/NIRCam imaging of the PRIMER survey. Using the 2D profile fitting codeGalfit, we examine its morphology, revealing a disc-like profile with aS\'{e}rsic index of $n=1.1 \pm 0.1$. On the size-mass relation, we find apotential distinction between less-massive ($\log_{10}{(M_*/M_\odot)}&lt;10.3$)and massive ($\log_{10}{(M_*/M_\odot)}&gt;10.3$) QGs in their evolutionarypathways. The derived quenching timescales for our targets are less than 1 Gyr.This may result from these galaxies being quenched by AGN feedback, supportingthe AGN scenario of the emission line features.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: MNRAS accepted
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.08745v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.08745v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Riku A. Sato</author><pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 12:02:56 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08745v1</guid></item><item><title>The JWST Emission Line Survey (JELS): Extending rest-optical narrow-band  emission line selection into the Epoch of Reionization</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09000v1</link><description>K. J. Duncan, D. J. McLeod, P. N. Best, C. A. Pirie, M. Clausen, R. K. Cochrane, J. S. Dunlop, S. R. Flury, J. E. Geach, C. L. Hale, E. Ibar, R. Kondapally, Zefeng Li, J. Matthee, R. J. McLure, Luis Ossa-Fuentes, A. L. Patrick, Ian Smail, D. Sobral, H. M. O. Stephenson, J. P. Stott, A. M. Swinbank
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present the JWST Emission Line Survey (JELS), a Cycle 1 JWST imagingprogramme exploiting the wavelength coverage and sensitivity of NIRCam toextend narrow-band rest-optical emission line selection into the epoch ofreionization (EoR) for the first time, and to enable unique studies of theresolved ionised gas morphology in individual galaxies across cosmic history.The primary JELS observations comprise $\sim4.7\mu$m narrow-band imaging over$\sim63$ arcmin$^{2}$ designed to enable selection of H$\alpha$ emitters at$z\sim6.1$, as well as the selection of a host of novel emission-line samplesincluding [OIII] at $z\sim8.3$ and Pa $\alpha/\beta$ at $z\sim1.5/2.8$. For theprime F466N and F470N narrow-band observations, the emission-line sensitivitiesachieved are up to $\sim2\times$ more sensitive than current slitlessspectroscopy surveys (5$\sigma$ limits of 1.1-1.6$\times10^{-18}\text{ergs}^{-1}\text{cm}^{-2}$), corresponding to unobscured H$\alpha$ star-formationrates (SFRs) of 1-1.6 $\text{M}_{\odot}\,\text{yr}^{-1}$ at $z\sim6.1$ andextending emission-line selections in the EoR to fainter populations.Simultaneously, JELS also obtained F200W broadband and F212N narrow-bandimaging (H$\alpha$ at $z\sim2.23$) that probes SFRs $\gtrsim5\times$ fainterthan previous ground-based narrow-band studies ($\sim0.2\text{M}_{\odot}\text{yr}^{-1}$), offering an unprecedented resolved view ofstar formation at cosmic noon. In this paper we describe the detailed JELSsurvey design, key data processing steps specific to the survey observations,and demonstrate the exceptional data quality and imaging sensitivity achieved.We then summarise the key scientific goals of JELS and present some earlyscience results, including examples of spectroscopically confirmed H$\alpha$and [OIII] emitters discovered by JELS that illustrate the novel parameterspace probed.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Submitted to MRNAS; 13 pages, 8 figures. Accompanying data will be  publicly released upon acceptance of this and companion paper (Pirie et al.,  subm.)
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09000v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09000v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>K. J. Duncan</author><pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 17:13:39 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09000v1</guid></item><item><title>A JWST/MIRI View of the ISM in M83: I. Resolved Molecular Hydrogen  Properties, Star Formation, and Feedback</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09020v1</link><description>Logan H. Jones, Svea Hernandez, Linda J. Smith, Aditya Togi, Tanio Diaz-Santos, Alessandra Aloisi, William Blair, Alec S. Hirschauer, Leslie K. Hunt, Bethan L. James, Nimisha Kumari, Vianney Lebouteiller, Matilde Mingozzi, Lise Ramambason
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present a spatially-resolved (~3 pc pix$^{-1}$) analysis of thedistribution, kinematics, and excitation of warm H2 gas in the nuclearstarburst region of M83. Our JWST/MIRI IFU spectroscopy reveals a clumpyreservoir of warm H2 (&gt; 200 K) with a mass of ~2.3 x 10$^{5}$ Msun in the areacovered by all four MRS channels. We additionally use the [Ne II] 12.8 ${\mu}$mand [Ne III] 15.5 ${\mu}$m lines as tracers of the star formation rate,ionizing radiation hardness, and kinematics of the ionized ISM, findingtantalizing connections to the H2 properties and to the ages of the underlyingstellar populations. Finally, qualitative comparisons to the trove of public,high-spatial-resolution multiwavelength data available on M83 shows that ourMRS spectroscopy potentially traces all stages of the process of creatingmassive star clusters, from the embedded proto-cluster phase through thedispersion of ISM from stellar feedback.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 21 pages, 11+1 figures; submitted to ApJ
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09020v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09020v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Logan H. Jones</author><pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 17:37:09 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09020v1</guid></item><item><title>JWST/MIRI Observations of Newly Formed Dust in the Cold, Dense Shell of  the Type IIn SN 2005ip</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09142v1</link><description>Melissa Shahbandeh, Ori D. Fox, Tea Temim, Eli Dwek, Arkaprabha Sarangi, Nathan Smith, Luc Dessart, Bryony Nickson, Michael Engesser, Alexei V. Filippenko, Thomas G. Brink, Weikang Zheng, Tamás Szalai, Joel Johansson, Armin Rest, Schuyler D. Van Dyk, Jennifer Andrews, Chris Ashall, Geoffrey C. Clayton, Ilse De Looze, James M. Derkacy, Michael Dulude, Ryan J. Foley, Suvi Gezari, Sebastian Gomez, Shireen Gonzaga, Siva Indukuri, Jacob Jencson, Mansi Kasliwal, Zachary G. Lane, Ryan Lau, David Law, Anthony Marston, Dan Milisavljevic, Richard O'Steen, Justin Pierel, Matthew Siebert, Michael Skrutskie, Lou Strolger, Samaporn Tinyanont, Qinan Wang, Brian Williams, Lin Xiao, Yi Yang, Szanna Zsíros
    &lt;p&gt;
    Dust from core-collapse supernovae (CCSNe), specifically Type IIP SNe, hasbeen suggested to be a significant source of the dust observed in high-redshiftgalaxies. CCSNe eject large amounts of newly formed heavy elements, which cancondense into dust grains in the cooling ejecta. However, infrared (IR)observations of typical CCSNe generally measure dust masses that are too smallto account for the dust production needed at high redshifts. Type IIn SNe,classified by their dense circumstellar medium (CSM), are also known to exhibitstrong IR emission from warm dust, but the dust origin and heating mechanismhave generally remained unconstrained because of limited observationalcapabilities in the mid-IR. Here, we present a JWST/MIRI Medium ResolutionSpectrograph (MRS) spectrum of the Type IIn SN 2005ip nearly 17 yearspost-explosion. The Type IIn SN 2005ip is one of the longest-lasting and mostwell-studied SNe observed to date. Combined with a Spitzer mid-IR spectrum ofSN 2005ip obtained in 2008, this data set provides a rare 15-year baseline,allowing for a unique investigation of the evolution of dust. The JWST spectrumshows a new high-mass dust component ($\gtrsim0.08$ M$_{\odot}$) that is notpresent in the earlier Spitzer spectrum. Our analysis shows dust likely formedover the past 15 years in the cold, dense shell (CDS), between the forward andreverse shocks. There is also a smaller mass of carbonaceous dust($\gtrsim0.005$ M$_{\odot}$) in the ejecta. These observations provide newinsights into the role of SN dust production, particularly within the CDS, andits potential contribution to the rapid dust enrichment of the early Universe.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09142v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09142v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Melissa Shahbandeh</author><pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09142v1</guid></item><item><title>Extending the cosmic distance ladder two orders of magnitude with  strongly lensed Cepheids, carbon AGB, and RGB stars</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09162v1</link><description>J. M. Diego, S. P. Willner, J. M. Palencia
    &lt;p&gt;
    Extreme magnification of stars near the caustics of clusters allow to detectindividual luminous stars at high redshift. We show how deep exposures ofcaustic crossing galaxies at $z\lesssim1$ with IR telescopes such as JWST, candetect non-explosive distance calibrators, such as Cepheids, carbon stars inthe asymptotic giant branch or stars in the tip of the red giant branch. Alarge number of such detections, combined with careful modelling of themagnification affecting these stars (including microlensing), opens the door tousing them as alternative standard candles to SNe in a redshift range thatwould extend the cosmic distance ladder two orders of magnitude for thesedistance calibrators. As a bonus, strongly lensed stars detected in deepexposures provide also a robust method of mapping small dark mattersubstructures since they cluster around the critical curves of small scale darkmatter halos.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 6 pages and 6 figures
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09162v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09162v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>J. M. Diego</author><pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 18:09:55 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09162v1</guid></item><item><title>From UV-bright Galaxies to Early Disks: the Importance of Turbulent Star  Formation in the Early Universe</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09205v1</link><description>Vadim A. Semenov, Charlie Conroy, Lars Hernquist
    &lt;p&gt;
    Bursty star formation at early times can explain the surprising abundance ofearly UV-bright galaxies revealed by JWST but can also be a reason for thedelayed formation of galactic disks in high-resolution cosmologicalsimulations. We investigate this interplay in a cosmological simulation of anearly-forming Milky Way analog with detailed modeling of cold turbulentinterstellar medium (ISM), star formation, and feedback. We find that themodeling of locally variable star formation efficiency (SFE) coupled with theISM turbulence on the scales of star-forming regions is important for producingboth early bursty evolution and early formation and survival of galactic disks.Such a model introduces a qualitatively new channel of the global starformation rate (SFR) burstiness caused by chaotic fluctuations in the averageSFE due to changes in the ISM turbulence, which, in our simulation, dominatesthe short-term SFR variability. The average SFE stays low, close to $\sim 1\%$per freefall time, and its variation decreases when the gas disk forms, leadingto only mild effects of stellar feedback on the early disk, enabling itssurvival. By rerunning our simulation with fixed SFE values, we explicitly showthat low SFEs lead to smoother SFR histories and disk survival, while high SFEslead to bursty SFRs and hinder disk formation. The model with variable SFEswitches between these two regimes at the moment of disk formation. Thesetrends are missing in more commonly used star formation prescriptions withfixed SFE; in particular, the prescriptions tying star formation to moleculargas should be interpreted with caution because the two are decoupled at earlytimes, as we also show in this paper.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 16 pages, 10 figures; to be submitted; comments are welcome. For  visualizations, see https://vadimsemenov.com/visualizations/
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09205v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09205v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Vadim A. Semenov</author><pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 19:21:08 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09205v1</guid></item><item><title>The JWST-NIRCam View of Sagittarius C. I. Massive Star Formation and  Protostellar Outflows</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09253v1</link><description>Samuel Crowe, Rubén Fedriani, Jonathan C. Tan, Alva Kinman, Yichen Zhang, Morten Andersen, Lucía Bravo Ferres, Francisco Nogueras-Lara, Rainer Schödel, John Bally, Adam Ginsburg, Yu Cheng, Yao-Lun Yang, Sarah Kendrew, Chi-Yan Law, Joseph Armstrong, Zhi-Yun Li
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present James Webb Space Telescope (JWST)-NIRCam observations of themassive star-forming molecular cloud Sagittarius C (Sgr C) in the CentralMolecular Zone (CMZ). In conjunction with ancillary mid-IR and far-IR data, wecharacterize the two most massive protostars in Sgr C via spectral energydistribution (SED) fitting, estimating that they each have current masses of$m_* \sim 20\:M_\odot$ and surrounding envelope masses of $\sim 100\:M_\odot$.We report a census of lower-mass protostars in Sgr C via a search for infraredcounterparts to mm continuum dust cores found with ALMA. We identify 88molecular hydrogen outflow knot candidates originating from outflows fromprotostars in Sgr C, the first such unambiguous detections in the infrared inthe CMZ. About a quarter of these are associated with flows from the twomassive protostars in Sgr C; these extend for over 1 pc and are associated withoutflows detected in ALMA SiO line data. An additional $\sim 40$ featureslikely trace shocks in outflows powered by lower-mass protostars throughout thecloud. We report the discovery of a new star-forming region hosting twoprominent bow shocks and several other line-emitting features driven by atleast two protostars. We infer that one of these is forming a high-mass stargiven an SED-derived mass of $m_* \sim 9\:M_\odot$ and associated massive($\sim 90\:M_\odot$) mm core and water maser. Finally, we identify a populationof miscellaneous Molecular Hydrogen Objects (MHOs) that do not appear to beassociated with protostellar outflows.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Appendix figures B1 and B2 will be made into online-only figure sets  for the eventual ApJ publication
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09253v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09253v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Samuel Crowe</author><pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 20:59:21 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09253v1</guid></item><item><title>Measuring Star Formation Histories from Asymptotic Giant Branch Stars: A  Demonstration in M31</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09256v1</link><description>Abigail J. Lee, Daniel R. Weisz, Yi Ren, Alessandro Savino, Andrew E. Dolphin
    &lt;p&gt;
    We demonstrate how near infrared (NIR) imaging of resolved luminousasymptotic giant branch (AGB) stars can be used to measure well-constrainedstar formation histories (SFHs) across cosmic time. Using UKIRT J and K-bandimaging of M31, we first show excellent agreement over the past $\sim8$ Gyrbetween the PHAT SFH of M31's outer disk derived from a deep opticalcolor-magnitude diagram (CMD; $\sim3.3\times10^{7}$ stars with $M_{F814W}\lesssim +2$), and our spatially-matched SFH based only on modeling AGB starson a NIR CMD ($\sim2.3\times10^{4}$ stars with $M_{J} \lesssim -5$). We findthat only hundreds of AGB stars are needed for reliable SFH recovery, owing totheir excellent age sensitivity in the NIR. We then measure the spatiallyresolved SFH of M31's inner stellar halo ($D_{M31, projected} \sim20-30$ kpc)using $\sim10^5$ AGB stars. We find: (i) a dominant burst of star formationacross M31's inner stellar halo from $4-5$ Gyr ago and lower level, spatiallydistributed star formation $\sim1-2$ Gyr ago; (ii) a younger 'quenching time'in the vicinity of NGC 205 ($\sim1$ Gyr ago) than near M32 ($\sim1.1$ Gyr ago);(iii) $M_{\star}\sim4\pm0.5\times10^9 M_{\odot}$ formed over the past $\sim8$Gyr. We discuss some caveats and the enormous potential of resolved AGB starsin the NIR for measuring SFHs back to ancient epochs ($\sim13$ Gyr ago) ingalaxies to large distances ($D\gtrsim20$ Mpc) with JWST, Roman, and Euclid.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 25 pages, 19 figures, submitted to AAS Journals
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09256v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09256v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Abigail J. Lee</author><pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 21:11:46 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09256v1</guid></item><item><title>The effects of super-Eddington accretion and feedback on the growth of  early supermassive black holes and galaxies</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09450v1</link><description>Filip Huško, Cedric G. Lacey, William J. Roper, Joop Schaye, Jemima Mae Briggs, Matthieu Schaller
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present results of cosmological zoom-in simulations of a massiveprotocluster down to redshift $z\approx4$ (when the halo mass is$\approx10^{13}$ M$_\odot$) using the SWIFT code and the EAGLE galaxy formationmodel, focusing on supermassive black hole (BH) physics. The BH was seeded witha mass of $10^4$ M$_\odot$ at redshift $z\approx17$. We compare the base modelthat uses an Eddington limit on the BH accretion rate and thermal isotropicfeedback by the AGN, with one where super-Eddington accretion is allowed, aswell as two other models with BH spin and jets. In the base model, the BH growsat the Eddington limit from $z=9$ to $z=5.5$, when it becomes massive enough tohalt its own and its host galaxy's growth through feedback. We find thatallowing super-Eddington accretion leads to drastic differences, with the BHgoing through an intense but short super-Eddington growth burst around$z\approx7.5$, during which it increases its mass by orders of magnitude,before feedback stops further growth (of both the BH and the galaxy). By$z\approx4$ the galaxy is only half as massive in the super-Eddington cases,and an order of magnitude more extended, with the half-mass radius reachingvalues of a few physical kpc instead of a few hundred pc. The BH masses in oursimulations are consistent with the intrinsic BH mass$-$stellar mass relationinferred from high-redshift observations by JWST. This shows that galaxyformation models using the $\Lambda$CDM cosmology are capable of reproducingthe observed massive BHs at high redshift. Allowing jets, either at super- orsub-Eddington rates, has little impact on the host galaxy properties, but leadsto lower BH masses as a result of stronger self-regulation, which is itself aconsequence of higher feedback efficiencies.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Submitted to MNRAS
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09450v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.09450v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Filip Huško</author><pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 09:06:10 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09450v1</guid></item><item><title>JWST/NIRSpec Observations of Brown Dwarfs in the Orion Nebula Cluster</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10000v1</link><description>K. L. Luhman, C Alves de Oliveira, I. Baraffe, G. Chabrier, E. Manjavacas, R. J. Parker, P. Tremblin
    &lt;p&gt;
    We have used the multiobject mode of the Near-Infrared Spectrograph (NIRSpec)on board the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) to obtain low-resolution 1-5umspectra of 22 brown dwarf candidates in the Orion Nebula Cluster, which wereselected with archival images from the Hubble Space Telescope. One of thetargets was previously classified as a Herbig-Haro (HH) object and exhibitsstrong emission in H I, H2, and the fundamental band of CO, furtherdemonstrating that HH objects can have bright emission in that CO band. Theremaining targets have late spectral types (M6.5 to early L) and are youngbased on gravity sensitive features, as expected for low-mass members of thecluster. According to theoretical evolutionary models, these objects shouldhave masses that range from the hydrogen burning limit to 0.003-0.007 Msun. Twoof the NIRSpec targets were identified as proplyds in earlier analysis ofHubble images. They have spectral types of M6.5 and M7.5, making them two ofthe coolest and least massive known proplyds. Another brown dwarf showsabsorption bands at 3-5um from ices containing H2O, CO2, OCN-, and CO,indicating that it is either an edge-on class II system or a class I protostar.It is the coolest and least massive object that has detections of these icefeatures. In addition, it appears to be the first candidate for a protostellarbrown dwarf that has spectroscopy confirming its late spectral type.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Astronomical Journal, in press
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10000v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10000v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>K. L. Luhman</author><pubDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2024 20:45:26 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10000v1</guid></item><item><title>Candidates for Substellar Members of the Orion Nebula Cluster from  JWST/NIRCam</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10406v1</link><description>K. L. Luhman
    &lt;p&gt;
    In 2022, the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) obtained 1-5um images of thecenter of the Orion Nebula Cluster (ONC). I have analyzed these data in anattempt to search for substellar members of the cluster. Using a pair ofcolor-color diagrams, I have identified &gt;200 brown dwarf candidates that lackspectral classifications. Some of the candidates could be protostars (eitherstellar or substellar) given their very red colors. Based on the age of the ONCand the photometry predicted by theoretical evolutionary models, the faintestcandidates could have masses of 1-2 Mjup. This sample of candidates may proveto be valuable for studying various aspects of young brown dwarfs, includingtheir mass function and minimum mass. However, spectroscopy is needed toconfirm the membership (via signatures of youth) and late spectral types of thecandidates. Finally, I note that most of the "Jupiter-mass binary objects" thathave been previously identified with these JWST images are absent from mysample of candidates because their colors are indicative of reddened backgroundsources rather than young brown dwarfs or their photometry is inadequate forassessing their nature because of very low signal-to-noise ratios and/ordetections in only a few bands.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Astronomical Journal, in press
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10406v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10406v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>K. L. Luhman</author><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 11:58:37 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10406v1</guid></item><item><title>Hidden Cooling Flows IV: More Details on Centaurus and the Efficiency of  AGN Feedback in Clusters</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10675v1</link><description>A. C. Fabian, G. J. Ferland, J. S. Sanders, H. R. Russell, B. R. McNamara, C. Pinto, J. Hlavacek-Larrondo, S. A. Walker, L. R. Ivey, M. McDonald
    &lt;p&gt;
    Cooling flows are common in galaxy clusters which have cool cores. The softX-ray emission below 1 keV from the flows is mostly absorbed by cold dusty gaswithin the central cooling sites. Further evidence for this process ispresented here through a more detailed analysis of the nearby Centaurus clusterand some additional clusters. Predictions of JWST near and mid-infrared spectrafrom cooling gas are presented. [NeVI] emission at 7.65 micron should be animportant diagnostic of gas cooling between 6 and 1.5 times 10^5 K. Theemerging overall picture of hidden cooling flows is explored. The efficiency ofAGN feedback in reducing the total cooling rate in cool cores is shown to beabove 50 percent for many clusters but is rarely above 90 per cent. Thereduction is mostly in outer gas. Cooling dominates in elliptical galaxies andgalaxy groups which have mass flow rates below about 15M/yr and in some massiveclusters where rates can exceed 1000M/yr.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 17 pages, 49 figures submitted to MNRAS
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10675v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10675v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>A. C. Fabian</author><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 16:17:20 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10675v1</guid></item><item><title>Spectroscopic confirmation of a dust-obscured, metal-rich dwarf galaxy  at z~5</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10954v1</link><description>L. Bisigello, G. Gandolfi, A. Feltre, P. Arrabal Haro, A. Calabrò, N. J. Cleri, L. Costantin, G. Girardi, M. Giulietti, A. Grazian, C. Gruppioni, N. P. Hathi, B. W. Holwerda, M. Llerena, R. A. Lucas, F. Pacucci, I. Prandoni, G. Rodighiero, L. -M. Seillé, S. M. Wilkins, M. Bagley, M. Dickinson., S. L. Finkelstein, J. Kartaltepe, A. M. Koekemoer, C. Papovich, N. Pirzkal
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present the first spectroscopic confirmation of a dust-obscured dwarfgalaxy, CEERS-14821.  The analysis is performed combining JWST NIRCam broad-band photometry andNIRSpec/PRISM spectroscopic data. From the detection of multiple rest-frameoptical lines, we derive that CEERS-14821 is located at $z=4.883\pm0.003$.Moreover, from a secure detection of the $H_{\alpha}$ and $H_{\beta}$ wederived that the galaxy has a dust extinction ranging from Av=2.2 to Av=3.3,depending on the assumed reddening law. This value is extremely large giventhat we estimated a low stellar mass around log(M/Mo)=8.0-8.2. Moreover, usingdifferent metallicity tracers, we verify that the galaxy is also metal-rich,with 12+log(O/H)&gt;8.3. This is well above the expectation from both themass-metallicity relation and the fundamental mass-metalliticy relation.CEERS-14821 is going through a burst of star formation, there are noindications of a strong contribution from an active galactic nuclei (f(AGN)&lt;0.5with respect to the total dust luminosity). Based on the rest-frame opticalimages, this source has a size compatible with galaxies of similar stellar massand redshift. Finally, with the current data, it seems that there are galaxiesclosely interacting with CEERS-14821.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 14 pages, 11 figures. Submitted to A&amp;A
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10954v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10954v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>L. Bisigello</author><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 18:00:02 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10954v1</guid></item><item><title>Seven wonders of Cosmic Dawn: JWST confirms a high abundance of galaxies  and AGNs at z $\simeq$ 9-11 in the GLASS field</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10967v1</link><description>L. Napolitano, M. Castellano, L. Pentericci, P. Arrabal Haro, A. Fontana, T. Treu, P. Bergamini, A. Calabro, S. Mascia, T. Morishita, G. Roberts-Borsani, P. Santini, E. Vanzella, B. Vulcani, D. Zakharova, T. Bakx, M. Dickinson, C. Grillo, N. Leethochawalit, M. Llerena, E. Merlin, D. Paris, S. Rojas-Ruiz, P. Rosati, X. Wang, I. Yoon, J. Zavala
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present JWST/NIRSpec PRISM follow-up of candidate galaxies at z=9-11selected from deep JWST/NIRCam photometry in GLASS-JWST Early Release Sciencedata. We spectroscopically confirm six sources with secure redshifts at z =9.52-10.43, each showing multiple emission lines. An additional object islikely at z = 10.66, based on its Lya-break and a single emission feature,while one source is a lower redshift interloper. The sample includes the firstJWST-detected candidate at z=10, GHZ1/GLASS-z10, which we confirm at z = 9.875,and the X-ray detected AGN GHZ9 confirmed at z = 10.145. Three objects in oursample, including GHZ9, have EW(CIII])&gt;20A and occupy a region compatible withAGN emission in the EW(CIII]) vs CIV/CIII] diagram. The spectroscopic sampleconfirms a high abundance of galaxies at z &gt; 9. We measure a number density ofz=10 galaxies in the GLASS-JWST ERS field that is a factor of &gt;3 higher thanother JWST-based estimates at demagnified rest-frame magnitudes of -21 &lt; Muv &lt;-19. We find that the positions of these galaxies in redshift and angular spaceare not consistent with all of them being part of a unique progenitor ofpresent-day galaxy clusters. The high density of objects in the GLASS regioncan be explained either by clustering on large scales or by a superposition ofdifferent forming structures of which we observe only the brightest members. Byconsidering all the spectroscopic z=10 sources in the Abell-2744 field, weidentify two potential galaxy proto-clusters centered around GHZ9 and JD1, withrelative separations between their members of 1-2 pMpc. The potential AGNnature of three of the sources in our sample lends support to a scenario inwhich the high abundance of bright sources determined by JWST surveys at cosmicdawn may be affected by AGN contribution to their UV luminosity.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Submitted to A&amp;A
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10967v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10967v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>L. Napolitano</author><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 18:00:22 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10967v1</guid></item><item><title>Tracing star formation across cosmic time at tens of parsec-scales in  the lensing cluster field Abell 2744</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10974v1</link><description>Adélaïde Claeyssens, Angela Adamo, Matteo Messa, Miroslava Dessauges-Zavadsky, Johan Richard, Ivan Kramarenko, Jorryt Matthee, Rohan P. Naidu
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present a sample of 1956 individual stellar clumps at redshift 0.7&lt;z&lt;10,detected with JWST/NIRCam in 476 galaxies lensed by the galaxy clusterAbell2744. The lensed clumps present magnifications ranging between $\mu$=1.8and $\mu$=300. We perform simultaneous size-photometry estimates in 20JWST/NIRCam median and broad-band filters from 0.7 to 5 $\mu$m. Spectral energydistribution (SED) fitting analyses enable us to recover the physicalproperties of the clumps. The majority of the clumps are spatially resolved andhave effective radii in the range R_eff = 10 - 700 pc. We restrict this firststudy to the 1751 post-reionisation era clumps with redshift &lt;5.5. We find asignificant evolution of the average clump ages, SFR, SFR surface densities andmetallicity with increasing redshift, while median stellar mass and stellarmass surface densities are similar in the probed redshift range. We observe astrong correlation between the clump properties and the properties of theirhost galaxies, with more massive galaxies hosting more massive and olderclumps. We find that clumps closer to their host galactic center are on averagemore massive, while their ages do not show clear sign of migration. We findthat clumps at cosmic noon sample the upper-mass end of the mass function tohigher masses than at z&gt;3, reflecting the rapid increase towards the peak ofthe cosmic star formation history. We conclude that the results achieved overthe studied redshift range are in agreement with expectation of in-situ clumpformation scenario from large-scale disk fragmentation.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Submitted to MNRAS, comments welcome
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10974v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10974v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Adélaïde Claeyssens</author><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 18:02:21 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10974v1</guid></item><item><title>The evolution of [OIII]$+\rm{H}β$ equivalent width from  $\mathbf{z\simeq3-8}$: implications for the production and escape of ionizing  photons during reionization</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10988v1</link><description>R. Begley, R. J. McLure, F. Cullen, D. J. McLeod, J. S. Dunlop, A. C. Carnall, T. M. Stanton, A. E. Shapley, R. Cochrane, C. T. Donnan, R. S. Ellis, A. Fontana, N. A. Grogin, A. M. Koekemoer
    &lt;p&gt;
    Accurately quantifying the ionizing photon production efficiency($\xi_\rm{ion}$) of $z&gt;6$ star-forming galaxies (SFGs) is necessary tounderstand their contribution to reionization. We investigate the ionizingproperties of N=289 SFGs selected at $z=6.9-7.6$ from the JWST Cycle-1 imagingprogrammes; PRIMER and JADES. We use BAGPIPES to consistently infer theequivalent widths of their [OIII]+$\rm{H\beta}$ emission lines ($W_\lambda$)and their physical properties. To supplement our high-redshift galaxies, wemeasure $W_\lambda$ photometrically for a sample of N=253 $z=3.2-3.6$ SFGsselected from the VANDELS spectroscopic survey. Comparing these samples, wefind a strong apparent redshift evolution in their median $W_\lambda$,increasing from $W_\lambda =310\pm25\,\r{A}$ in VANDELS to $W_\lambda=630\pm30\,\r{A}$ in our JWST-based sample. In the JWST sample at $z&gt;7$, wefind that $W_\lambda$ correlates with both stellar mass and UV luminosity, withhigh-mass, $M_{ UV}-$faint galaxies producing systematically weaker emissionlines. Moreover, we discover a departure from the standard log-normal shape ofthe $W_\lambda$ distribution, characterised by a more pronounced tail at lower$W_\lambda$, consistent with increasingly bursty star formation. Using$W_\lambda$ as a proxy for $\xi_\rm{ion}$, and UV spectral slope as a proxy forLyC escape fraction ($f_\rm{esc}$), we find a minority of galaxies with high$\xi_\rm{ion}$ and $f_\rm{esc}$ (e.g., $\rm{log(\xi_{ion}/erg^{-1}Hz})\sim25.6$and $f_\rm{esc}\sim0.15$). However, we find that the LyC photon budget at $z&gt;7$is dominated by galaxies with more moderate output, close to the sample medianof $\rm{log(\xi_{ion}/erg^{-1}Hz})\sim25.3$ and $f_\rm{esc}\sim0.05$. This isconsistent with estimates for the number of LyC photons required to powerreionization at $z&gt;7$, with no evidence for over or under-production.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 18 pages, 9 figures + 1 appendix. Submitted to MNRAS
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10988v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10988v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>R. Begley</author><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 18:15:54 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10988v1</guid></item><item><title>Direct High-resolution Observation of Feedback and Chemical Enrichment  in the Circumgalactic Medium at Redshift 2.8</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10993v1</link><description>Bo Peng, Fabrizio Arrigoni Battaia, Amit Vishwas, Mingyu Li, Eduardo Iani, Fengwu Sun, Qiong Li, Carl Ferkinhoff, Gordon Stacey, Zheng Cai
    &lt;p&gt;
    Although the circumgalactic medium (CGM) plays a vital role in galaxyevolution, studying the emission from CGM is challenging due to its low surfacebrightness and the complexities involved in interpreting resonant lines likeLy$\alpha$. The near-infrared coverage, unprecedented sensitivity, and highspatial resolution of the JWST enable us to study the optical strong linesassociated with the extended Ly$\alpha$ "nebulae" at redshift 2-3. These linesserve as diagnostic tools to infer the physical conditions in the massive CGMgas reservoir of these systems. In deep medium-band images taken by the JWST,we serendipitously discover the [O III] emission from the CGM surrounding amassive interacting galaxy system at redshift z ~ 2.8, known to be embedded ina bright extended (100 kpc) Ly$\alpha$ "nebula". This is the first time thatthe [O III] lines are detected from a Ly$\alpha$ "nebula", and the JWST imagesreveal that the CGM gas actually resides in narrow (~ 2.5 kpc) filamentarystructures with strong [O III] emission, tracing the same extent as theLy$\alpha$ emission. Analysis of the [O III] suggests that the emitting CGM isfully ionized and is energetically dominated by mechanical heating. We alsofind that the inferred density and pressure are higher than those commonlypredicted by simulations of the CGM. We conclude that the observed CGM emissionoriginates from the gas expelled by the episodic feedback processes, coolingdown and enriching the CGM, while travelling to a distance of at least 60 kpc.These observations demonstrate how fierce feedback processes shape gasdistribution and properties in the CGM around massive halos. While the deephigh-resolution imaging opens up a new discovery space for investigating theCGM, it also challenges numerical simulations to explain and reproduce theexquisitely complex structures revealed by the observations.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 13 pages, 6 figures, 1 table, submitted to A&amp;A Letter
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10993v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.10993v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Bo Peng</author><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 18:20:01 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10993v1</guid></item><item><title>GA-NIFS &amp; EIGER: A merging quasar host at z=7 with an overmassive black  hole</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11035v2</link><description>Madeline A. Marshall, Minghao Yue, Anna-Christina Eilers, Jan Scholtz, Michele Perna, Chris J. Willott, Roberto Maiolino, Hannah Übler, Santiago Arribas, Andrew J. Bunker, Stephane Charlot, Bruno Rodríguez Del Pino, Torsten Böker, Stefano Carniani, Giovanni Cresci, Francesco D'Eugenio, Gareth C. Jones, Giacomo Venturi, Rongmon Bordoloi, Daichi Kashino, Ruari Mackenzie, Jorryt Matthee, Rohan Naidu, Robert A. Simcoe
    &lt;p&gt;
    The James Webb Space Telescope is revolutionising our ability to understandthe host galaxies and local environments of high-z quasars. Here we obtain acomprehensive understanding of the host galaxy of the z=7.08 quasar J1120+0641by combining NIRSpec integral field spectroscopy with NIRCam photometry of thehost continuum emission. Our emission line maps reveal that this quasar host isundergoing a merger with a bright companion galaxy. The quasar host and thecompanion have similar dynamical masses of $\sim10^{10}M_\odot$, suggestingthat this is a major galaxy interaction. Through detailed quasar subtractionand SED fitting using the NIRCam data, we obtain an estimate of the hoststellar mass of $M_{\ast}\simeq2.6\times10^9M_\odot$, with$M_{*}\simeq5.0\times10^9M_\odot$ for the companion galaxy. Using the H$\beta$Balmer line we estimate a virial black hole mass of$M_{\rm{BH}}\simeq1.4\times10^9 M_\odot$. Thus, J1120+0641 has an extreme blackhole - stellar mass ratio of $M_{\rm{BH}}/M_\ast\simeq0.54$, which is ~3 dexlarger than expected by the local scaling relations between black hole andstellar mass. J1120+0641 is powered by an overmassive black hole with thehighest reported black hole - stellar mass ratio, in a quasar host that iscurrently undergoing a major merger -- these new insights highlight the powerof JWST for measuring and understanding these extreme first quasars.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Submitted to A&amp;A, comments welcome
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11035v2" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11035v2 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Madeline A. Marshall</author><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 19:36:02 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11035v2</guid></item><item><title>Unveiling two deeply embedded young protostars in the S68N Class 0  protostellar core with JWST/NIRSpec</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11095v1</link><description>Valentin J. M. Le Gouellec, Ben W. P. Lew, Thomas P. Greene, Doug Johnstone, Antoine Gusdorf, Logan Francis, Curtis DeWitt, Michael Meyer, Łukasz Tychoniec, Ewine F. van Dishoeck, Mary Barsony, Klaus W. Hodapp, Massimo Robberto
    &lt;p&gt;
    The near-infrared (NIR) emission of the youngest protostars still needs to becharacterized to better understand the evolution of their accretion andejection activity. We analyze James Webb Space Telescope NIRSpec 1.7 -- 5.3$\mu$m observations of two deeply embedded sources in the S68N protostellarcore in Serpens. The North Central (NC) source exhibits a highly obscuredspectrum (A_K ~ 4.8 mag) that is modeled with a pre-main-sequence photosphereand a hot disk component. The photospheric parameters are consistent with ayoung, low-mass photosphere, as suggested by the low surface gravity, log g of1.94 $\pm$ 0.15 cm s$^{-2}$. The hot disk suggests that accretion onto thecentral protostellar embryo is ongoing, although prototypical accretion-tracingemission lines HI are not detected. The South Central (SC) source, which iseven more embedded (A_K ~ 8 mag; no continuum is detected shortward of 3.6$\mu$m) appears to be driving the large-scale S68N protostellar outflow, andlaunches a collimated hot molecular jet detected in \Ht and CO ro-vibrationallines. Shock modeling of the \Ht (ro)vibrational lines establishes that fast$C$-type shocks ($\geq$ 30 km s$^{-1}$), with high pre-shock density ($\geq$$10^7$ cm$^{-3}$), and strong magnetic field (b ~ 3--10, where $B =b\,\times\,\sqrt{\textrm{n}_{\textrm{H}} (\textrm{cm}^{-3})}\,\mu\textrm{G}$)best match the data. The bright CO fundamental line forest suggests energeticexcitation, with the contribution of non-LTE effects, ie irradiation pumping.Detected OH and CH$^{+}$ ro-vibrational lines support this hypothesis. Thesetwo Class 0 protostars seem to be in very young evolutionary stages and stillhave to acquire the bulk of their final stellar masses. These resultsdemonstrate that JWST enables unprecedented diagnostics of these first stagesof the protostellar evolutionary phase.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11095v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11095v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Valentin J. M. Le Gouellec</author><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 21:16:10 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11095v1</guid></item><item><title>Spider-Webb: JWST Near Infrared Camera resolved galaxy star formation  and nuclear activities in the Spiderweb protocluster at z=2.16</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11174v1</link><description>Rhythm Shimakawa, Yusei Koyama, Tadayuki Kodama, Helmut Dannerbauer, J. M. Perez-Martinez, Huub J. A. Röttgering, Ichi Tanaka, Chiara D'Eugenio, Abdurrahman Naufal, Kazuki Daikuhara, Yuheng Zhang
    &lt;p&gt;
    Near-infrared (NIR) emission is less affected by dust than UV and opticalemission and is therefore useful for studying the properties of dust-obscuredgalaxies. Although rest-frame NIR observations of high-redshift galaxies havelong been made using space telescopes, their structures were unresolved due tothe lack of angular resolution. This letter reports the early results from theanalysis of high-resolution Pa$\beta$ imaging of the Spiderweb protocluster at$z=2.16$ with the JWST Near Infrared Camera. We investigate radial profiles ofPa$\beta$ lines and rest-frame NIR continua from luminous H$\alpha$-emittinggalaxies (HAEs) in the protocluster. Particularly, we compare those of 11 HAEs(N-HAEs) on the star-forming main sequence with those of 8 HAEs (X-HAEs) withX-ray AGNs. Resultant composite Pa$\beta$ line images of N-HAEs indicatesignificant star formation in galactic disks. In contrast, X-HAEs are dominatedby point source components rather than outer star formation, as inferred fromour earlier work based on multi-wavelength SED fitting. Given their higherstellar potentials suggested from their rest-frame NIR images, the differentcharacteristics may be driven by the impact of AGN feedback.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 6 pages, 6 figures; Accepted for publication in MNRAS Letters
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11174v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11174v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Rhythm Shimakawa</author><pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 01:25:51 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11174v1</guid></item><item><title>Exploring the effect of different cosmologies on the Epoch of  Reionization 21-cm signal with POLAR</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11620v1</link><description>Anshuman Acharya, Qing-bo Ma, Sambit K. Giri, Benedetta Ciardi, Raghunath Ghara, Garrelt Mellema, Saleem Zaroubi, Ian Hothi, Ilian T. Iliev, Léon V. E. Koopmans, Michele Bianco
    &lt;p&gt;
    A detection of the 21-cm signal power spectrum from the Epoch of Reionizationis imminent, thanks to consistent advancements from telescopes such as LOFAR,MWA, and HERA, along with the development of SKA. In light of this progress, itis crucial to expand the parameter space of simulations used to inferastrophysical properties from this signal. In this work, we explore the role ofcosmological parameters such as the Hubble constant $H_0$ and the matterclustering amplitude $\sigma_8$, whose values as provided by measurements atdifferent redshifts are in tension. We run $N$-body simulations using GADGET-4,and post-process them with the reionization simulation code POLAR, that usesL-GALAXIES to include galaxy formation and evolution properties and GRIZZLY toexecute 1-D radiative transfer of ionizing photons in the intergalactic medium(IGM). We compare our results with the latest JWST observations and explorewhich astrophysical properties for different cosmologies are necessary to matchthe observed UV luminosity functions at redshifts $z = 10$ and 9. Additionally,we explore the impact of these parameters on the observed 21-cm signal powerspectrum, focusing on the redshifts within the range of LOFAR 21-cm signalobservations ($z \approx 8.5-10$). Despite differences in cosmological andastrophysical parameters, the 21-cm power spectrum at these redshifts agreeswith presently observed upper limits. This suggests the need for broaderphysical parameter spaces for inference modeling to account for all models thatagree with observations. However, we also propose stronger constraining powerby using a combination of galactic and IGM observables.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 16 pages, 8 figures, 2 tables. Submitted to the Monthly Notices of  the Royal Astronomical Society (MNRAS)
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11620v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11620v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Anshuman Acharya</author><pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 13:58:39 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11620v1</guid></item><item><title>Population synthesis and astrophysical inference for high-$z$ JWST  galaxies</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11680v1</link><description>Trey Driskell, Ethan O. Nadler, Andrew Benson, Vera Gluscevic
    &lt;p&gt;
    Observations of the high-$z$ Universe from JWST have revealed a newpopulation of bright, early galaxies. A robust statistical interpretation ofthis data requires fast forward models that account for uncertainties in galaxyevolution and incorporate observational systematic effects. We present aprobabilistic framework for population synthesis of high-$z$ galaxies andinference of their properties. Our framework is based on the semi-analyticgalaxy-formation model Galacticus. To infer the astrophysical parametersgoverning high-$z$ galaxy evolution, we analyze JWST data from the CEERS andNGDEEP surveys and calculate the likelihood of observing individual objects inapparent magnitude--redshift space, for $z\geq8.5$ galaxy candidates. Weinclude observational selection effects due to limited survey volume and depth,as well as photometric redshift uncertainties. We recover the posteriorprobability distribution for parameters describing star formation and outflowrates. We place an upper limit on the star formation timescale of$500~\mathrm{Myr}$ at a disk velocity of $50~\mathrm{km\ s}^{-1}$, and we infera characteristic velocity at which the outflow mass-loading factor is $\sim 1$of $150^{+280}_{-60}~\mathrm{km\ s}^{-1}$, both at $95\%$ confidence.Marginalizing over our astrophysical model, we find that galaxies in CEERS andNGDEEP data occupy halos with virial masses $10^{10\pm 0.5}~M_{\mathrm{\odot}}$at $8.5\leq z\leq 12$, at $95\%$ confidence. The star formation timescalepreferred by our fit is relatively short compared to typical values at lowerredshifts, consistent with previous findings. The modeling and analysisframework presented here can enable systematic tests of high-$z$ galaxies' dustcontent, initial mass functions, and star formation burstiness in the future.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 14 pages, 10 figures
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11680v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11680v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Trey Driskell</author><pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 15:18:46 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11680v1</guid></item><item><title>The JWST Emission Line Survey (JELS): An untargeted search for H$α$  emission line galaxies at $z &gt; 6$ and their physical properties</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11808v1</link><description>C. A. Pirie, P. N. Best, K. J. Duncan, D. J. McLeod, R. K. Cochrane, M. Clausen, J. S. Dunlop, S. R. Flury, J. E. Geach, C. L. Hale, E. Ibar, R. Kondapally, Zefeng Li, J. Matthee, R. J. McLure, L. Ossa-Fuentes, A. L. Patrick, Ian Smail, D. Sobral, H. M. O. Stephenson, J. P. Stott, A. M. Swinbank
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present the first results of the JWST Emission Line Survey (JELS).Utilising the first NIRCam narrow-band imaging at 4.7$\mu$m, over 63arcmin$^{2}$ in the PRIMER/COSMOS field, we have identified 609 emission linegalaxy candidates. From these, we robustly selected 35 H$\alpha$ star-forminggalaxies at $z \sim 6.1$, with H$\alpha$ star-formation rates($\rm{SFR_{H\alpha}}$) of $\sim0.9-15\ \rm{M_{\odot} yr^{-1}}$. Combining ourunique H$\alpha$ sample with the exquisite panchromatic data in the field, weexplore their physical properties and star-formation histories, and comparethese to a broad-band selected sample at $z\sim 6$ to offer vital new insightinto the nature of high-redshift galaxies. UV-continuum slopes ($\beta$) areconsiderably redder for our H$\alpha$ sample ($\langle\beta\rangle\sim-1.92$)compared to the broad-band sample ($\langle\beta\rangle\sim-2.35$). This is notdue to dust attenuation as our H$\alpha$ sample is relatively dust-poor (median$A_V=0.23$); instead, we argue that the reddened slopes could be due to nebularcontinuum. We compared $\rm{SFR_{H\alpha}}$ and the UV-continuum-derived$\rm{SFR_{UV}}$ to SED-fitted measurements averaged over canonical timescalesof 10 and 100 Myr ($\rm{SFR_{10}}$ and $\rm{SFR_{100}}$). We find an increasein recent SFR for our sample of H$\alpha$ emitters, particularly at lowerstellar masses ($&lt;10^9 \rm{M_{\odot}}$). We also find that $\rm{SFR_{H\alpha}}$strongly traces SFR averaged over 10 Myr timescales, whereas the UV-continuumover-predicts SFR on 100 Myr timescales at low stellar masses. These resultspoint to our H$\alpha$ sample undergoing `bursty' star formation. Our F356W $z\sim 6$ sample show a larger scatter in $\rm{SFR_{10}/SFR_{100}}$ across allstellar masses, highlighting how narrow-band photometric selections ofH$\alpha$ emitters are key to quantifying the burstiness of star-formationactivity.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: Submitted to MRNAS; 27 pages, 19 figures. Accompanying data will be  publicly released upon acceptance of this manuscript
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11808v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11808v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>C. A. Pirie</author><pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 17:35:19 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11808v1</guid></item><item><title>A First-look at Spatially-resolved Infrared Supernova Remnants in M33  with JWST</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11821v1</link><description>Sumit K. Sarbadhicary, Erik Rosolowsky, Adam K. Leroy, Thomas G. Williams, Eric W. Koch, Joshua Peltonen, Adam Smercina, Julianne J. Dalcanton, Simon C. O. Glover, Margaret Lazzarini, Ryan Chown, Jennifer Donovan Meyer, Karin Sandstrom, Benjamin F. Williams, Elizabeth Tarantino
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present the first spatially-resolved infrared images of supernova remnants(SNRs) in M33 with the unprecedented sensitivity and resolution of JWST. Weanalyze 43 SNRs in four JWST fields: two covering central and southern M33 withseparate NIRCam (F335M, F444W) and MIRI (F560W, F2100W) observations, one$\sim$5 kpc-long radial strip observed with MIRI F770W, and one covering thegiant HII region NGC 604 with multiple NIRCam and MIRI broad/narrowbandfilters. Of the 21 SNRs in the MIRI field, we found three clear detections(i.e., identical infrared and \ha morphologies), and six partial-detections,implying a detection fraction of 43\% in these bands. In contrast, only one SNR(out of 16) is detectable in the NIRCam field. One of the SNRs, L10-080, is apotential candidate for having freshly-formed ejecta dust, based on its sizeand centrally-concentrated 21 \mum emission. Two SNRs near NGC 604 have strongevidence of molecular (H$_2$) emission at 4.7 \mum, making them the farthestknown SNRs with visible molecular shocks. Five SNRs have F770W observations,with the smaller younger objects showing tentative signs of emission, while theolder, larger ones have voids. Multi-wavelength data indicate that theclearly-detected SNRs are also among the smallest, brightest at otherwavelengths (\ha, radio and X-ray), have the broadest line widths (H$\alpha$FWHM$\sim$250-350 km/s), and the densest environments. No strong correlationwith star-formation histories are seen, with the clearly-detected SNRs havingboth high-mass ($\sim$35 \Msun) and low-mass ($\lesssim$10 \Msun) progenitors.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 33 pages, 17 figures, 2 tables, submitted to ApJ
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11821v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11821v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Sumit K. Sarbadhicary</author><pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 17:49:07 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11821v1</guid></item><item><title>Discovery of a 25 parsec-long precessing jet emanating from the old nova  GK Persei</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12103v1</link><description>Michael M. Shara, Kenneth M. Lanzetta, James T. Garland, David Valls-Gabaud, Stefan Gromoll, Mikita Misiura, Frederick M. Walter, John K. Webb, Barrett Martin
    &lt;p&gt;
    Classical nova eruptions result from thermonuclear-powered runaways in, andejection of, the hydrogen-rich envelopes of white dwarf stars accreted fromtheir close binary companions. Novae brighten to up to 1,000,000 solarluminosities, and recur thousands of times over their lifetimes spanningseveral billion years. Between eruptions, mass transfer from the donor star tothe white dwarf proceeds via an accretion disk unless the white dwarf possessesa strong magnetic field which can partially or totally disrupt the disk. Inthat case, accretion is focussed by the white dwarf's magnetic field towardsits magnetic poles. Optical spectroscopy and interferometric radio mapsdemonstrate the presence of bipolar jets, typically arcsec in angular size, andorders of magnitude smaller than one parsec in linear size, during the days tomonths after nova eruptions. These jets expel collimated matter from the whitedwarfs in nova binary stars, but well-resolved images of them are lacking. Herewe report the Condor telescope's detection of a hitherto unknown, highlyresolved and braided jet, three degrees (at least 25 parsecs) in length. Thejet originates at the white dwarf of the old nova GK Persei (nova Per 1901 CE).It precesses on a ~ 3600 yr timescale, and must be at least 7200 years old.Detected across four decades of wavelength, the jet's ultimate energy source islikely the strong accretion shocks near the white dwarf's magnetic poles.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 18 pages, 4 figures
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.12103v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.12103v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Michael M. Shara</author><pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 22:59:42 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12103v1</guid></item><item><title>The Physical Origin of Extreme Emission Line Galaxies at High redshifts:  Strong {\sc [Oiii]} Emission Lines Produced by Obscured AGNs</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12198v1</link><description>Chenghao Zhu, Yuichi Harikane, Masami Ouchi, Yoshiaki Ono, Masato Onodera, Shenli Tang, Yuki Isobe, Yoshiki Matsuoka, Toshihiro Kawaguchi, Hiroya Umeda, Kimihiko Nakajima, Yongming Liang, Yi Xu, Yechi Zhang, Dongsheng Sun, Kazuhiro Shimasaku, Jenny Greene, Kazushi Iwasawa, Kotaro Kohno, Tohru Nagao, Andreas Schulze, Takatoshi Shibuya, Miftahul Hilmi, Malte Schramm
    &lt;p&gt;
    We present deep Subaru/FOCAS spectra for two extreme emission line galaxies(EELGs) at $z\sim 1$ with strong {\sc[Oiii]}$\lambda$5007 emission lines,exhibiting equivalent widths (EWs) of $2905^{+946}_{-578}$ \AA\ and$2000^{+188}_{-159}$ \AA, comparable to those of EELGs at high redshifts thatare now routinely identified with JWST spectroscopy. Adding a similarly large{\sc [Oiii]} EW ($2508^{+1487}_{-689}$ \AA) EELG found at $z\sim 2$ in the JWSTCEERS survey to our sample, we explore for the physical origins of the large{\sc [Oiii]} EWs of these three galaxies with the Subaru spectra and variouspublic data including JWST/NIRSpec, NIRCam, and MIRI data. While there are noclear signatures of AGN identified by the optical line diagnostics, we findthat two out of two galaxies covered by the MIRI data show strong near-infraredexcess in the spectral energy distributions (SEDs) indicating obscured AGN.Because none of the three galaxies show clear broad H$\beta$ lines, the upperlimits on the flux ratios of broad-H$\beta$ to {\sc [Oiii]} lines are small,$\lesssim 0.15$ that are comparable with Seyfert $1.8-2.0$ galaxies. We conduct\texttt{Cloudy} modeling with the stellar and AGN incident spectra, allowing awide range of parameters including metallicities and ionization parameters. Wefind that the large {\sc [Oiii]} EWs are not self-consistently reproduced bythe spectra of stars or unobscured AGN, but obscured AGN that efficientlyproduces O$^{++}$ ionizing photons with weak nuclear and stellar continua thatare consistent with the SED shapes.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: submitted to ApJ
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.12198v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.12198v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Chenghao Zhu</author><pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 03:43:49 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12198v1</guid></item><item><title>Infrared Spectra of Solid-State Ethanolamine: Laboratory Data in Support  of JWST Observations</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12235v1</link><description>T. Suhasaria, S. M. Wee, R. Basalgète, S. A. Krasnokutski, C. Jäger, G. Perotti, Th. Henning
    &lt;p&gt;
    Ethanolamine (NH$_2$CH$_2$CH$_2$OH, EA) has been identified in the gas phaseof the ISM within molecular clouds. Although EA has not been directly observedin the molecular ice phase, a solid state formation mechanism has beenproposed. However, the current literature lacks an estimation of the infraredband strengths of EA ices. We conducted an experimental investigation of solidEA ice at low temperatures to ascertain its infrared band strengths, phasetransition temperature, and multilayer binding energy. The commonly used laserinterferometry method was not applied. Infrared band strengths were determinedusing three distinct methods. The obtained lab spectrum of EA was compared withthe publicly available MIRI MRS James Webb Space Telescope observations towarda low mass protostar. The phase transition temperature for EA ice falls withinthe range of 175 to 185 K. Among the discussed methods, the simple pressuregauge method provides a reasonable estimate of band strength. We derive a bandstrength value of about $1\times10^{-17}$ cm molecule$^{-1}$ for the NH$_2$bending mode in the EA molecules. Additionally, temperature-programmeddesorption analysis yielded a multilayer desorption energy of 0.61$\pm$0.01 eV.By comparing the laboratory data documented in this study with the JWSTspectrum of the low mass protostar IRAS 2A, an upper-limit for the EA iceabundances was derived.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 8 pages, 5 figures
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.12235v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.12235v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>T. Suhasaria</author><pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 04:53:26 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12235v1</guid></item><item><title>Galaxy Mass Modelling from Multi-Wavelength JWST Strong Lens Analysis:  Dark Matter Substructure, Angular Mass Complexity, or Both?</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12987v1</link><description>Samuel C. Lange, Aristeidis Amvrosiadis, James W. Nightingale, Qiuhan He, Carlos S. Frenk, Andrew Robertson, Shaun Cole, Richard Massey, Xiaoyue Cao, Ran Li, Kaihao Wang
    &lt;p&gt;
    We analyze two galaxy-scale strong gravitational lenses, SPT0418-47 andSPT2147-50, using JWST NIRCam imaging across multiple filters. To account forangular complexity in the lens mass distribution, we introduce multipoleperturbations with orders $m=1, 3, 4$. Our results show strong evidence forangular mass complexity in SPT2147, with multipole strengths of 0.3-1.7 $\%$for $m=3, 4$ and 2.4-9.5 $\%$ for $m=1$, while SPT0418 shows no suchpreference. We also test lens models that include a dark matter substructure,finding a strong preference for a substructure in SPT2147-50 with a Bayesfactor (log-evidence change) of $\sim 60$ when multipoles are not included.Including multipoles reduces the Bayes factor to $\sim 11$, still correspondingto a $5\sigma$ detection of a subhalo with an NFW mass of$\log_{10}(M_{200}/M_{\odot}) = 10.87\substack{+0.53\\ -0.71}$. WhileSPT2147-50 may represent the fourth detection of a dark matter substructure ina strong lens, further analysis is needed to confirm that the signal is not dueto systematics associated with the lens mass model.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 16 pages, 11 figures, submitted to MNRAS
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.12987v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.12987v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Samuel C. Lange</author><pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 19:32:47 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12987v1</guid></item><item><title>Lyman Continuum leakage from massive leaky starbursts: A different class  of emitters?</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13254v1</link><description>Namrata Roy, Timothy Heckman, Alaina Henry, John Chisholm, Sophia Flury, Claus Leitherer, Matthew J. Hayes, Anne Jaskot, Zhiyuan Ji, Daniel Schaerer, Bingjie Wang, Sanchayeeta Borthakur, Xinfeng Xu, Göran Östlin
    &lt;p&gt;
    The origin of Lyman Continuum (LyC) photons responsible for reionizing theuniverse remains a mystery, with the fraction of escaping LyC photons fromgalaxies at z$\sim$ 6 to 12 being highly uncertain. While direct detection ofLyC photons from this epoch is hindered by absorption from the intergalacticmedium, lower redshift analogs offer a promising avenue to study LyC leakage.We present Hubble Space Telescope Cosmic Origins Spectrograph (HST COS)observations of five low redshift (z$\sim$ 0.3) massive starburst galaxies,selected for their high stellar mass and weak [SII] nebular emission - anindirect tracer of LyC escape. Three of the five galaxies show LyC leakage,highlighting the reliability of weak [SII] as a tracer, especially in light ofrecent JWST discoveries of z $&gt;$ 5 galaxies with similarly weak [SII] emission.The dust corrected LyC escape fractions, which represent the LyC photons thatwould escape in the absence of dust, range from 33% to 84%. However, theabsolute escape fractions, which show the LyC photons escaping after passingthrough both neutral hydrogen absorption and dust attenuation, aresignificantly lower, ranging between 1% and 3%. This suggests that while thegalaxies are nearly optically thin to HI, their high dust content significantlysuppresses LyC photon escape. These [SII] weak, massive leakers are distinctfrom typical low-redshift LyC emitters, showing higher metallicity, lowerionization states, more dust extinction and higher star formation surfacedensities. This suggests that these galaxies constitute a distinct population,likely governed by a different mechanism facilitating LyC photon escape. Wepropose that the feedback-driven winds in these compact starbursts createionized channels through which LyC photons escape, aligning with a picket-fencemodel.
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    Comments: 16 pages, 10 figures, 1 Table
    &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;
    PDF: &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.13254v1" /&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.13254v1 &lt;/a&gt;
    ]]</description><author>Namrata Roy</author><pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 06:21:22 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13254v1</guid></item></channel></rss>