<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>JWST arXiv Feed (author)</title><link>https://github.com/gbrammer/arxiv-to-rss</link><description>Custom arXiv Query of JWST articles</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 05:06:36 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.1.1</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Spatial Variation in Strong Line Ratios and Physical Conditions in Two Strongly-Lensed Galaxies at z~1.4</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.11387v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Michael K. Florian, Jane R. Rigby, Ayan Acharyya, Keren Sharon, Michael D. Gladders, Lisa Kewley, Gourav Khullar, Katya Gozman, Gabriel Brammer, Ivelina Momcheva, David Nicholls, Stephanie LaMassa, Hakon Dahle, Matthew B. Bayliss, Eva Wuyts, Traci Johnson, Katherine Whitaker &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For studies of galaxy formation and evolution, one of the major benefits of the James Webb Space Telescope is that space-based IFUs like those on its NIRSpec and MIRI instruments will enable spatially resolved spectroscopy of distant galaxies, including spectroscopy at the scale of individual star-forming regions in galaxies that have been gravitationally lensed. In the meantime, there is only a very small subset of lensed sources where work like this is possible even with the Hubble Space Telescope's Wide Field Camera 3 infrared channel grisms. We examine two of these sources, SDSS J1723+3411 and SDSS J2340+2947, using HST WFC3/IR grism data and supporting spatially-unresolved spectroscopy from several ground-based instruments to explore the size of spatial variations in observed strong emission line ratios like O32, R23, which are sensitive to ionization parameter and metallicity, and the Balmer decrement as an indicator of reddening. We find significant spatial variation in the reddening and the reddening-corrected O32 and R23 values which correspond to spreads of a few tenths of a dex in ionization parameter and metallicity. We also find clear evidence of a negative radial gradient in star formation in SDSS J2340+2947 and tentative evidence of one in SDSS J1723+3411, though its star formation is quite asymmetric. Finally, we find that reddening can vary enough spatially to make spatially-resolved reddening corrections necessary in order to characterize gradients in line ratios and the physical conditions inferred from them, necessitating the use of space-based IFUs for future work on larger, more statistically robust samples.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2020-06-19T21:10:02Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2020-06-19T21:10:02Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 24 pages, including references, 6 tables, 17 figures, and appendix.   Submitted to ApJ June 19, 2020 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2006.11387v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2006.11387v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Michael K. Florian</author><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 21:10:02 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.11387v1</guid></item><item><title>Metal Deficiency in Two Massive Dead Galaxies at z~2</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/1803.01852v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; T. Morishita, L. E. Abramson, T. Treu, X. Wang, G. B. Brammer, P. Kelly, M. Stiavelli, T. Jones, K. B. Schmidt, M. Trenti, B. Vulcani &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Local massive early-type galaxies are believed to have completed most of their star formation ~10Gyr ago and evolved without having substantial star formation since. If so, their progenitors should have roughly solar stellar metallicities (Z_*), comparable to their values today. We report the discovery of two lensed massive (log M_*/M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;~11), z~2.2 dead galaxies, that appear markedly metal deficient given this scenario. Using 17-band HST+K_s+Spitzer photometry and deep HST grism spectra from the GLASS and SN Refsdal follow-up campaigns covering features near &amp;lambda;_rest~4000&amp;#8491;, we find these systems to be dominated by A-type stars with log Z_*/Z&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;=-0.40±0.02 and -0.49±0.03 (30-40&amp;percnt; solar) under standard assumptions. The second system's lower metallicity is robust to isochrone changes, though this choice can drive the first system's from log Z_*/Z&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;=-0.6 to 0.1. If these two galaxies are representative of larger samples, this finding suggests that evolutionary paths other than dry minor-merging are required for these massive galaxies. Future analyses with direct metallicity measurements-e.g., by the James Webb Space Telescope-will provide critical insight into the nature of such phenomena.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2018-03-05T19:00:00Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2018-03-05T19:00:00Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; Accepted for publication in Astrophysical Journal Letters; 6 pages, 3   figures, 1 table &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1803.01852v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/1803.01852v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>T. Morishita</author><pubDate>Mon, 05 Mar 2018 19:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/1803.01852v1</guid></item><item><title>The Number Density Evolution of Extreme Emission Line Galaxies in 3D-HST: Results from a Novel Automated Line Search Technique for Slitless Spectroscopy</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/1608.01674v2</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Michael V. Maseda, Arjen van der Wel, Hans-Walter Rix, Ivelina Momcheva, Gabriel B. Brammer, Marijn Franx, Britt F. Lundgren, Rosalind E. Skelton, Katherine E. Whitaker &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The multiplexing capability of slitless spectroscopy is a powerful asset in creating large spectroscopic datasets, but issues such as spectral confusion make the interpretation of the data challenging. Here we present a new method to search for emission lines in the slitless spectroscopic data from the 3D-HST survey utilizing the Wide-Field Camera 3 on board the Hubble Space Telescope. Using a novel statistical technique, we can detect compact (extended) emission lines at 90% completeness down to fluxes of 1.5 (3.0) times 10^-17 erg/s/cm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, close to the noise level of the grism exposures, for objects detected in the deep ancillary photometric data. Unlike previous methods, the Bayesian nature allows for probabilistic line identifications, namely redshift estimates, based on secondary emission line detections and/or photometric redshift priors. As a first application, we measure the comoving number density of Extreme Emission Line Galaxies (restframe [O III] 5007 equivalent widths in excess of 500 Angstroms). We find that these galaxies are nearly 10 times more common above z~1.5 than at z&amp;lt;0.5. With upcoming large grism surveys such as Euclid and WFIRST as well as grisms featuring prominently on the NIRISS and NIRCam instruments on James Webb Space Telescope, methods like the one presented here will be crucial for constructing emission line redshift catalogs in an automated and well-understood manner.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2016-08-04T20:00:01Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2018-01-16T23:46:19Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 16 pages, 14 Figures; Accepted to ApJ &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1608.01674v2"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/1608.01674v2 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Michael V. Maseda</author><pubDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2016 20:00:01 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/1608.01674v2</guid></item></channel></rss>