<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>JWST arXiv Feed (feed)</title><link>https://github.com/gbrammer/arxiv-to-rss</link><description>Custom arXiv Query of JWST articles</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 Jul 2025 05:10:06 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.1.1</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>COSMOS-Web: Comprehensive Data Reduction for Wide-Area JWST NIRCam Imaging</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03256v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Maximilien Franco, Caitlin M. Casey, Anton M. Koekemoer, Daizhong Liu, Micaela B. Bagley, Henry Joy McCracken, Jeyhan S. Kartaltepe, Hollis B. Akins, Olivier Ilbert, Marko Shuntov, Santosh Harish, Brant E. Robertson, Rafael C. Arango-Toro, Andrew J. Battisti, Nima Chartab, Nicole E. Drakos, Andreas L. Faisst, Carter Flayhart, Ghassem Gozaliasl, Michaela Hirschmann, Richard Massey, Jason Rhodes, Zahra Sattari, Diana Scognamiglio, John R. Weaver, Lilan Yang, Jorge A. Zavala, Edward M. Berman, Fabrizio Gentile, Steven Gillman, Arianna S. Long, Georgios Magdis, Jacqueline E. McCleary, Jed McKinney, Bahram Mobasher, Louise Paquereau, Armin Rest, David B. Sanders, Sune Toft, Si-Yue Yu &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We present the data reduction methodology used for the COSMOS-Web survey JWST NIRCam data. Covering 0.54 deg&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; with four broadband filters (F115W, F150W, F277W, F444W) and a total exposure time of approximately 270 hours, COSMOS-Web represents the largest contiguous field surveyed during JWST Cycle 1, posing unique data reduction challenges due to its extensive scale. By combining the official JWST Calibration Pipeline with custom improvements for noise removal, background subtraction, and astrometric alignment, we achieve high fidelity science-ready mosaics. We detail the systematic approach employed in the three stages of the JWST Calibration Pipeline. The data, collected in three epochs from January 2023 to January 2024, encompass 152 visits and have been processed into 20 mosaic tiles to optimize computational efficiency and data processing. The final data products achieve 5 sigma depths of 26.7-28.3 AB mag in 0.15" apertures. The processed and calibrated datasets are made available to the public.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-06-03T18:00:05Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-06-03T18:00:05Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 22 pages, 11 figures, Submitted to ApJ &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2506.03256v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2506.03256v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Maximilien Franco</author><pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 18:00:05 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03256v1</guid></item><item><title>The Pandora project. II: how non-thermal physics drives bursty star formation and temperate mass-loaded outflows in dwarf galaxies</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03245v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Sergio Martin-Alvarez, Debora Sijacki, Martin G. Haehnelt, Alice Concas, Yuxuan Yuan, Roberto Maiolino, Risa H. Wechsler, Francisco Rodríguez Montero, Marion Farcy, Mahsa Sanati, Yohan Dubois, Joki Rosdahl, Enrique Lopez-Rodriguez, Susan E. Clark &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Dwarf galaxies provide powerful laboratories for studying galaxy formation physics. Their early assembly, shallow gravitational potentials, and bursty, clustered star formation histories make them especially sensitive to the processes that regulate baryons through multi-phase outflows. Using high-resolution, cosmological zoom-in simulations of a dwarf galaxy from itthe Pandora suite, we explore the impact of stellar radiation, magnetic fields, and cosmic ray feedback on star formation, outflows, and metal retention. We find that our purely hydrodynamical model without non-thermal physics - in which supernova feedback is boosted to reproduce realistic stellar mass assembly - drives violent, overly enriched outflows that suppress the metal content of the host galaxy. Including radiation reduces the clustering of star formation and weakens feedback. However, the additional incorporation of cosmic rays produces fast, mass-loaded, multi-phase outflows consisting of both ionized and neutral gas components, in better agreement with observations. These outflows, which entrain a denser, more temperate ISM, exhibit broad metallicity distributions while preserving metals within the galaxy. Furthermore, the star formation history becomes more bursty, in agreement with recent JWST findings. These results highlight the essential role of non-thermal physics in galaxy evolution and the need to incorporate it in future galaxy formation models.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-06-03T18:00:01Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-06-03T18:00:01Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; Submitted to MNRAS. 15 pages of main text, 9 figures, 3 appendices &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2506.03245v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2506.03245v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Sergio Martin-Alvarez</author><pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 18:00:01 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03245v1</guid></item><item><title>Age dependence of Lyα escape fraction of Lyα emitters and their significant role in cosmic reionization</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03242v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Shunta Shimizu, Nobunari Kashikawa, Satoshi Kikuta, Yoshihiro Takeda, Junya Arita, Ryo Emori, Kentaro Koretomo &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We study the Ly&amp;alpha; escape fraction, f&lt;sub&gt;esc&lt;/sub&gt;^Ly&amp;alpha; of Ly&amp;alpha; emitters (LAEs) identified by Subaru/HSC narrowband imaging at z = 2.2-6.6, using publicly available deep imaging data from HST and JWST. We perform SED fitting for 127 LAEs at 0.4 - 5.0  &amp;mu; m to estimate their physical properties robustly, and confirm that two distinct LAE populations exist: young LAEs (&amp;lt; 100 Myr) and old LAEs (&amp;gt; 100 Myr). Young LAEs are characterized by burst-like star formation activity and low dust content, significantly differing from Lyman-break galaxies (LBGs) at the same stellar mass, while old LAEs show similar star formation activity to LBGs, yet with lower dust content and more compact morphology in rest-UV/optical than LBGs. The f&lt;sub&gt;esc&lt;/sub&gt;^Ly&amp;alpha; of LAEs is anticorrelated with stellar mass, and this correlation is found to depend on the age of LAEs, such that old LAEs show a weaker anticorrelation than young LAEs, and tend to exhibit higher f&lt;sub&gt;esc&lt;/sub&gt;^Ly&amp;alpha; than young LAEs at a given stellar mass. This implies that Ly&amp;alpha; photons escape more efficiently from old LAEs, possibly through the low-density channels of HI and dust created by outflows. The average f&lt;sub&gt;esc&lt;/sub&gt;^Ly&amp;alpha; of young LAEs remains nearly constant at ~40% at z = 2.2-6.6, suggesting that the previously observed evolution of global f&lt;sub&gt;esc&lt;/sub&gt;^Ly&amp;alpha; of star-forming galaxies (SFGs) is due to the changes in the LAE fraction among the SFGs. Converting f&lt;sub&gt;esc&lt;/sub&gt;^Ly&amp;alpha; to Lyman continuum escape fraction using empirical relations, we demonstrate that LAEs alone can supply the ionizing photons necessary for reionization at z~6, causing rapid and late reionization.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-06-03T18:00:00Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-06-03T18:00:00Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 19 pages, 14 figures, submitted to MNRAS &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2506.03242v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2506.03242v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Shunta Shimizu</author><pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03242v1</guid></item><item><title>COSMOS2025: The COSMOS-Web galaxy catalog of photometry, morphology, redshifts, and physical parameters from JWST, HST, and ground-based imaging</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03243v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Marko Shuntov, Hollis B. Akins, Louise Paquereau, Caitlin M. Casey, Olivier Ilbert, Rafael C. Arango-Toro, Henry Joy McCracken, Maximilien Franco, Santosh Harish, Jeyhan S. Kartaltepe, Anton M. Koekemoer, Lilan Yang, Marc Huertas-Company, Edward M. Berman, Jacqueline E. McCleary, Sune Toft, Raphaël Gavazzi, Mark J. Achenbach, Emmanuel Bertin, Malte Brinch, Jackie Champagne, Nima Chartab, Nicole E. Drakos, Eiichi Egami, Ryan Endsley, Andreas L. Faisst, Xiaohui Fan, Carter Flayhart, William G. Hartley, Hossein Hatamnia, Ghassem Gozaliasl, Fabrizio Gentile, Iris Jermann, Shuowen Jin, Koki Kakiichi, Ali Ahmad Khostovan, Martin Kümmel, Clotilde Laigle, Ronaldo Laishram, Erini Lambrides, Daizhong Liu, Jianwei Lyu, Georgios Magdis, Bahram Mobasher, Thibaud Moutard, Alvio Renzini, Brant E. Robertson, Marc Schefer, Diana Scognamiglio, Nick Scoville, Zahra Sattari, David B. Sanders, Sina Taamoli, Benny Trakhtenbrot, Francesco Valentino, Feige Wang, John R. Weaver, Jinyl Yang &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We present COSMOS2025, the COSMOS-Web catalog of photometry, morphology, photometric redshifts and physical parameters for more than 700,000 galaxies in the Cosmic Evolution Survey (COSMOS) field. This catalog is based on our itJames Webb Space Telescope 255 h COSMOS-Web program, which provides deep near-infrared imaging in four NIRCam (F115W, F150W, F277W, F444W) and one MIRI (F770W) filter over the central ~ 0.54   deg&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; (~ 0.2   deg&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; for MIRI) in COSMOS. These data are combined with ground- and space-based data to derive photometric measurements of NIRCam-detected sources using both fixed-aperture photometry (on the space-based bands) and a profile-fitting technique on all 37 bands spanning 0.3-8 micron. We provide morphology for all sources from complementary techniques including profile fitting and machine-learning classification. We derive photometric redshifts, physical parameters and non-parametric star formation histories from spectral energy distribution (SED) fitting. The catalog has been extensively validated against previous COSMOS catalogs and other surveys. Photometric redshift accuracy measured using spectroscopically confirmed galaxies out to z~9 reaches &amp;sigma;_MAD = 0.012 at m_F444W&amp;lt;28 and remains at &amp;sigma;_MAD ≲ 0.03 as a function of magnitude, color, and galaxy type. This represents a factor of ~ 2 improvement at 26 AB mag compared to COSMOS2020. The catalog is approximately 80&amp;percnt; complete at log(M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;sext;&lt;/sub&gt;/M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;) ~ 9 at z ~ 10 and at log(M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;sext;&lt;/sub&gt;/M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;) ~ 7 at z ~ 0.2, representing a gain of 1 dex compared to COSMOS2020. COSMOS2025 represents the definitive COSMOS-Web catalog. It is provided with complete documentation, together with redshift probability distributions, and it is ready for scientific exploitation today.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-06-03T18:00:00Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-06-03T18:00:00Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2506.03243v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2506.03243v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Marko Shuntov</author><pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03243v1</guid></item><item><title>AGNBoost: A Machine Learning Approach to AGN Identification with JWST/NIRCam+MIRI Colors and Photometry</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03130v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Kurt Hamblin, Allison Kirkpatrick, Bren E. Backhaus, Gregory Troiani, Fabio Pacucci, Jonathan R. Trump, Alexander de la Vega, L. Y. Aaron Yung, Jeyhan S. Kartaltepe, Dale D. Kocevski, Anton M. Koekemoer, Erini Lambrides, Casey Papovich, Kaila Ronayne, Guang Yang, Pablo Arrabal Haro, Micaela B. Bagley, Mark Dickinson, Steven L. Finkelstein, Nor Pirzkal &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We present AGNBoost, a machine learning framework utilizing XGBoostLSS to identify AGN and estimate redshifts from JWST NIRCam and MIRI photometry. AGNBoost constructs 121 input features from 7 NIRCam and 4 MIRI bands-including magnitudes, colors, and squared color terms-to simultaneously predict the fraction of mid-IR 3-30 &amp;mu;m emission attributable to an AGN power law (frac_AGN) and photometric redshift. Each model is trained on a sample of 10^6 simulated galaxies from CIGALE providing ground truth values of both frac_AGN and redshift. Models are tested against both mock CIGALE galaxies set aside for testing and 698 observations from the JWST MIRI EGS Galaxy and AGN (MEGA) survey. On mock galaxies, AGNBoost achieves 15&amp;percnt; outlier fractions of 0.19&amp;percnt; (frac_AGN) and 0.63&amp;percnt; (redshift), with a root mean square error (&amp;sigma;_RMSE) of 0.027 for frac_AGN and a normalized mean absolute deviation (&amp;sigma;_NMAD) of 0.011 for redshift. On MEGA galaxies with spectroscopic redshifts, AGNBoost achieves &amp;sigma;_NMAD = 0.074 and 17.05&amp;percnt; outliers, with most outliers at z&lt;sub&gt;spec&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;gt; 2. AGNBoost frac_AGN estimates broadly agree with CIGALE fitting (&amp;sigma;_RMSE = 0.183, 20.41&amp;percnt; outliers), and AGNBoost finds a similar number of AGNs as CIGALE SED fitting. The flexible framework of AGNBoost allows straightforward incorporation of additional photometric bands and derived qualities, and simple re-training for other variables of interest. AGNBoost's computational efficiency makes it well-suited for wide-sky surveys requiring rapid AGN identification and redshift estimation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-06-03T17:57:13Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-06-03T17:57:13Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2506.03130v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2506.03130v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Kurt Hamblin</author><pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 17:57:13 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03130v1</guid></item><item><title>EIGER VII. The evolving relationship between galaxies and the intergalactic medium in the final stages of reionization</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03121v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Daichi Kashino, Simon J. Lilly, Jorryt Matthee, Ruari Mackenzie, Anna-Christina Eilers, Rongmon Bordoloi, Robert A. Simcoe, Rohan P. Naidu, Minghao Yue, Bin Liu &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We present a comprehensive analysis of the relationship between galaxies and the intergalactic medium (IGM) during the late stages of cosmic reionization, based on the complete JWST EIGER dataset. Using deep NIRCam 3.5 &amp;mu; m slitless spectroscopy, we construct a sample of 948 [\OIII]&amp;lambda;5008-emitting galaxies with -21.4≲ M_UV≲ -17.2 spanning 5.33&amp;lt;z&amp;lt;6.97 along six quasar sightlines. We correlate these galaxies with \Lya and \Lyb transmission measured from high-resolution quasar spectra across multiple redshift intervals. We find clear redshift evolution in the correlation between galaxy density and transmission: it is suppressed in overdense regions at z&amp;lt;5.50, while enhanced at 5.70&amp;lt;z&amp;lt;6.15. The intermediate range exhibits a transitional behavior. Cross-correlation measurements further reveal excess absorption within ~ 8 cMpc of galaxies at low redshifts, and enhanced transmission at intermediate scales (~5&amp;ndash;20 cMpc) at z&amp;gt;5.70. Statistical tests using mock catalogs with realistic galaxy clustering but no correlation with the transmission field confirm that the observed correlations are unlikely to arise by chance. The evolving signals can be explained by stronger absorption in overdense regions, combined with the competing influences of local radiation fields and the rising background radiation. While local radiation dominates ionization of the surrounding IGM at earlier times, the background becomes increasingly important, eventually surpassing the impact of nearby galaxies. These results support an inside-out progression of reionization, with ionized regions originating around clustered, star-forming galaxies and gradually extending into underdense regions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-06-03T17:53:08Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-06-03T17:53:08Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; Submitted to ApJ &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2506.03121v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2506.03121v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Daichi Kashino</author><pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 17:53:08 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03121v1</guid></item><item><title>MINDS: The very low-mass star and brown dwarf sample. Detections and trends in the inner disk gas</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02748v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; A. M. Arabhavi, I. Kamp, Th. Henning, E. F. van Dishoeck, H. Jang, L. B. F. M. Waters, V. Christiaens, D. Gasman, I. Pascucci, G. Perotti, S. L. Grant, M. Güdel, P. -O. Lagage, D. Barrado, A. Caratti o Garatti, F. Lahuis, T. Kaeufer, J. Kanwar, M. Morales-Calderón, K. Schwarz, A. D. Sellek, B. Tabone, M. Temmink, M. Vlasblom, P. Patapis &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Planet-forming disks around brown dwarfs and very low-mass stars (VLMS) are on average less massive and are expected to undergo faster radial solid transport than their higher mass counterparts. Spitzer had detected C_2H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and HCN around these objects. With better sensitivity and spectral resolving power, JWST recently revealed incredibly carbon-rich spectra from such disks. A study of a larger sample of objects is necessary to understand how common such carbon-rich inner disk regions are and to put constraints on their evolution. We present and analyze MIRI observations of 10 disks around VLMS from the MIRI GTO program. This sample is diverse, with the central object ranging in mass from 0.02 to 0.14 M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;. They are located in three star-forming regions and a moving group (1-10 Myr). We identify molecular emission in all sources and report detection rates. We compare the molecular flux ratios between different species and to dust emission strengths. We also compare the flux ratios with the stellar and disk properties. The spectra of these VLMS disks are extremely molecular rich, and we detect the 10 &amp;mu;m silicate dust emission feature in 70% of the sample. We detect C_2H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and HCN in all of the sources and find larger hydrocarbons such as C_4H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and C_6H_6 in nearly all sources. Among O-bearing molecules, we find firm detections of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O, and CO in 90%, 50%, and 20% of the sample, respectively. We find that the detection rates of organic molecules correlate with other organic molecules and anti-correlate with inorganic molecules. Hydrocarbon-rich sources show a weaker 10&amp;mu;m dust strength as well as lower disk dust mass than the oxygen-rich sources. We find potential evidence for C/O enhancement with disk age. The observed trends are consistent with models that suggest rapid inward solid material transport and grain growth.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-06-03T11:11:27Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-06-03T11:11:27Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 20 pages, 18 figures, Accepted for publication in Astronomy &amp;   Astrophysics &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2506.02748v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2506.02748v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>A. M. Arabhavi</author><pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 11:11:27 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02748v1</guid></item><item><title>The Stellar Populations and Rest-Frame Colors of Star-Forming Galaxies at z ≈ 8: Exploring the Impact of Filter Choice and Star Formation History Assumption with JADES</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02099v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Jakob M. Helton, Stacey Alberts, George H. Rieke, Kevin N. Hainline, Zhiyuan Ji, Marcia J. Rieke, Benjamin D. Johnson, Brant Robertson, Sandro Tacchella, Lily Whitler, William M. Baker, Rachana Bhatawdekar, Kristan Boyett, Andrew J. Bunker, Phillip A. Cargile, Stefano Carniani, Stephane Charlot, Jacopo Chevallard, Emma Curtis-Lake, Eiichi Egami, Daniel J. Eisenstein, Ryan Hausen, Jianwei Lyu, Roberto Maiolino, Erica Nelson, Pablo G. Pérez-González, Pierluigi Rinaldi, Meredith Stone, Fengwu Sun, Christina C. Williams, Christopher N. A. Willmer, Chris Willott, Joris Witstok &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Our understanding of the physical properties of star-forming galaxies during the Epoch of Reionization (EoR, at z &amp;gt; 6) suffers from degeneracies among the apparent properties of the stars, the nebular gas, and the dust. These degeneracies are most prominent with photometry, which has insufficient (1) spectral resolution and (2) rest-frame spectral coverage. We explore ways to break these degeneracies with a sample of N = 22 high-redshift star-forming galaxies at 7 &amp;lt; z&lt;sub&gt;phot&lt;/sub&gt; ≤ 9, using some of the deepest existing imaging from JWST/NIRCam and JWST/MIRI with JADES. Key to this study is the imaging from JWST/MIRI at 7.7 &amp;mu;m, which provides coverage of the rest-frame I-band at the observed redshifts. We infer stellar population properties and rest-frame colors using a variety of filter sets and star formation history assumptions to explore the impact of these choices. Evaluating these quantities both with and without the 7.7 &amp;mu;m data point shows that dense spectral coverage with JWST/NIRCam (eight or more filters, including at least one medium-band) can compensate for lacking the rest-frame I-band coverage for the vast majority (≈ 80&amp;percnt;) of our sample. Furthermore, these galaxy properties are most consistently determined by assuming the delayed-tau star formation history, which provides the smallest offsets and scatters around these offsets when including JWST/MIRI. Within extragalactic surveys like JADES and CEERS, our findings suggest that robust characterization of the stellar population properties and rest-frame colors for high-redshift star-forming galaxies is possible with JWST/NIRCam alone at z ≈ 8.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-06-02T17:59:59Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-06-02T17:59:59Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; Submitted to ApJ; main text has 22 pages, 8 figures (including 2   figure sets) and 4 tables; appendix has 2 pages, 2 figures (including 2   figure sets), and 5 tables &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2506.02099v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2506.02099v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Jakob M. Helton</author><pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 17:59:59 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02099v1</guid></item><item><title>Diversity of Cold Worlds: A Near Complete Spectral Energy Distribution for 2MASS J04151954-0935066 using JWST</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24591v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Sherelyn Alejandro Merchan, Jacqueline K. Faherty, Genaro Suárez, Kelle L. Cruz, Adam J. Burgasser, Jonathan Gagné, Callie E. Hood, Eileen C. Gonzales, Daniella C. Bardalez Gagliuffi, Jolie L'Heureux, Johanna M. Vos, Adam C. Schneider, Aaron M. Meisner, Caroline Morley, J. Davy Kirkpatrick, Federico Marocco, Rocio Kiman, Charles A. Beichman, Ben Burningham, Dan Caselden, Peter R. Eisenhardt, Christopher R. Gelino, Ehsan Gharib-Nezhad, Marc J. Kuchner, Brianna Lacy, Austin Rothermich, Melanie J. Rowland, Niall Whiteford &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We present the a near complete spectral energy distribution (SED) for an extrasolar world: the T8 brown dwarf 2MASS~J04151954-0935066. Spanning from optical to mid-infrared (0.7&amp;ndash;20.4 micron) wavelengths, the SED for this substellar atmosphere is constructed from new JWST NIRSpec G395H (R~2700) and Magellan FIRE echelle (R~8000) near-infrared spectra, along with MIRI mid-infrared photometry complemented by spectra from Keck I, IRTF, Magellan, AKARI, Spitzer and photometry from various surveys and missions. The NIRSpec G395H spectrum reveals strong molecular absorptions from NH_3, CH_4, H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;S, CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O at approximately 3.00, 3.35, 3.95, 4.25, and 5.00 micron respectively, along with the presence of a CO absorption feature detected mainly at ~ 4.6 micron. We detect no absorption of near-infrared K I doublets in the R~8000 FIRE spectra. In the mid-infrared IRS spectrum, we tentatively identify a new CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; feature at 14&amp;ndash;16 micron. The comprehensive SED allows us to empirically constrain bolometric luminosity, effective temperature, mass and radius. Additionally, we demonstrate that the NIRSpec G395H resolution, the highest allowable by JWST, enables a precise radial velocity measurement of 47.1±1.8 km s&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; for the object, in agreement with previous measurements.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-30T13:40:13Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-30T13:40:13Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 13 pages, 6 figures, 3 tables. Accepted for publication in ApJ &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.24591v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.24591v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Sherelyn Alejandro Merchan</author><pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 13:40:13 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24591v1</guid></item><item><title>The Impact of Galaxy Overdensities and Ionized Bubbles on Lyα Emission at z~7.0-8.5</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24080v2</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Zuyi Chen, Daniel P. Stark, Charlotte A. Mason, Mengtao Tang, Lily Whitler, Ting-Yi Lu, Michael W. Topping &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Ly&amp;alpha; spectroscopy with JWST is opening a new window on the sizes of ionized bubbles through the reionization epoch. Theoretical expectations suggest typical bubble radii should be 0.6-1.5 pMpc at z≃ 7, assuming neutral hydrogen fractions of the intergalactic medium in the range x_HI=0.5-0.7. Here we investigate this picture using JWST to characterize the environment and Ly&amp;alpha; emission of 292 galaxies at 7.0&amp;lt;z&amp;lt;8.5 across 5 fields spanning a comoving volume of 1.3×10^6 Mpc^3. If the reionization predictions are correct, we should see overdensities and strong Ly&amp;alpha; emission clustered in redshift windows of dz=0.04-0.08 and angular scales of 5-11 arcmin. We detect Ly&amp;alpha; emission in 36 out of 292 galaxies, including nine new Ly&amp;alpha; detections, two of which (in the UDS field) show extremely large equivalent widths (EW = 200_-78^+50 A and 284_-75^+56 A). We identify 13 significant (4-11×) galaxy overdensities using redshifts from NIRCam grism and NIRSpec. Strong Ly&amp;alpha; emitters are almost uniformly found in the overdensities, with nearly all located between the center and back of the structures. The overdensities that host the strong Ly&amp;alpha; emitters span typical line-of-sight distances (dz~ 0.14) and angular scales (~ 8 arcmin) that are comparable to the predicted bubble sizes at z≃ 7. We discuss evidence that the EGS is mostly ionized along a 24 pMpc sightline at z≃ 7.0-7.6, based on the presence of 3 overdense structures and 10 Ly&amp;alpha; emitters in this volume, and find such a large ionized region would pose tension with standard reionization models.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-29T23:55:44Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-06-03T01:23:42Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; main text 23 pages, 12 figures, submitted to ApJ &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.24080v2"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.24080v2 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Zuyi Chen</author><pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 23:55:44 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24080v2</guid></item><item><title>Dust Budget Crisis in Little Red Dots</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22600v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Kejian Chen, Zhengrong Li, Kohei Inayoshi, Luis C. Ho &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Little red dots (LRDs), a population of active galactic nuclei (AGNs) recently identified by JWST, are characterized by their compact morphology and red optical continuum emission, which is often interpreted as evidence for significant dust extinction of A_V ≳ 3 mag. However, the dust-reddened AGN scenario is increasingly challenged by their faint near-to-far infrared emission and a potential "dust budget crisis" in cases when the host galaxy is either undetectably low-mass or absent. In this study, we re-evaluate the dust extinction level in LRDs by modeling the UV-to-infrared spectra for various extinction laws and a broad range of dusty distribution parameters. Comparing the predicted infrared fluxes with observational data from the JWST MIRI, Herschel, and ALMA, our analysis finds that the visual extinction is tightly constrained to A_V ≲ 1.0 mag for A2744-45924 and A_V ≲ 1.5 mag for RUBIES-BLAGN-1 under the SMC extinction laws, with slightly weaker constraints for those with gray extinction in the UV range. The revised A_V values yield a radiative efficiencies of 10&amp;percnt; for the LRD population, easing the tension with the Soltan argument for the bulk AGN population at lower redshifts. Moreover, this moderate extinction (or dust-free) scenario, with reprocessed emission spectra testable by future far-infrared observatories, provides a paradigm shift in understanding their natures, environments, and evolutionary pathways of massive black holes in the early universe.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-28T17:14:52Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-28T17:14:52Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 12 pages, 5 figures &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.22600v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.22600v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Kejian Chen</author><pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 17:14:52 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22600v1</guid></item><item><title>Solar C/O ratio in planet-forming gas at 1 au in a highly irradiated disk</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22314v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Ilane Schroetter, Olivier Berné, Emeric Bron, Felipe Alarcon, Paul Amiot, Edwin A. Bergin, Christiaan Boersma, Jan Cami, Gavin A. L. Coleman, Emmanuel Dartois, Asuncion Fuente, Javier R. Goicoechea, Emilie Habart, Thomas J. Haworth, Christine Joblin, Franck Le Petit, Takashi Onaka, Els Peeters, Markus Rölling, Alexander G. G. M. Tielens, Marion Zannese &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The chemical composition of exoplanets is thought to be influenced by the composition of the disks in which they form. JWST observations have unveiled a variety of species in numerous nearby disks, showing significant variations in the C/O abundance ratio. However, little is known about the composition and C/O ratio of disks around young stars in clusters exposed to strong ultraviolet (UV) radiation from nearby massive stars, which are representative of the environments where most planetary systems form, including ours. We present JWST spectroscopy of d203-504, a young 0.7 M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt; star in the Orion Nebula with a 30 au disk irradiated by nearby massive stars. These observations reveal spectroscopic signatures of CO, H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O, CH_3^+, and PAHs. Water and CO are detected in absorption in the inner disk (r≲ 1 au), where the estimated gas-phase C/O ratio is 0.48, consistent with the Solar value and that of the Orion Nebula. In contrast, \chCH3+ and PAHs are found in the extended surface layers of the disk. These results suggest that gas in the inner disk is chemically shielded from UV radiation while the surface layers of the disk experience UV-induced chemistry, potentially depleting their carbon content.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-28T12:58:00Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-28T12:58:00Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 20 pages, 14 figures, submitted to Nature Astronomy &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.22314v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.22314v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Ilane Schroetter</author><pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 12:58:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22314v1</guid></item><item><title>Ito calculus meets the Hubble tension: Effects of small-scale electron density fluctuations on the CMB anisotropies</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22242v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Jens Chluba, Geoffrey Vasil, Richard Battye &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In this work, we develop a novel formalism to include the effect of electron density fluctuations at ultra small scales (well below the sound horizon at last scattering) on the observed anisotropies of the Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB). We treat the electron field as an independent stochastic variable and obtain the required ensemble-averaged photon Boltzmann equations using Ito calculus. Beyond changes to the average recombination history (which can be incorporated in the standard approach) our work identifies two new effects caused by the clumpiness of the medium. The first is a correction to the Thomson visibility function caused by correlations of the electron fluctuations along the line of sight, leading to an additional broadening of the visibility towards higher redshifts which causes extra damping and smearing of the CMB anisotropies. The second effect is a reduction of the effective scattering rate in the (pre-)recombination era that affects the photon transfer functions in a non-trivial manner. These new effects are subdominant in LCDM but can be significant in cosmologies with an early onset of structure formation (e.g., due to generation of enhanced small-scale power) as suggested by a number of indicators (e.g., the abundance of high redshift galaxies observed by JWST). We discuss the relevance of these new effects to the Hubble tension, finding that corrections which cannot be captured by simple modifications to the average recombination history arise. This highlights how important an understanding of the recombination process is in cosmological inference, and that a coordinated simulation and analysis campaign is required as part of the search for the origin of the various tensions in cosmology.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-28T11:22:45Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-28T11:22:45Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 22 pages, 18 figures, submitted to MNRAS, comments welcome &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.22242v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.22242v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Jens Chluba</author><pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 11:22:45 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22242v1</guid></item><item><title>First IFU observations of two GRB host galaxies at cosmic noon with JWST/NIRSpec</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21643v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; B. Topçu, P. Schady, S. Wuyts, A. Inkenhaag, M. Arabsalmani, H. -W. Chen, L. Christensen, V. D'Elia, J. P. U. Fynbo, K. E. Heintz, P. Jakobsson, T. Laskar, A. Levan, G. Pugliese, A. Rossi, R. L. C. Starling, N. R. Tanvir, P. Wiseman, R. M. Yates &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Long gamma-ray bursts (GRBs) serve as powerful probes of distant galaxies. Their luminous afterglow pinpoints galaxies independent of luminosity, in contrast to most flux-limited surveys. Nevertheless, GRB-selected galaxy samples are not free from bias, instead tracing the conditions favoured by the progenitor stars. Characterising the galaxy populations traced by GRBs is therefore important both to effectively use GRBs as probes as well as to place stronger constraints on the progenitor stars capable of forming long GRBs. Spatially-resolved spectroscopic observations with integral field units (IFUs) provide valuable insights into the interstellar medium and stellar populations of GRB host galaxies. In this paper we present results of the first two GRB host galaxies observed with the JWST/NIRSpec IFU with a spatial resolution of ~ 1.6 kpc; the hosts of GRB 150403A and GRB 050820A at redshifts z ~ 2.06 and z ~ 2.61, respectively. The data reveal two complex galaxy environments made up of two or more star forming galaxies that are likely interacting given their small spatial separation (&amp;lt; 20 kpc) and line of sight velocity offsets (&amp;lt; 100 km/s). The measured gas-phase metallicity, star formation rates (SFRs), and key diagnostic line ratios for each of the detected galaxies are overall consistent with the properties of other star forming galaxies and GRB hosts at z &amp;gt; 2. However, differences in the SFR and metallicities of the interacting galaxies highlight the importance of spatially resolved observations in order to accurately characterise the galaxy properties traced by GRBs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-27T18:18:24Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-27T18:18:24Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; Accepted for publication in MNRAS; 16 pages, 8 figures &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.21643v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.21643v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>B. Topçu</author><pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 18:18:24 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21643v1</guid></item><item><title>DAWN JWST Archive: Morphology from profile fitting of over 340,000 galaxies in major fields</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21622v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Aurélien Genin, Marko Shuntov, Gabe Brammer, Natalie Allen, Kei Ito, Georgios Magdis, Jasleen Matharu, Pascal A. Oesch, Sune Toft, Francesco Valentino &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To better understand how galaxies assemble their structure and evolve over cosmic time, we present a new catalog of morphological measurements for over 340,000 sources spanning 0 &amp;lt; z &amp;lt; 12, derived from deep JWST NIRCam imaging across four major extragalactic fields (CEERS, PRIMER-UDS, PRIMER-COSMOS, GOODS) compiled in the DAWN JWST Archive (DJA). We perform two-dimensional surface brightness fitting for all galaxies in a uniform, flux-limited sample. Each galaxy is modeled with both a S\'ersic profile and a two-component (bulge and disk) decomposition, yielding consistent structural parameters - including effective radius, S\'ersic index, axis ratio, and bulge-to-total ratio (B/T). To demonstrate the scientific application of our morphology catalogs, we combined these measurements with DJA photometric redshifts, physical parameters and rest-frame colors, and investigated the relation between total, bulge and disk sizes, S\'ersic index (n_S), star formation activity, and redshift. Bulge-dominated galaxies (high n_S and B/T) predominantly occupy the quiescent region of the UVJ diagram, while disk-dominated galaxies are mostly star-forming. A significant bimodality persists, with quiescent disks and compact, bulge-dominated star-forming galaxies observed out to z &amp;gt; 3. Quiescent galaxies also show significantly higher stellar mass surface densities, nearly an order of magnitude greater at z ~ 4 than at z ~ 1. Our results confirm a strong and evolving link between morphology and star formation activity, and support a scenario in which bulge growth and quenching are closely connected. This work is a highly valuable addition to the DJA, adding a morphological dimension to this rich dataset and thus enabling a wider scientific application.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-27T18:00:04Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-27T18:00:04Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 12 pages, 9 figures; accepted for publication in A&amp;A &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.21622v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.21622v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Aurélien Genin</author><pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 18:00:04 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21622v1</guid></item><item><title>Spectral Evolution of Rotating Population III Stars</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21463v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Jake Hassan, Rosalba Perna, Matteo Cantiello, Tyler Parsotan, Davide Lazzati, Nathan Walker &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Population III (Pop III) stars, the first generation of stars formed from primordial gas, played a fundamental role in shaping the early universe through their influence on cosmic reionization, early chemical enrichment, and the formation of the first galaxies. However, to date they have eluded direct detection due to their short lifetimes and high redshifts. The launch of the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) has revolutionized observational capabilities, providing the opportunity to detect Pop~III stars via caustic lensing, where strong gravitational lensing magnifies individual stars to observable levels. This prospect makes it compelling to develop accurate models for their spectral characteristics to distinguish them from other stellar populations. Previous studies have focused on computing the spectral properties of non-rotating, zero-age main sequence (ZAMS) Pop III stars. In this work, we expand upon these efforts by incorporating the effects of stellar rotation and post-ZAMS evolution into spectral calculations. We use the JWST bands and magnitude limits to identify the optimal observing conditions, both for isolated stars, as well as for small star clusters. We find that, while rotation does not appreciably change the observability at ZAMS, the subsequent evolution can significantly brighten the stars, making the most massive ones potentially visible with only moderate lensing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-27T17:34:40Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-27T17:34:40Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 18 pages, 6 figures &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.21463v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.21463v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Jake Hassan</author><pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 17:34:40 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21463v1</guid></item><item><title>The Properties of Little Red Dot Galaxies in the ASTRID Simulation</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20439v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Patrick LaChance, Rupert A. C. Croft, Tiziana Di Matteo, Yihao Zhou, Fabio Pacucci, Yueying Ni, Nianyi Chen, Simeon Bird &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We present simulated counterparts of the "Little Red Dot'' (LRD) galaxies observed with JWST, using the large cosmological hydrodynamic simulation, ASTRID. We create mock observations of the galaxies (5 ≤ z ≤ 8) in ASTRID, and find seventeen which fit the color and size criteria of LRDs. These LRDs are galaxies with high stellar masses (log(M_*/M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;) ≥ 9.7), and massive black holes (log(M_BH/M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;) ≥ 6.8). The host galaxies are dense, with stellar half mass radii (325 pc ≤ r_half,* ≤ 620 pc), and dust attenuation in the F444W band above 1.25. Their star formation has been recently quenched. They host relatively bright AGN that are dust-obscured and contribute significantly to the rest-frame optical red slope and have relatively low luminosity in the rest-frame ultraviolet, where the host galaxy's stars are more dominant. These LRDs are in an evolutionary phase of miniquenching that is the result of AGN feedback from their massive black holes. The LRDs in ASTRID are bright with F444W magnitudes of 23.5-25.5. The less massive and fainter galaxies in ASTRID lack the dust concentration necessary to produce the red slope of an LRD, though this could be an effect of limited resolution. Most of the highest Eddington black holes are not LRDs due to their host galaxies having typical dust levels and relatively high star formation rates accompanying their highly accreting black holes, resulting in their spectra being too flat.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-26T18:34:36Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-26T18:34:36Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 15 pages, 12 figures &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.20439v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.20439v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Patrick LaChance</author><pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 18:34:36 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20439v1</guid></item><item><title>Bursty or heavy? The surprise of bright Population III systems in the Reionization era</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20263v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Alessandra Venditti, Julian B. Munoz, Volker Bromm, Seiji Fujimoto, Steven L. Finkelstein, John Chisholm &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The nature of the first, so-called Population III (Pop III), stars has for long remained largely unconstrained. However, the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) finally opened new concrete prospects for their detection during the Epoch of Reionization (EoR), notably providing promising observational constraints on the Pop III ultra-violet luminosity function (UVLF) at z ~ 6.5. These preliminary data hint towards an unexpected population of UV-bright Pop III sources, which challenges the prevailing view that Pop III star formation is confined to molecular-cooling mini-halos. Here we show that there are two families of models that can explain these surprising observations, either by allowing for late-time Pop III formation within massive, atomic-cooling halos (with halo masses up to M_up^III ≳ 10^10.5 ~M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;) or by invoking a highly bursty Pop III star-formation activity (with a stochasticity parameter &amp;sigma;_UV^III ≳ 1.5). In these scenarios Pop III systems would have to be either heavier or burstier than usually assumed, underscoring the need to reconsider common assumptions about Pop III star-formation sites, and the potential implications of JWST candidates for current and future observations.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-26T17:42:17Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-26T17:42:17Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 14 pages, 5 figures. Submitted to APJL &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.20263v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.20263v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Alessandra Venditti</author><pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 17:42:17 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20263v1</guid></item><item><title>Origins of Supermassive Black Holes in Galactic Centers</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19039v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Ke-Jung Chen &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Direct imaging of black hole shadow halos has firmly confirmed the existence of supermassive black holes (SMBHs), with millions of solar masses, residing at the centers of the Milky Way and M87 galaxies. These groundbreaking discoveries represent a monumental success of Einstein's theory of general relativity and have revealed the hidden "monsters" lurking at the centers of galaxies. Moreover, observations of active galactic nuclei (AGNs) indicate that SMBHs with billions of solar masses were already in place within the first billion years after the Big Bang. However, the origins of these SMBHs, as well as their co-evolution with host galaxies, remain poorly understood. This review focuses on the origin of SMBHs, particularly on the formation of their seed black holes. We also highlight several outstanding challenges in modeling seed formation and discuss possible observational signatures. These signatures may be testable with current and future facilities, including the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) and the upcoming gravitational wave observatory, the Laser Interferometer Space Antenna (LISA).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-25T08:39:10Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-25T08:39:10Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 11 pages, 3 figures, Review for MPLA &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.19039v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.19039v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Ke-Jung Chen</author><pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 08:39:10 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19039v1</guid></item><item><title>An upper limit of 10^6 M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt; in dust from ALMA observations in 60 Little Red Dots</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18873v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Caitlin M. Casey, Hollis B. Akins, Steven L. Finkelstein, Maximilien Franco, Seiji Fujimoto, Daizhong Liu, Arianna S. Long, Georgios Magdis, Sinclaire M. Manning, Jed McKinney, Marko Shuntov, Takumi S. Tanaka &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
By virtue of their red color, the dust in little red dots (LRDs) has been thought to be of appreciable influence, whether that dust is distributed in a torus around a compact active galactic nucleus (AGN) or diffuse in the interstellar medium (ISM) of nascent galaxies. In Casey et al. (2024) we predicted that, based on the compact sizes of LRDs (unresolved in JWST NIRCam imaging), detection of an appreciable dust mass would be unlikely. Here we present follow-up ALMA 1.3mm continuum observations of a sample of 60 LRDs drawn from Akins et al. (2024). None of the 60 LRDs are detected in imaging that reaches an average depth of &amp;sigma;_rms=22 &amp;mu; Jy. A stack of the 60 LRDs also results in a non-detection, with an inverse-variance weighted flux density measurement of S_1.3mm=2.1±2.9 &amp;mu; Jy. This observed limit translates to a 3&amp;sigma; upper limit of 10^6 M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt; in LRDs' dust mass, and ≲10^11 L&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt; in total dust luminosity; both are a factor of 10× deeper than previous submm stack limits for LRDs. These results are consistent with either the interpretation that LRDs are reddened due to compact but modest dust reservoirs (with A_V~2-4) or, alternatively, that instead of being reddened by dust, they have extreme Balmer breaks generated by dense gas (&amp;gt;10^9 cm^-3) enshrouding a central black hole.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-24T21:27:46Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-24T21:27:46Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 7 pages, 3 figures, submitted to AAS journals &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.18873v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.18873v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Caitlin M. Casey</author><pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2025 21:27:46 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18873v1</guid></item><item><title>Enhanced Merger Fractions in a Reionization-Era Protocluster</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18262v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Lorraine C. Marcelin, Jaclyn B. Champagne, Feige Wang, Xiaohui Fan, Maria Pudoka, Wei Leong Tee, Yongda Zhu &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Mergers play a critical role in galaxy evolution, but their relationship to their surrounding environments is unexplored at high redshift. We investigate the galaxy merger rate among 124 [OIII] emitters at 5.3&amp;lt;z&amp;lt;6.9 as a function of local galaxy density. Identified in the ASPIRE JWST/NIRCam grism survey, we investigate three density regimes: a z=6.6 quasar-centered protocluster, two overdensities at z=5.4 and z=6.2, and field galaxies. We evaluate merger candidates through close pair and morphological criteria in NIRCam imaging, finding that the z=6.6 protocluster contains the highest fraction of galaxies meeting either criterion. We observe a &amp;gt;3&amp;sigma; enhancement of the merger fraction amongst all three overdense structures compared to the field. Eleven galaxies are classified as "active mergers" satisfying both merger criteria, all of which occur within the overdensity samples. We conclude that environment affects the merger rates of galaxies at z&amp;gt;6, leading to increased specific star formation at the 4&amp;sigma; level.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-23T18:00:33Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-23T18:00:33Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; submitted to RNAAS &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.18262v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.18262v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Lorraine C. Marcelin</author><pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 18:00:33 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18262v1</guid></item><item><title>Galaxy-scale lens search in the PEARLS NEP TDF and CEERS JWST fields</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17318v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Giovanni Ferrami, Nathan J. Adams, Lewi Westcott, Thomas Harvey, Rolf A. Jansen, Jose M. Diego, Vince Estrada-Carpente, Rogier A. Windhorst, Christopher J. Conselice, Anton M. Koekemoer, Jordan C. J. D'Silva, Christopher Willmer, J. Stuart B. Wyithe, Michael J. Rutkowski, Seth H. Cohen, Brenda L. Frye, Norman A. Grogin &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We present four galaxy scale lenses discovered in two JWST blank-fields: the ~ 54 arcmin&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; of the PEARLS North-Ecliptic-Pole Time-Domain Field (NEP TDF) and in the ~ 90 arcmin&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; of CEERS. We perform the search by visual inspection of NIRCam photometric data, obtaining an initial list of 16 lens candidates. We down-select this list to 4 high-confidence lens candidates, based on lens modelling of the image configuration and photometric redshift measurements for both the source and the deflector. We compare our results to samples of lenses obtained in ground-based and space-based lens searches and theoretical expectations. We expect that JWST observations of field galaxies will yield approximately 1 galaxy scale lens every three to five NIRCam pointings of comparable depth to these observations (~ 9 arcmin&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; each). This shows that JWST, compared to other lens searches, can yield an extremely high number of secure lenses per unit area, with redshift and size distributions complementary to lens samples obtained from ground-based and wide-area surveys. We estimate that a single JWST pure-parallel survey of comparable depth could yield ~ 70 galaxy scale lenses, with a third of them having z_lens&amp;gt;1 and z_source&amp;gt;3.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-22T22:13:58Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-22T22:13:58Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 11 pages, 5 figures. Submitted to MNRAS. arXiv admin note: text   overlap with arXiv:2504.03571 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.17318v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.17318v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Giovanni Ferrami</author><pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 22:13:58 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17318v1</guid></item><item><title>Oort Cloud Formation and Evolution in Star Clusters</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17246v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Justine C. Obidowski, Jeremy J. Webb, Simon Portegies Zwart, Maxwell X. Cai &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It is unknown if an Oort cloud reaches its maximum mass within its star's birth cluster or millions of years later. Complicating the Oort cloud evolution process is the fact that comets can be stripped from orbit due to perturbations from passing stars. We explore how a star's cluster escape time (t_ esc) and the time its Oort cloud reaches maximum mass (t_ max) affect the Oort cloud's ability to survive via N-body simulations. In a 14 M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;/pc^3 cluster, we identify 50 stars of 1 M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt; with a range of t_ esc to host Oort clouds, each with 1000 comets at t_ max. For each host, we consider Oort clouds that reach maximum mass 0, 50, and 250 Myr after the cluster's formation. Each Oort cloud's evolution is simulated in the cluster from t_ max to t_ esc. Only a fraction of comets tend to remain in orbit, with this amount depending on t_ max and t_ esc. We observe that 12%, 22%, and 32% of Oort clouds with a t_ max of 0, 50 and 250 Myr retain &amp;gt;50% of their comets at t_ esc, respectively. We find that the fraction of comets stripped has the relationship, f=mlog_10(\fract_ esc-t_ max Myr) where m = 0.32±0.04, indicating that the longer the Oort cloud remains in the cluster, the more comets are stripped, with this fraction increasing logarithmically at approximately the same rate for each t_ max.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-22T19:48:37Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-22T19:48:37Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 14 pages, 7 figures, 1 table, accepted for publication in The   Astrophysical Journal &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.17246v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.17246v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Justine C. Obidowski</author><pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 19:48:37 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17246v1</guid></item><item><title>The Lyman-α emitter bispectrum as a probe of reionization morphology</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17188v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Soumak Maitra, Girish Kulkarni, Shikhar Asthana, James S. Bolton, Martin G. Haehnelt, Laura Keating &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Ly&amp;alpha; emitters (LAEs) have now been discovered out to redshift z=13, and are valuable probes of the reionization history at redshifts beyond the reach of other currently available tracers. Most inferences of the neutral hydrogen fraction from LAE observations rely on one-point and two-point statistics like the luminosity function and the power spectrum. We present here an analysis of the bispectrum of high-redshift LAEs and demonstrate its sensitivity to the Epoch of Reionization. We use the Sherwood-Relics suite of cosmological hydrodynamical simulations post-processed with the GPU-based radiative transfer code ATON-HE to generate realistic LAE mock catalogues for a wide range of reionization models, varying the ionization history and the source populations, including contributions of AGN to hydrogen reionization. We demonstrate that the bispectrum provides greater sensitivity than the power spectrum to both the timing and spatial morphology of reionization. Using reduced-&amp;chi;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; analysis we further show that the bispectrum also responds more strongly to variations in source population and AGN contribution, apparently more efficiently capturing morphological features missed by two-point statistics. The redshift evolution of the bispectrum reflects the increased clustering of ionizing sources at earlier epochs. The sensitivity of the bispectrum to peculiar velocities underscores the importance of velocity corrections in comparisons to observations. Our findings demonstrate that the LAE bispectrum is a powerful higher-order statistic for probing reionization through current and future LAE surveys using telescopes such as Subaru and JWST.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-22T18:00:09Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-22T18:00:09Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 22 pages, 7 figures, 4 tables. Submitted to MNRAS. Comments are   welcome &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.17188v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.17188v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Soumak Maitra</author><pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 18:00:09 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17188v1</guid></item><item><title>JWST observations of segregated ^12CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and ^13CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; ices in protostellar envelopes</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14769v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; N. G. C. Brunken, A. C. A. Boogert, E. F. van Dishoeck, N. J. Evans, C. A. Poteet, K. Slavicinska, L. Tychoniec, P. Nazari, L. W. Looney, H. Tyagi, M. Narang, P. Klaassen, Y. Yang, P. J. Kavanagh, S. T. Megeath, M. E. Ressler &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The evolution of interstellar ices can be studied with thermal tracers such as the vibrational modes of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; ice that show great diversity depending on their local chemical and thermal environment. In this work we present JWST observations of the 15.2 &amp;mu;m bending mode, the 4.39 &amp;mu;m stretching mode and the 2.70 &amp;mu;m combination mode of ^12CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and ^13CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; ice in the high-mass protostar IRAS 20126 and the low-mass protostar Per-emb 35. The 15.2 &amp;mu;m bending mode of both protostars shows the characteristic double peak profile that is associated with pure CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; ice and a sharp short-wavelength peak is observed at 4.38 &amp;mu;m in the ^13CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; bands of the two sources. Furthermore, a narrow short-wavelength feature is detected at 2.69 &amp;mu;m in the ^12CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; combination mode of Per-emb 35. We perform a consistent profile decomposition on all three vibrational modes and show that the profiles of all three bands can be reproduced with the same linear combination of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; ice in mixtures with mostly CH_3OH and H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O ices when the ices undergo segregation due to heating. The findings show that upon heating, CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; ice is likely segregating from mostly the water-rich ice layer and the CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-CH_3OH component becomes dominant in all three vibrational modes. Additionally, we find that the contribution of the different CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; components to the total absorption band is similar for both ^12CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and ^13CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;. This indicates that fractionation processes must not play a significant role during the different formation epochs, H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O-dominated and CO-dominated. We quantify the ^12CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and ^13CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; ice column densities and derive ^12C/^13C_ice = 90 ± 9 in IRAS 20126. Finally, we report the detection of the ^13CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; bending mode of pure CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; ice at 15.64 &amp;mu;m in both IRAS 20126 and Per-emb 35.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-20T18:00:00Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-20T18:00:00Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.14769v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.14769v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>N. G. C. Brunken</author><pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14769v1</guid></item><item><title>HDO ice detected toward an isolated low-mass protostar with JWST</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14686v3</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Katerina Slavicinska, Łukasz Tychoniec, María Gabriela Navarro, Ewine F. van Dishoeck, John J. Tobin, Martijn L. van Gelder, Yuan Chen, A. C. Adwin Boogert, W. Blake Drechsler, Henrik Beuther, Alessio Caratti o Garatti, S. Thomas Megeath, Pamela Klaassen, Leslie W. Looney, Patrick J. Kavanagh, Nashanty G. C. Brunken, Patrick Sheehan, William J. Fischer &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Water is detected in environments representing every stage of star and solar system formation, but its chemical evolution throughout these stages remains poorly constrained. Deuterium ratios offer a means of probing chemical links between water in different cosmic regions because of their sensitivity to physicochemical conditions. Here, we present the first detection of the 4.1 &amp;mu;m HDO ice feature with JWST toward a low-mass protostar, L1527 IRS, which may eventually grow to a sun-like mass. We measure an ice HDO/H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O ratio of 4.4^+3.7_-1.7×10^-3, where the reported error is dominated by uncertainties in continuum definition and ice band strengths. This fraction is similar to the gas HDO/H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O ratios measured in the warm (&amp;gt;100 K) inner cores of other low-mass protostellar envelopes and protoplanetary disks found in comparably isolated star-forming regions. Such a similarity tentatively supports the assumption that water vapor detected in these regions is not significantly altered by gas-phase reactions following ice sublimation. It also supports the hypothesis that pre- and protostellar water ice is largely inherited in a chemically unaltered state by outer protoplanetary disks. However, the fraction is a factor of ~4-10 times higher than the gas HDO/H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O ratios measured toward comets and low-mass protostars in clustered star-forming regions. This difference may be due to either gas-phase water reprocessing in protostellar envelopes and protoplanetary disks, or differences between prestellar conditions of isolated dense cores and the clustered star-forming regions that are more analogous to the environment in which our Sun formed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-20T17:59:58Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-06-03T16:07:37Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; Accepted for publication in ApJL. 10 pages, 4 figures, 1 table (+14   pages, 10 figures, 2 tables in appendix) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.14686v3"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.14686v3 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Katerina Slavicinska</author><pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 17:59:58 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14686v3</guid></item><item><title>A JWST View of the Overmassive Black Hole in NGC 4486B</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14676v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Behzad Tahmasebzadeh, Matthew A. Taylor, Monica Valluri, Haruka Yoshino, Eugene Vasiliev, Michael J. Drinkwater, Solveig Thompson, Kristen Dage, Patrick Côté, Laura Ferrarese, Tatsuya Akiba, Vivienne Baldassare, Misty C. Bentz, John P. Blakeslee, Holger Baumgardt, Youkyung Ko, Chengze Liu, Ann-Marie Madigan, Eric W. Peng, Joel Roediger, Kaixiang Wang, Tyrone E. Woods &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We present a new stellar dynamical measurement of the supermassive black hole (SMBH) in the compact elliptical galaxy NGC 4486B, based on integral field spectroscopy with JWST/NIRSpec. The two-dimensional kinematic maps reveal a resolved double nucleus and a velocity dispersion peak offset from the photometric center. Utilizing two independent methods-Schwarzschild orbit-superposition and Jeans Anisotropic Modeling-we tightly constrain the black hole mass by fitting the full line-of-sight velocity distribution. Our axisymmetric Schwarzschild models yield a best-fit black hole mass of M_BH = 3.6^+0.6_-0.6 × 10^8   M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;, slightly lower but significantly more precise than previous estimates. However, since our models do not account for the non-equilibrium nature of the double nucleus, this value may represent a lower limit. The inferred black hole mass corresponds to approximately 4-13% of the total stellar mass, providing robust evidence for an overmassive SMBH in NGC 4486B. Combined with the galaxy's location deep within the Virgo Cluster, our results support the interpretation that NGC 4486B is the tidally stripped remnant core of a formerly massive galaxy. As the JWST/NIRSpec field of view is insufficient to constrain the dark matter halo, we incorporate archival ground-based long-slit kinematics extending to 5 arcsec. While this provides some leverage on the dark matter content, the constraints remain relatively weak. We place only an upper limit on the dark matter fraction, with M_DM/M_* &amp;lt; 0.5 within 1 kpc-well beyond the effective radius. The inferred black hole mass remains unchanged with or without a dark matter halo.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-20T17:58:23Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-20T17:58:23Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 12 pages, 5 figures, 2 tables; submitted to ApJL, comments welcome! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.14676v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.14676v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Behzad Tahmasebzadeh</author><pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 17:58:23 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14676v1</guid></item><item><title>The JCMT BISTRO-3 Survey: Variation of magnetic field orientations on parsec and sub-parsec scales in the massive star-forming region G28.34+0.06</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14047v2</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Jihye Hwang, Kate Pattle, Chang Won Lee, Janik Karoly, Kee-Tae Kim, Jongsoo Kim, Junhao Liu, Keping Qiu, A-Ran Lyo, David Eden, Patrick M. Koch, Doris Arzoumanian, Ekta Sharma, Frédérick Poidevin, Doug Johnstone, Simon Coudé, Mehrnoosh Tahani, Derek Ward-Thompson, Archana Soam, Ji-hyun Kang, Thiem Hoang, Woojin Kwon, Nguyen Bich Ngoc, Takashi Onaka, Florian Kirchschlager, Motohide Tamura, Jungmi Kwon, Xindi Tang, Eun Jung Chung, Tyler L. Bourke, Eswaraiah Chakali, Tie Liu, Pierre Bastien, Ray S. Furuya, Shih-Ping Lai, Sheng-Jun Lin, Jia-Wei Wang, David Berry &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Magnetic fields play a significant role in star-forming processes on core to clump scales. We investigate magnetic field orientations and strengths in the massive star-forming clump P2 within the filamentary infrared dark cloud G28.34+0.06 using dust polarization observations made using SCUBA-2/POL-2 on the James Clerk Maxwell Telescope as part of the B-field In STar-forming Region Observations (BISTRO) survey. We compare the magnetic field orientations at the clump scale of ~2 parsecs from these JCMT observations with those at the core scale of ~0.2 parsecs from archival ALMA data, finding that the magnetic field orientations on these two different scales are perpendicular to one another. We estimate the distribution of magnetic field strengths, which range from 50 to 430 &amp;mu;G over the clump. The region forming the core shows the highest magnetic field strength. We also obtain the distribution of mass-to-flux ratios across the clump. In the region surrounding the core, the mass-to-flux ratio is larger than 1, which indicates the magnetic field strength is insufficient to support the region against gravitational collapse. Therefore, the change in the magnetic field orientation from clump to core scales may be the result of gravitational collapse, with the field being pulled inward along with the flow of material under gravity.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-20T07:44:38Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-23T22:13:17Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.14047v2"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.14047v2 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Jihye Hwang</author><pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 07:44:38 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14047v2</guid></item><item><title>Gamma Analytical Modeling Evolution (GAME) I: The physical implications of deriving the stellar mass functions from z=0 to z=8</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13301v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Antonios Katsianis, Qingshan Wang, Xiaohu Yang, Xian Zhong Zheng, Pedro Cataldi, Nicola Napolitano, Weishan Zhu, Nicolas Tejos, Weiguang Cui, Cheng Li, Weipeng Lin, Long-long Feng, Junde Li, Ying Tang, Yuchang Li, Hangxin Pu &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The \Gamma growth model is an effective parameterization employed across various scientific disciplines and scales to depict growth. It has been demonstrated that the cosmic star formation rate density (CSFRD) can also be described broadly by this pattern, i.e. \fracdM(T) dT = M_z,0  × \frac&amp;beta;^&amp;alpha; \Gamma(&amp;alpha;)   T^&amp;alpha;-1 e^-&amp;beta;   T  M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt; Gyr^-1, where M_z,0 is the stellar mass at z = 0, &amp;alpha; = 3.0, &amp;beta; = 0.5 Gyr^-1 and T describes time. We use the identical \Gamma growth pattern given by the CSFRD to extend the present day (z = 0) stellar mass bins M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;ast;&lt;/sub&gt;(T) of the Galaxy Stellar Mass Function (GSMF) and investigate if we are able to reproduce observations for the high redshift GSMFs. Surprisingly, our scheme describes successfully the evolution of the GSMF over 13.5 Gyrs, especially for objects with intermediate and low masses. We observe some deviations that manifest  solely at very high redshifts (z &amp;gt; 1.5, i.e. more than 9.5 Gyr ago) and  specifically for very small and exceedingly massive objects. We discuss the possible solutions (e.g. impacts of mergers) for these offsets. Our formalism suggests that the evolution of the GSMF is set by simple (few parameters) and physically motivated arguments. The parameters &amp;beta; and &amp;alpha; are theoretically consistent within a multi-scale context and are determined from the dynamical time scale (&amp;beta;) and the radial distribution of the accreting matter (&amp;alpha;). We demonstrate that both our formalism and state-of-the-art simulations are consistent with recent GSMFs derived from JWST data at high redshifts.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-19T16:20:42Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-19T16:20:42Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 29 pages, 15 Figures, Published to MNRAS &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.13301v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.13301v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Antonios Katsianis</author><pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 16:20:42 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13301v1</guid></item><item><title>The Dichotomy in the Nuclear and Host Galaxy Properties of High-redshift Quasars</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12867v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Ruancun Li, Luis C. Ho, Chang-Hao Chen &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The early growth of high-redshift quasars and their host galaxies raises critical questions about their cosmic evolution. We exploit the angular resolution and sensitivity of NIRCam to investigate the host galaxies of 31 quasars at 4≲ z≲7 drawn from multiple JWST surveys. Using a new multi-band forward-modeling code (scGalfitS) that incorporates physically motivated priors, we securely detect and quantify the host emission in 30 objects, while simultaneously characterizing the nuclear spectral energy distribution. The host galaxies of high-redshift quasars are ~ 0.3~dex more compact than star-forming galaxies of comparable mass. A striking dichotomy emerges: luminous "blue'' quasars (L_5100≳10^45 erg s&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) reside in bulge-dominated galaxies (n ≈ 5) and exhibit a narrow range of ultraviolet nuclear slopes (median &amp;beta;_UV ≈ -1.4), while fainter "red'' quasars inhabit disk-like hosts (n≈ 1) and display a broad range of slopes (&amp;beta;_UV≈-2 to 4). These two populations differ markedly in their black hole-to-stellar mass ratios, with high-luminosity quasars showing M_BH/M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;ast;&lt;/sub&gt; = 1.2&amp;percnt; compared to 4.7&amp;percnt; for lower luminosity sources, placing them collectively ~0.6~dex above the local M_BH-M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;ast;&lt;/sub&gt; relation. This offset likely reflects rapid black hole growth in early gas-rich environments, where feedback from the active galactic nucleus becomes effective only after substantial gas depletion. Our findings suggest that the observed dichotomy, whether due to intrinsic spectral differences or dust extinction, fundamentally shapes the coevolution of supermassive black holes and their host galaxies in the early Universe.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-19T08:51:37Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-19T08:51:37Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 38 pages, 20 figures, submitted to ApJ. Comments greatly appreciated   and warmly welcomed! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.12867v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.12867v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Ruancun Li</author><pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 08:51:37 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12867v1</guid></item><item><title>Low-Metallicity Star Formation Survey in Sh2-284 (LZ-STAR). II. The inital mass function</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12802v1</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; M. Andersen, A. Brizawasi, Y. Cheng, J. C. Tan, R. Fedriani, J. J. Armstrong, M. Robberto &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To fully understand the star formation process, we are compelled to study it in a variety of environments. Of particular interest are how star formation and the resulting initial mass function (IMF) vary as a function of metallicity. We have observed an embedded young cluster in Sh2-284 (hereafter S284), the HII region associated with the open cluster Dolidze 25 using JWST/NIRCam with the aim to study star formation in a metal-poor, i.e., about 1/3 of solar, environment. In particular, we aim to measure the peak of the IMF. Using JWST NIRCam photometry, we identified the embedded cluster S284-EC1 and resolved its low-mass content. By comparison with pre-main sequence evolutionary tracks we determine the mass and extinction for the individual cluster members. Extinction limited samples are created based on the distribution of extinction and the completeness of the data. For the region with a completeness of 50% or higher, we have fitted a log-normal distribution to the IMF. Adopting a fiducial age of 1 Myr of the members, the peak of the IMF is found to be at mc = 0.16+-0.02M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;, which is significantly smaller than the peak mass measured in local young clusters, such as mc = 0.26+0.11-0.07 M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt; in the Orion Nebula Cluster (Gennaro &amp; Robberto 2020), or the local Galactic disk value of mc = 0.25 M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt; (Chabrier 2005). We have found evidence for IMF variation as a function of metallicity, i.e., the peak of the IMF shifts to lower masses as one goes from solar to 1/3 solar metallicity. However, we caution that the result is sensitive to the assumed age of the stellar population, i.e., with peak mass rising if an age older than 1 Myr is adopted. This study further motivates the need for expanded samples of low-metallicity regions and their content to enable more comprehensive measures of the IMF in such environments.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-19T07:32:03Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-19T07:32:03Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; Submitted to A&amp;A, comments welcome &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.12802v1"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.12802v1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>M. Andersen</author><pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 07:32:03 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12802v1</guid></item><item><title>Carbon-rich dust injected into the interstellar medium by Galactic WC binaries survives for hundreds of years</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11616v2</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Noel D. Richardson, Micaela Henson, Emma P. Lieb, Corey Kehl, Ryan M. Lau, Peredur M. Williams, Michael F. Corcoran, J. R. Callingham, André-Nicolas Chené, Theodore R. Gull, Kenji Hamaguchi, Yinuo Han, Matthew J. Hankins, Grant M. Hill, Jennifer L. Hoffman, Jonathan Mackey, Anthony F. J. Moffat, Benjamin J. S. Pope, Pragati Pradhan, Christopher M. P. Russell, Andreas A. C. Sander, Nicole St-Louis, Ian R. Stevens, Peter Tuthill, Gerd Weigelt, Ryan M. T. White &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some carbon-rich Wolf-Rayet stars (WC stars) show an infrared excess from dust emission. Dust forms in the collision of the WC wind with a companion star's wind. As this dust is carried towards the ISM at close to the WCd wind speed and the binary continues through its orbit, a spiral structure forms around the system. The shape depends on the orbital eccentricity and period, as well as stellar parameters like mass-loss rates and terminal wind speeds. Imaging of the WCd binary WR 140 with JWST/MIRI revealed 17 concentric dust shells surrounding the binary. We present new JWST imaging of four additional WCd systems (WR 48a, WR 112, WR 125, and WR 137) that were imaged in 2024. In this analysis, we show that the dust is long-lived, detected with an age of at least 130 years, but more than 300 years in some systems. Longer duration measurements are limited by sensitivity. Regular spacing of dust features confirms the periodic nature of dust formation, consistent with a connection to binary motion. We use these images to estimate the proper motion of the dust, finding the dust to propagate out to the interstellar medium with motion comparable to the wind speed of the WC stars. In addition to these results, we observe unusual structures around WR 48a, which could represent dusty clumps shaped by photoevaporation and wind ablation like young proplyd objects. These results demonstrate that WC dust is indeed long-lived and should be accounted for in galactic dust budgets.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-16T18:23:15Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-29T14:51:47Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; accepted to ApJ &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.11616v2"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.11616v2 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Noel D. Richardson</author><pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2025 18:23:15 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11616v2</guid></item><item><title>A weak Lyα halo for an extremely bright Little Red Dot. Indications of enshrouded SMBH growth</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09542v2</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Alberto Torralba, Jorryt Matthee, Gabriele Pezzulli, Tanya Urrutia, Max Gronke, Sara Mascia, Francesco D'Eugenio, Claudia Di Cesare, Anna-Christina Eilers, Jenny E. Greene, Edoardo Iani, Yuzo Ishikawa, Ruari Mackenzie, Rohan P. Naidu, Benjamín Navarrete, Gauri Kotiwale &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The abundant population of "Little Red Dots" (LRDs)-compact objects with red UV to optical colors and broad Balmer lines at high redshift-is unveiling new insights into the properties of early active galactic nuclei (AGN). Perhaps the most surprising features of this population are the presence of Balmer absorption and ubiquitous strong Balmer breaks. Recent models link these features to an active supermassive black hole (SMBH) cocooned in very dense gas (N_H~10^24 cm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;). We present a stringent test of such models using VLT/MUSE observations of A2744-45924, the most luminous LRD known to date (L_H&amp;alpha;≈10^44~erg s&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;), located behind the Abell-2744 lensing cluster at z=4.464 (&amp;mu;=1.8). We detect a moderately extended Ly&amp;alpha; nebula (h≈5.7 pkpc), spatially offset from the point-like H&amp;alpha; seen by JWST. The Ly&amp;alpha; emission is narrow (FWHM=270± 15~km s&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;), spatially offset to H&amp;alpha;, and faint (Ly&amp;alpha;=0.07H&amp;alpha;) compared to Ly&amp;alpha; nebulae typically observed around quasars of similar luminosity. We detect compact N IV]&amp;lambda;1486 emission, spatially aligned with H&amp;alpha;, and a spatial shift in the far-UV continuum matching the Ly&amp;alpha; offset. We discuss that H&amp;alpha; and Ly&amp;alpha; have distinct physical origins: H&amp;alpha; originates from the AGN, while Ly&amp;alpha; is powered by star formation. In the environment of A2744-45924, we identify four extended Ly&amp;alpha; halos (&amp;Delta; z&amp;lt;0.02, &amp;Delta; r&amp;lt;100 pkpc). Their Ly&amp;alpha; luminosities match expectations based on H&amp;alpha; emission, indicating no evidence for radiation from A2744-45924 affecting its surroundings. The lack of strong, compact, and broad Ly&amp;alpha; and the absence of a luminous extended halo, suggest that the UV AGN light is obscured by dense gas cloaking the SMBH with covering factor close to unity.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-14T16:40:35Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-20T14:22:39Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 12 pages, 8 figures. Main figs. 7 (radial surface brightness profile)   and 8 (Ly-alpha halo and spatial positions of spectral components). Submitted   to A&amp;A. Comments welcome &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.09542v2"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.09542v2 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Alberto Torralba</author><pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 16:40:35 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09542v2</guid></item><item><title>Ages and metallicities of quiescent galaxies: confronting broadband (UVJ) colours with stellar absorption lines</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08858v2</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Chloe M. Cheng, Mariska Kriek, Aliza G. Beverage, Martje Slob, Rachel Bezanson, Marijn Franx, Joel Leja, Pavel E. Mancera Piña, Katherine A. Suess, Arjen van der Wel, Jesse van de Sande, Pieter G. van Dokkum &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For decades, studying quiescent galaxies beyond z~1 has been challenging due to the reliance on photometric spectral energy distributions, which are highly susceptible to degeneracies between age, metallicity, dust, and star-formation history. Only recently has deep, rest-frame, optical spectroscopy made robust metallicity and age measurements possible, allowing us to empirically assess their effects on continuum shapes. To this end, we measure ages and metallicities of ~700 massive (10.2≲log(M_*/M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;)≲11.8), quiescent galaxies at 0.6≲ z≲1.0 from the Large Early Galaxy Astrophysics Census (LEGA-C) via continuum-normalized, absorption-line spectra, and compare with independent rest-frame U-V and V-J colours. Age increases along the quiescent sequence as both colours redden, consistent with stellar population synthesis (SPS) model predictions. Metallicity increases perpendicularly to the age trend, with higher metallicities at redder U-V and bluer V-J colours. Thus, age and metallicity behave differently in the UVJ diagram. Moreover, this trend conflicts with SPS model expectations of increasing metallicity approximately along the quiescent sequence. Independent dynamical mass-to-light ratio trends also differ dramatically from SPS model predictions. These results demonstrate that relying on model fits to continuum shapes alone may lead to systematic biases in ages, metallicities, and stellar masses. The cause of these data-model disparities may stem from non-solar abundance patterns in quiescent galaxies or the treatment of evolved stellar phases in the models. Resolving these discrepancies is crucial, as photometric data remain central even with JWST.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-13T18:00:00Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-26T15:58:46Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 17 pages, 7 figures, accepted for publication in MNRAS; minor   typesetting corrections after copyediting &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.08858v2"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.08858v2 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Chloe M. Cheng</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08858v2</guid></item><item><title>SHELLQs. Bridging the gap: JWST unveils obscured quasars in the most luminous galaxies at z &amp;gt; 6</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04825v2</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Yoshiki Matsuoka, Masafusa Onoue, Kazushi Iwasawa, Kentaro Aoki, Michael A. Strauss, John D. Silverman, Xuheng Ding, Camryn L. Phillips, Masayuki Akiyama, Junya Arita, Masatoshi Imanishi, Takuma Izumi, Nobunari Kashikawa, Toshihiro Kawaguchi, Satoshi Kikuta, Kotaro Kohno, Chien-Hsiu Lee, Tohru Nagao, Ayumi Takahashi, Yoshiki Toba &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The unprecedented sensitivity of the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) has uncovered a surprisingly abundant population of mildly obscured, low-luminosity active galactic nuclei (AGNs) in the epoch of reionization (EoR). However, the link between these objects and classical unobscured quasars remains a mystery. Here we report the discovery of obscured quasars hosted by the most luminous galaxies at z &amp;gt; 6, possibly bridging the gap between the two AGN populations. The 13 objects presented here were originally selected from a rest-frame ultraviolet (UV) imaging survey over &amp;gt;1000 deg&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, and were known to have luminous (&amp;gt;10^43 erg s&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) narrow Ly&amp;alpha; emission. With JWST/NIRSpec follow-up observations, we found that 7 out of 11 objects with narrow Ly&amp;alpha; exhibit a broad component in H I Balmer lines and He I lines, but not in [O III] and other forbidden lines. Mild dust obscuration (0 &amp;lt; A_V &amp;lt; 3) is inferred from the Balmer decrements. The estimated intrinsic luminosities suggest that our broad line (BL) objects are the long-sought UV-obscured counterparts of luminous quasars in the EoR. They host supermassive black holes (SMBHs) with masses 10^7.8 - 9.1 M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;, undergoing sub-Eddington to Eddington accretion. Most of the BL objects are spatially unresolved, and are close to "little red dots" with their blue rest-UV and red rest-optical colors. We estimate the AGN number density among similarly luminous Ly&amp;alpha; emitters to be larger than 2 × 10^-8 Mpc^-3. This density is comparable to that of classical quasars with similar continuum luminosities, suggesting that a substantial fraction of active SMBHs are obscured in the EoR and have been overlooked in past rest-UV surveys.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-07T21:58:21Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-30T10:49:41Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; Accepted for publication in ApJ &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.04825v2"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.04825v2 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Yoshiki Matsuoka</author><pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 21:58:21 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04825v2</guid></item><item><title>Population Models for Star Formation Timescales in Early Galaxies: The First Step Towards Solving Outshining in Star Formation History Inference</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15255v2</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Bingjie Wang, Joel Leja, Hakim Atek, Rachel Bezanson, Emilie Burnham, Pratika Dayal, Robert Feldmann, Jenny E. Greene, Benjamin D. Johnson, Ivo Labbe, Michael V. Maseda, Themiya Nanayakkara, Sedona H. Price, Katherine A. Suess, John R. Weaver, Katherine E. Whitaker &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
JWST have revealed temporarily-quenched and ultraviolet-luminous galaxies in the early universe, suggesting enhanced star formation stochasticity. Verifying this hypothesis is critical, yet challenging; outshining, wherein light from young stars dominates the spectral energy distribution, represents perhaps the greatest challenge in inferring the formation histories of unresolved galaxies. In this paper, we take a simple model of burstiness and show that state-of-the-art inference methods with flexible star formation histories (SFHs) and neutral priors, while recovering average star formation rates (SFRs; ~0.1 dex median offset), fail to recover the complexities of fluctuations on tens of Myr timescales, and typically underestimate masses in bursty systems (~0.15 dex). Surprisingly, detailed SFH recovery is still sensitive to priors even when data quality is optimal, e.g., including high signal-to-noise (20~pixel^-1) spectroscopy with wide coverage (rest-frame 0.12-1.06~&amp;mu;m). Crucially, however, refitting the same data with a prior correctly encoding the bursty expectation eliminates these biases: median offsets in mass and SFRs decrease to ~ 0.04 dex and ~ 0.05 dex, respectively. Under the assumption that current population burstiness predicts past SFH, the solution to outshining in modeling statistical samples is empirically measuring recent galaxy SFHs with population modeling. A prototype is H&amp;alpha;/UV: while helpful, it is insufficient to constrain the expected complex burstiness. To this end, we introduce a more complete, quantitative population-level approach and demonstrate that it promises to recover the typical amplitude, timescale, and slope of the recent SFH to high accuracy. This approach thus has the strong potential to solve outshining using observations from JWST.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-04-21T17:34:55Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-26T15:10:00Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; Accepted for publication in ApJ; 27 pages, 17 figures &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2504.15255v2"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2504.15255v2 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Bingjie Wang</author><pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 17:34:55 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15255v2</guid></item><item><title>How do Massive Primordial Black Holes Impact the Formation of the First Stars and Galaxies?</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17585v2</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Saiyang Zhang, Boyuan Liu, Volker Bromm, Junehyoung Jeon, Michael Boylan-Kolchin, Florian Kuhnel &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We investigate the impact of massive primordial black holes (PBHs; m_BH~ 10^6~M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;) on the star formation and first galaxy assembly process using high-resolution hydrodynamical simulations from z = 1100 to z ~ 9. We find that PBH accretion is self-regulated by feedback, suppressing mass growth unless feedback is weak. PBHs accelerate structure formation by seeding dark matter halos and gravitationally attracting gas, but strong feedback can delay cooling and suppress star formation. In addition, the presence of baryon-dark matter streaming creates an offset between the PBH location and the peaks induced in gas density, promoting earlier and more efficient star formation compared to standard &amp;Lambda;CDM. By z ~ 10, PBH-seeded galaxies form dense star clusters, with PBH-to-stellar mass ratios comparable to observed high-z AGN like UHZ-1. Our results support PBHs as viable SMBH seeds but do not exclude alternative scenarios. We emphasize that PBH-seeding provides a natural explanation for some of the newly-discovered overmassive SMBHs at high redshift, in particular those with extreme ratios of BH-to-dynamical (virial) mass that challenge standard formation channels. Future studies with ultra-deep JWST surveys, the Roman Space Telescope, and radio surveys with facilities such as SKA and HERA will be critical in distinguishing PBH-driven SMBH growth from other pathways.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-03-22T00:06:11Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-26T05:27:30Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 24 pages, 11 figures. Accepted by ApJ &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2503.17585v2"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2503.17585v2 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Saiyang Zhang</author><pubDate>Sat, 22 Mar 2025 00:06:11 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17585v2</guid></item><item><title>Where Have All the Little Red Dots Gone? Supermassive Black Hole Binary Dynamics and its Impact on Galaxy Properties</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07711v2</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Fazeel Mahmood Khan, Benjamin L. Davis, Andrea Valerio Macciò, Kelly Holley-Bockelmann &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Recent James Webb Space Telescope observations have revealed a peculiar class of galaxies at redshifts z ≳ 6, characterized by extremely high central stellar densities and overmassive central supermassive black holes (SMBHs), "little red dots" (LRDs). A critical question remains: If LRDs were common at high redshifts, how would they evolve into local elliptical galaxies with significantly lower central densities? To address this, we performed direct N-body simulations of LRD mergers, focusing on the coevolution of host galaxies and central SMBHs. We track the complete evolution of SMBH binaries into the three-body hardening and gravitational-wave (GW) emission phase. Our results demonstrate that during galaxy mergers, the central SMBHs can eject a substantial amount of mass from the galactic core via the three-body slingshot effect, leading to a decrease in central stellar surface density by an order of magnitude. Additionally, GW recoil can further contribute in making the galaxy centers less dense and more in alignment with low-redshift quiescent galaxies. This transformation occurs on a relatively short timescale of a few ~100 Myr, implying that LRDs can evolve into lower-redshift elliptical galaxies by z&amp;lt;4. The timescales for our SMBH mergers vary between 100 Myr and 800 Myr, depending on the initial orbital parameters of the merging galaxies and the mass ratio of the SMBHs. Our findings provide a plausible mechanism for the transformation of LRDs into elliptical galaxies while highlighting the efficiency of SMBH mergers in such high-density environments, which plays a crucial role in SMBH growth.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-03-10T18:00:00Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-20T12:59:44Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 12 pages, 4 figures, and 2 tables. Original unedited manuscript   accepted by The Astrophysical Journal Letters on May 19, 2025 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2503.07711v2"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2503.07711v2 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Fazeel Mahmood Khan</author><pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07711v2</guid></item><item><title>Exploring the mysterious high-ionization source powering [Ne V] in high-z analog SBS0335-052 E with JWST/MIRI</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2502.07662v2</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Matilde Mingozzi, Macarena Garcia Del Valle-Espinosa, Bethan L. James, Ryan J. Rickards Vaught, Matthew Hayes, Ricardo O. Amorín, Claus Leitherer, Alessandra Aloisi, Leslie Hunt, David Law, Chris Richardson, Aidan Pidgeon, Karla Z. Arellano-Córdova, Danielle A. Berg, John Chisholm, Svea Hernandez, Logan Jones, Nimisha Kumari, Crystal L. Martin, Swara Ravindranath, Livia Vallini, Xinfeng Xu &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Nearby blue compact dwarf galaxies (BCDs) share similar properties with objects from the Epoch of Reionization revealed by JWST, in terms of low stellar mass, low metallicity and high specific star-formation rate. Thus, they represent ideal local laboratories for detailed multi-wavelength studies to understand their properties and the mechanisms shaping them. We report the first JWST MIRI/MRS observations of the BCD SBS 0335-052 E, analyzing MIR emission lines tracing different levels of ionization (e.g., [NeII], [SIV], [NeIII], [OIV], [NeV]) of the ionized gas. SBS 0335-052 E MIR emission is characterized by a bright point source, located in one of the youngest and most embedded stellar clusters (t~3 Myr, A_V~15), and underlying extended high-ionization emission (i.e., [OIV], [NeV]) from the surroundings of the older and less dusty stellar clusters (t&amp;lt; 20 Myr, A_V~8). From the comparison with state-of-the-art models, we can exclude shocks, X-ray binaries, and old stellar populations as the main sources of the high ionization. Interestingly, a 4-16% contribution of a ~10^5 M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt; intermediate massive black hole (IMBH) is needed to justify the strong [NeV]/[NeII] and would be consistent with optical/UV line ratios from previous studies. However, even IMBH models cannot explain the strongest [OIV]/[NeIII]. Also, star-forming models (regardless of including X-ray binaries) struggle to reproduce even the lower ionization line ratios (e.g., [SIV]/[NeII]) typically observed in BCDs. Overall, while current models suggest the need to account for an accreting IMBH in this high-z analog, limitations still exist in predicting high-ionization emission lines (I.P. &amp;gt;54 eV) when modeling these low-metallicity environments, thus other sources of ionization cannot be fully ruled out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-02-11T15:53:42Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-29T18:21:38Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; Accepted for publication in ApJ &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2502.07662v2"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2502.07662v2 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Matilde Mingozzi</author><pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 15:53:42 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2502.07662v2</guid></item><item><title>On The Very Bright Dropouts Selected Using the James Webb Space Telescope NIRCam Instrument</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05751v2</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Bangzheng Sun, Haojing Yan &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The selection of candidate high-redshift galaxies using the dropout technique targeting the Lyman-break signature sometimes yields very bright objects that are too luminous to be easily explained if they are indeed at the expected redshifts. Here we present a systematic study of very bright dropouts selected through successive bands of the NIRCam instrument onboard the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST). Using the public NIRCam data in four blank fields over 500~arcmin&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, 300 such objects were found. They have F356W magnitudes &amp;lt;25.1~mag or &amp;lt;26.0~mag depending on the dropout passband, and the majority of them (&amp;gt;80&amp;percnt;) have very red F115W-F356W colors &amp;gt; 2.0~mag, qualifying them as "extremely red objects'' (EROs). We focus on 137 objects that also have mid-IR observations from the JWST MIRI instrument. Their spectral energy distribution analysis shows that these objects are dominated by low-redshift (z~1&amp;ndash;4) galaxies (≳67&amp;percnt;). However, a non-negligible fraction (≳7&amp;percnt;) could be at high redshifts. Seven of our objects have secure spectroscopic redshifts from JWST NIRSpec identifications, and the results confirm this picture: while six are low-redshift galaxies (z≈3), one is a known galaxy at z=8.679 (with M_UV=-22.4~mag and stellar mass M_*=10^9.1M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;) recovered in our sample. In light of recent theoretical models on early galaxy formation, this confirmed high-redshift galaxy does not pose a challenge. However, as our sample contains very luminous high-redshift candidates in the regime still underexplored (M_UV≤ -23~mag and M_*&amp;gt;10^10.5M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;), spectroscopic identifications are necessary to ensure they do not create tension with these new models.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-02-09T03:02:06Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-20T16:22:24Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; Accepted for publication by ApJ &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2502.05751v2"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2502.05751v2 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Bangzheng Sun</author><pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2025 03:02:06 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05751v2</guid></item><item><title>Luminous Mid-IR Selected Type-2 Quasars at Cosmic Noon in SDSS Stripe82 I: Selection, Composite Photometry, and Spectral Energy Distributions</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14026v2</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Ben Wang, Joseph F. Hennawi, Zheng Cai, Gordon T. Richards, Jan-Torge Schindler, Nadia L. Zakamska, Yuzo Ishikawa, Hollis B. Akins, Zechang Sun &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We analyze 23 spectroscopically confirmed Type-2 quasars (QSOs) selected from the WISE 22&amp;mu;m band in the SDSS Stripe 82 region, focusing on their multi-band photometry and spectral energy distributions (SEDs). These objects were selected to be IR-luminous (flux_W4 &amp;gt; 5mJy, i.e., 12.62 &amp;lt; W4 &amp;lt; 14.62  AB   magnitude), optically faint (r &amp;gt; 23) or with red color (r - W4 &amp;gt;8.38). Gemini/GNIRS observations were conducted for all 24 candidates, and 18/24 were also observed with Keck/LRIS. The observations confirm 23 to be real Type-2 QSOs in the redshift range 0.88 - 2.99 (12 are at z&amp;gt;2). We collect multi-band photometry and conduct SED fitting. The composite photometry probes the wavelength from 0.1&amp;mu;m to 10&amp;mu;m at the rest frame. The IR emission is dominated by dust torus implying an average torus luminosity for the sample of L_torus 10^46.84 erg/s. The origin of the rest-UV/optical light is not definitive, but we present three possible scenarios: scattered light, stellar emission, and the reddened accretion disk. Assuming an obscured:unobscured ratio of approximately 1:1, our targets have L_bol = 10^46.28 erg  s&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; - 10^47.49 erg  s&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; and around SMBH masses 10^8.18 M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt; - 10^9.39 M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;, assuming they accreate at the Eddington limit. Compared to previous Type-2 AGN SEDs, our targets have a brighter dust torus and redder optical-IR color. By comparing the SED to the results from JWST `little red dots' (LRDs), we find that these IR-selected Type-2 QSOs have similar SED shapes to the LRDs. This pilot Type-2 QSO survey demonstrates that mid-IR selection is an efficient way to find luminous Type-2 QSOs at z&amp;gt;2. Finally, the composite photometry and Type-2 QSOs SED model generated by this sample provide a guide for finding more Type-2 QSOs at higher redshift.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-01-23T19:00:06Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-22T04:03:33Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2501.14026v2"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2501.14026v2 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Ben Wang</author><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 19:00:06 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14026v2</guid></item><item><title>The JWST EXCELS survey: an extremely metal-poor galaxy at z=8.271 hosting an unusual population of massive stars</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11099v4</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; F. Cullen, A. C. Carnall, D. Scholte, D. J. McLeod, R. J. McLure, K. Z. Arellano-Córdova, T. M Stanton, C. T. Donnan, J. S. Dunlop, A. E. Shapley, L. Barrufet, R. Begley, C. Bondestam, M. Cirasuolo, H. -H. Leung, C. L. Pollock, S. Stevenson &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We present an analysis of the rest-frame optical (&amp;lambda; ≃ 3100-5600  &amp;#8491;) spectrum of a log_10(M_*/M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;) = 8.6 star-forming galaxy at z=8.271 from JWST/NIRSpec medium-resolution observations taken as part of the EXCELS survey. The galaxy (EXCELS-63107) is compact, with a size consistent with the size of local star-forming cluster complexes (r_e &amp;lt; 200   pc) and has an extremely steep UV continuum measured from JWST/NIRCam photometry (&amp;beta;=-3.3±0.3). The JWST/NIRSpec G395M spectrum of EXCELS-63107 is notable for its strong [OIII]&amp;lambda;4363 auroral-line emission relative to the [OIII]&amp;lambda;5007 forbidden line. Via a detailed emission-line and photoionization-modelling analysis, we find that the the observed properties of EXCELS-63107 are consistent with the presence of an ionizing source with an effective temperature of T_eff ≳ 80   000 K heating ionized gas with a density of n_e &amp;lt; 10^4   cm^-3 to a volume-averaged electron temperature of T_e ≃ 34   000 K. Crucially, we find that stellar population models assuming a standard IMF are not capable of producing the required heating. We determine an oxygen abundance of 12+log(O/H)= 6.89^+0.26_-0.21 which is one of the lowest directly constrained oxygen abundances measured in any galaxy to date, and ≃ 10 × lower than is typical for z≃8 galaxies with the same stellar mass. The extremely low metallicity of EXCELS-63107 places it in a regime in which theoretical models expect a transition to a top-heavy IMF, and we speculate that a ≃ 10-30   × excess of M &amp;gt; 50   M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt; stars is one plausible explanation for its observed properties. However, more exotic scenarios, such as Pop III star formation within a mildly enriched halo, are also consistent with the observations.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-01-19T16:19:34Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-06-02T15:14:33Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 18 pages, 11 figures, updated to the final MNRAS accepted version &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2501.11099v4"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2501.11099v4 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>F. Cullen</author><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2025 16:19:34 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11099v4</guid></item><item><title>TP-AGB stars and stellar population properties of a post-starburst galaxy at z ~ 2 through optical and NIR spectroscopy with JWST</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07291v2</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Davide Bevacqua, Paolo Saracco, Francesco La Barbera, Guido De Marchi, Roberto De Propris, Fabio Ditrani, Anna R. Gallazzi, Giovanna Giardino, Danilo Marchesini, Anna Pasquali, Tim D. Rawle, Chiara Spiniello, Alexandre Vazdekis, Stefano Zibetti &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We present a detailed optical and NIR spectral analysis of J-138717, a post-starburst galaxy at z = 1.8845 observed with JWST/NIRSpec, for which we derive a stellar mass of 3.5 ± 0.2 × 10^10 M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt; and a stellar velocity dispersion of 198 ± 10 km s&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;. We estimate an age of ~0.9 Gyr and a sub-solar metallicity (between -0.4 and -0.2 dex). We find generally consistent results when fitting the optical and NIR wavelength ranges separately or using different model libraries. The reconstruction of the star formation history indicates that the galaxy assembled most of its mass quickly and then rapidly quenched, ~0.4 Gyr prior to observation. Line diagnostics suggest that the weak emission is probably powered by residual star formation (SFR~0.2M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt; yr^-1) or a low-luminosity AGN, with no strong evidence for outflows in ionized or neutral gas. We perform a detailed study of the NIR spectral indices by comparing observations with predictions of several state-of-the-art stellar population models. This is unprecedented at such a high redshift. In particular, the analysis of several CO and CN features argues against a heavy contribution of Thermally Pulsating (TP-)AGB stars. Observations align better with models that include a minimal contribution from TP-AGB stars, but they are also consistent with a mild contribution from TP-AGB stars, assuming a younger age (consistent with the fits). The analysis of other NIR spectral indices shows that current models struggle to reproduce observations. This highlights the need for improved stellar population models in the NIR, especially at young ages and low metallicities, which is most relevant for studying high redshift galaxies in the JWST era.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-01-13T13:00:06Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-23T15:50:42Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; Accepted for publication in Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2501.07291v2"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2501.07291v2 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Davide Bevacqua</author><pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 13:00:06 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07291v2</guid></item><item><title>Diffuse Neutrino Signals from Dark Stars Seeding Super-Massive Black Holes</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18654v2</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Thomas Schwemberger, Volodymyr Takhistov &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Dark stars (DSs) &amp;ndash; first stars powered by dark-matter (DM) heating rather than fusion &amp;ndash; could form in the early Universe. They can grow to ≳ 10^5 M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt; masses and collapse into seeds of supermassive black holes (SMBHs). We demonstrate that diffuse neutrino flux generated by DSs can be observable in existing experiments and have energies reaching hundreds of MeV, providing novel window for probing SMBH progenitors. We establish first constraints on DSs and DM annihilations powering them using data from Super-Kamiokande and IceCube neutrino experiments, and consistent with James Webb Space Telescope observations. Upcoming experiments such as Hyper-Kamiokande, DUNE, JUNO will be able to explore DS properties with enhanced sensitivity.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2024-12-24T19:00:02Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-22T14:14:26Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 15 pages, 8 figures &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2412.18654v2"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2412.18654v2 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Thomas Schwemberger</author><pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 19:00:02 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18654v2</guid></item><item><title>The JWST EXCELS survey: direct estimates of C, N, and O abundances in two relatively metal-rich galaxies at z≃5</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10557v2</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; K. Z. Arellano-Córdova, F. Cullen, A. C. Carnall, D. Scholte, T. M. Stanton, C. Kobayashi, Z. Martinez, D. A. Berg, L. Barrufet, R. Begley, C. T. Donnan, J. S. Dunlop, M. L. Hamadouche, D. J. McLeod, R. J. McLure, K. Rowlands, A. E. Shapley &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We present a spectroscopic analysis of two star-forming galaxies at z≃5 observed with JWST/NIRSpec as part of the EXCELS survey. The detection of the CIII]~&amp;lambda;&amp;lambda;1906,09, [OII] &amp;lambda;&amp;lambda;3726,29, [OIII] &amp;lambda;&amp;lambda;4363,5007, and [NII] &amp;lambda;6584 emission lines enables an investigation of the C/O, N/O, and C/N abundance ratios using the temperature-sensitive method. The galaxies have stellar masses of log(M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;sext;&lt;/sub&gt;/M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;) = 8.09^+  0.24_-0.15 and log(M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;sext;&lt;/sub&gt;/M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;) = 8.02^+  0.06_-0.08 with metallicities of Z ≃ 0.2   Z&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt; and Z ≃ 0.3   Z&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;. These metallicities are somewhat higher than is typical for other z≳ 5 galaxies with similar stellar mass and are comparable to z ≃ 0 analogues. Both galaxies display evidence for elevated N/O ratios with respect to the typical star-forming galaxies at z≃0, with log(N/O) = -1.07^+ 0.17_-0.13 and log(N/O) = -0.86^+ 0.15_-0.11 respectively. In contrast, we find low C abundances, with log(C/O)=-0.82±0.22 and log(C/O)=-1.02±0.22, consistent with the predicted yields of core-collapse supernovae. Following the trend observed in other high-redshift sources, we find that the C/N ratios are lower at fixed O/H compared to the majority of local galaxies. Via a comparison to detailed chemical evolution models, we find that a standard or bottom-heavy IMF can explain the observed abundance ratios where the N-enrichment comes from intermediate mass (≃ 4-7   M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;) stars. Our results demonstrate that robust measurements of CNO abundances with phJWST can reveal unique enrichment pathways in galaxies as a function of both metallicity and redshift.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2024-12-13T21:02:27Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-22T16:21:19Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 17 pages, 8 Figures, and 3 Tables. Accepted in MNRAS &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2412.10557v2"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2412.10557v2 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>K. Z. Arellano-Córdova</author><pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 21:02:27 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10557v2</guid></item><item><title>The ionizing photon production efficiency of star-forming galaxies at z~ 4-10</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2412.01358v2</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; M. Llerena, L. Pentericci, L. Napolitano, S. Mascia, R. Amorín, A. Calabrò, M. Castellano, N. J. Cleri, M. Giavalisco, N. A. Grogin, N. P. Hathi, M. Hirschmann, A. M. Koekemoer, T. Nanayakkara, F. Pacucci, L. Shen, S. M. Wilkins, I. Yoon, L. Y. A. Yung, R. Bhatawdekar, R. A. Lucas, X. Wang, P. Arrabal Haro, M. B. Bagley, S. L. Finkelstein, J. S. Kartaltepe, E. Merlin, C. Papovich, N. Pirzkal, P. Santini &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Investigating the ionizing emission of star-forming galaxies is critical to understanding their contribution to reionization and their impact on the surrounding environment. The number of ionizing photons available to reionize the intergalactic medium (IGM) depends not only on the abundance of galaxies but also on their efficiency in producing ionizing photons ( &amp;xi;&lt;sub&gt;ion&lt;/sub&gt; ). We aim to estimate the  &amp;xi;&lt;sub&gt;ion&lt;/sub&gt;  using Balmer lines in a sample of 761 galaxies at 4≤ z ≤ 10 selected from different JWST surveys. We used the available HST and JWST photometry to perform a SED fitting in the sample to determine their physical properties. We used the BAGPIPES code and assumed a delayed exponential model for the star formation history. We used the NIRSpec spectra from prism or grating configurations to estimate Balmer luminosities and then constrained  &amp;xi;&lt;sub&gt;ion&lt;/sub&gt;  values after dust correction. We find a mean value of 10^25.22Hz erg^-1 for  &amp;xi;&lt;sub&gt;ion&lt;/sub&gt;  in the sample with an observed scatter of 0.42dex. We find an increase in the median values of  &amp;xi;&lt;sub&gt;ion&lt;/sub&gt;  which confirms the redshift evolution of  &amp;xi;&lt;sub&gt;ion&lt;/sub&gt;  found in other works. Regarding the relation with physical properties, we find a decrease of  &amp;xi;&lt;sub&gt;ion&lt;/sub&gt;  with increasing stellar mass, indicating that low-mass galaxies are efficient producers of ionizing photons. We also find an increase of  &amp;xi;&lt;sub&gt;ion&lt;/sub&gt;  with increasing specific star formation rate (sSFR) and increasing UV absolute magnitude, which indicates that faint galaxies and with high sSFR are also efficient producers. We also investigated the relation of  &amp;xi;&lt;sub&gt;ion&lt;/sub&gt;  with the EW([OIII]&amp;lambda;5007) and find that galaxies with the higher EW([OIII]) are the more efficient producers of ionizing photons. Similarly, we find that galaxies with higher O32 ratios and lower gas-phase metallicities (based on the R23 calibration) show higher  &amp;xi;&lt;sub&gt;ion&lt;/sub&gt;  values.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2024-12-02T10:35:32Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-23T16:51:46Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; Accepted for publication in A&amp;A &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2412.01358v2"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2412.01358v2 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>M. Llerena</author><pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 10:35:32 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2412.01358v2</guid></item><item><title>CO(1&amp;ndash;0) imaging reveals 10-kiloparsec molecular gas reservoirs around star-forming galaxies at high redshift</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06474v2</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Matus Rybak, J. T. Jansen, M. Frias Castillo, J. A. Hodge, P. P. van der Werf, I. Smail, G. Calistro Rivera, S. Chapman, C. -C. Chen, E. da Cunha, H. Dannerbauer, E. F. Jiménez-Andrade, C. Lagos, C. -L. Liao, E. J. Murphy, D. Scott, A. M. Swinbank, F. Walter &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Massive, intensely star-forming galaxies at high redshift require a supply of molecular gas from their gas reservoirs, replenished by infall from the surrounding circumgalactic medium, to sustain their immense star-formation rates. However, our knowledge of the extent and morphology of their cold-gas reservoirs is still in its infancy. We present the results of stacking 80 hours of JVLA observations of CO(1&amp;ndash;0) emission &amp;ndash; which traces the cold molecular gas &amp;ndash; in nineteen z=2.0-4.5 dusty, star-forming galaxies from the AS2VLA survey. The visibility-plane stack reveals extended emission with a half-light radius of 3.8±0.5~kpc, 2&amp;ndash;3× more extended than the dust-obscured star formation and 1.4±0.2× more extended than the stellar emission revealed by JWST. Stacking the [CI](1&amp;ndash;0) observations for ten galaxies from our parent sample yields a half-light radius ≤2.6~kpc, marginally smaller than CO(1&amp;ndash;0). The CO(1&amp;ndash;0) size is also comparable to the [CII] halos detected around high-redshift star-forming galaxies, suggesting these arise from molecular gas. Photo-dissociation region modelling indicates that the extended CO(1&amp;ndash;0) emission arises from clumpy, dense clouds rather than smooth, diffuse gas. Our results show that the bulk (up to 80&amp;percnt;) of molecular gas resides outside the star-forming region; with only a small part directly contributing to their current star formation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2024-11-10T14:24:14Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-27T20:53:39Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; Submitted to A&amp;A, second version 2025 May 27. 9 pages, 5 figures &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2411.06474v2"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2411.06474v2 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Matus Rybak</author><pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2024 14:24:14 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06474v2</guid></item><item><title>Compact dust-obscured star-formation and the origin of the galaxy bimodality</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2411.00279v2</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Maxime Tarrasse, Carlos Gómez-Guijarro, David Elbaz, Benjamin Magnelli, Mark Dickinson, Aurélien Henry, Maximilien Franco, Yipeng Lyu, Jean-Baptiste Billand, Rachana Bhatawdekar, Yingjie Cheng, Adriano Fontana, Steven L. Finkelstein, Giovanni Gandolfi, Nimish Hathi, Michaela Hirschmann, Benne W. Holwerda, Anton M. Koekemoer, Ray A. Lucas, Lise-Marie Seillé, Stephen Wilkins, L. Y. Aaron Yung &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
During the last decade, studies about highly attenuated and massive red star-forming galaxies (RedSFGs) at z ~ 4 have suggested that they could constitute a crucial population for unraveling the mechanisms driving the transition from vigorous star formation to quiescence at high redshifts. Since such a transition seems to be linked to a morphological transformation, studying the morphological properties of these RedSFGs is essential to our understanding of galaxy evolution. To this end, we are using JWST/NIRCam images from the CEERS survey to assemble a mass-complete sample of 188 massive galaxies at z=3-4, for which we perform resolved-SED fit. After classifying galaxies into typical blue SFGs (BlueSFGs), RedSFGs and quiescent galaxies (QGs), we compare the morphologies of each population in terms of stellar mass density, SFR density, sSFR, dust-attenuation and mass-weighted age. We find that RedSFGs and QGs present similar stellar surface density profiles and that RedSFGs manifest a dust attenuation concentration significantly higher than that of BlueSFGs at all masses. This indicates that to become quiescent, a BlueSFG must transit through a major compaction phase once it has become sufficiently massive. At the same time, we find RedSFGs and QGs to account for more than 50&amp;percnt; of galaxies with log(M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;ast;&lt;/sub&gt;/M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;)&amp;gt; 10.4 at this redshift. This transition mass corresponds to the "critical mass" delineating the bimodality between BlueSFGs and QGs in the local Universe. We then conclude that there is a bimodality between extended BlueSFGs and compact, highly attenuated RedSFGs that have undergone a major gas compaction phase enabling the latter to build a massive bulb in situ. There is evidence that this early-stage separation is at the origin of the local bimodality between BlueSFGs and QGs, which we refer to as a "primeval bimodality".
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2024-11-01T00:24:48Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-21T16:44:20Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2411.00279v2"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2411.00279v2 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Maxime Tarrasse</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:24:48 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2411.00279v2</guid></item><item><title>GA-NIFS &amp; EIGER: A merging quasar host at z=7 with an overmassive black hole</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11035v3</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Madeline A. Marshall, Minghao Yue, Anna-Christina Eilers, Jan Scholtz, Michele Perna, Chris J. Willott, Roberto Maiolino, Hannah Übler, Santiago Arribas, Andrew J. Bunker, Stephane Charlot, Bruno Rodríguez Del Pino, Torsten Böker, Stefano Carniani, Chiara Circosta, Giovanni Cresci, Francesco D'Eugenio, Gareth C. Jones, Giacomo Venturi, Rongmon Bordoloi, Daichi Kashino, Ruari Mackenzie, Jorryt Matthee, Rohan Naidu, Robert A. Simcoe &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The James Webb Space Telescope is revolutionising our ability to understand the host galaxies and local environments of high-z quasars. Here we obtain a comprehensive understanding of the host galaxy of the z=7.08 quasar J1120+0641 by combining NIRSpec integral field spectroscopy with NIRCam photometry of the host continuum emission. Our emission line maps reveal that this quasar host is undergoing a merger with a bright companion galaxy. The quasar host and the companion have similar dynamical masses of ~10^10M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;, suggesting that this is a major galaxy interaction. Through detailed quasar subtraction and SED fitting using the NIRCam data, we obtain an estimate of the host stellar mass of M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;ast;&lt;/sub&gt;=(3.0^+2.5_-1.4)×10^9M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;, with M_*=(2.7^+0.5_-0.5)×10^9M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt; for the companion galaxy. Using the H&amp;beta; Balmer line we estimate a virial black hole mass of M_BH=(1.9^+2.9_-1.1)×10^9 M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;. Thus, J1120+0641 has an extreme black hole-stellar mass ratio of M_BH/M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;ast;&lt;/sub&gt;=0.63^+0.54_-0.31, which is ~3 dex larger than expected by the local scaling relations between black hole and stellar mass. J1120+0641 is powered by an overmassive black hole with the highest reported black hole-stellar mass ratio, in a quasar host that is currently undergoing a major merger &amp;ndash; these new insights highlight the power of JWST for measuring and understanding these extreme first quasars.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2024-10-14T19:36:02Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-20T13:52:30Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; Resubmitted to A&amp;A following referee feedback &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11035v3"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.11035v3 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Madeline A. Marshall</author><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 19:36:02 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11035v3</guid></item><item><title>The Tale of Two Telescopes: How Hubble Uniquely Complements the James Webb Space Telescope: Galaxies</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01187v2</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Rogier A. Windhorst, Jake Summers, Timothy Carleton, Seth H. Cohen, Kevin S. Croker, Rolf A. Jansen, Rosalia O'Brien, Brent M. Smith, Christopher J. Conselice, Jose M. Diego, Simon P. Driver, Brenda Frye, Benne W. Holwerda, Haojing Yan &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In this paper, we present a simple but compelling argument, focusing on galaxy science, for preserving the main imagers and operational modes of the Hubble Space Telescope (HST) for as long as is technically feasible. While star-formation started at redshifts z≳10-13, when the universe was less than 300-500 Myr old, the CSFH did not peak until z≃1.9, and has steadily declined since that time. Hence, at least half of all stars in the universe formed in the era where HST provides its unique rest-frame UV view of unobscured young, massive stars tracing cosmic star-formation. By rendering a subset of the 556.3 hours of available HST images in 12 filters of the Hubble Ultra Deep Field (HUDF) in an appropriate mix of colors, we illustrate the unique capabilities of HST for galaxy science emphasizing that rest-frame UV-optical wavelength range. We then contrast this with the 52.7 publicly available hours of JWST/NIRCam images in 8 filters of the same HUDF area from the JADES project, rendering these at the redder near-IR wavelengths to illustrate the unique capabilities of JWST to detect older stellar populations at higher redshifts, as well as very dusty stellar populations and Active Galactic Nuclei (AGN). HST uniquely probes (unobscured) young, hot, massive stars in galaxies, while JWST reveals more advanced stages of older stellar populations, as well as relatively short-lived phases where galaxies produce and shed a lot of dust from intense star-formation, and the very high redshift universe (z≳10-11) not accessible by HST. We conclude that HST and JWST are highly complementary facilities that took decades to build to ensure decades of operation. To maximize return on investment on both HST and JWST, ways will need to be found to operate HST imaging instruments in all relevant modes for as long as possible into the JWST mission.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2024-10-02T02:40:28Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-27T23:18:27Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; White paper published in 2025, J. BAAS 57, 1, at the request of   NASA/STScI for the HST Senior Review of 2024. The full res HST+JWST PDF color   images are too big for astro-ph. Please view the full res PDF files on the   Zenodo links in the published paper   (https://baas.aas.org/pub/2025i009/release/1), or retrieve the full res TIFF   files and v5.pdf from: http://www.asu.edu/clas/hst/www/jwst2024/ &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.01187v2"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.01187v2 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Rogier A. Windhorst</author><pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 02:40:28 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01187v2</guid></item><item><title>Measuring Resolved Star Formation Histories from High-Precision Color-Magnitude Diagrams with StarFormationHistories.jl</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19534v2</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Christopher T. Garling, Nitya Kallivayalil, Kristen B. W. McQuinn, Jack T. Warfield, Mario Gennaro, Roger E. Cohen &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Understanding how and when galaxies formed stars over the history of the Universe is fundamental to the study of galaxy evolution. The star formation histories (SFHs) of galaxies in the local Universe can be measured with high precision using deep imaging with space telescopes. Such phresolved SFHs are based on modelling the observed color-magnitude diagram (CMD) with stellar evolution models and rely on age-sensitive features like the main sequence turn-off to measure a galaxy's star formation rate as a function of time. There are many other population-level parameters that factor into these measurements, such as the stellar initial mass function (IMF), binary fraction, and metallicity, to name a few. We present and release StarFormationHistories.jl, a modular, open-source Julia package for measuring resolved SFHs with a focus on model flexibility for these types of population parameters. The code can model unresolved photometric binaries and supports arbitrary IMFs. Random uncertainties in the SFH measurements can be quantified with Monte Carlo posterior sampling methods. We illustrate the performance of the package on JWST/NIRCAM data of the Local Group dwarf irregular galaxy WLM ≤ft(M_v≈-14.2  mag), which exhibits a complex, well-sampled CMD, and HST/ACS data of the ultra-faint Milky Way satellite dwarf galaxy Horologium I ≤ft(M_v≈-3.7  mag), which has a much simpler but sparser CMD.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2024-07-28T16:47:38Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-23T12:52:38Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 33 pages, 14 figures, 3 appendices -- updated to match published ApJS   version &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2407.19534v2"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2407.19534v2 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Christopher T. Garling</author><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2024 16:47:38 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19534v2</guid></item><item><title>Do high redshift QSOs and GRBs corroborate JWST?</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19953v3</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Eoin Ó Colgáin, M. M. Sheikh-Jabbari, Lu Yin &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) is reporting massive high redshift galaxies that appear challenging from the &amp;Lambda;CDM perspective. Interpreted as a cosmological problem, this necessitates the Planck collaboration underestimating either matter density &amp;Omega;_m or physical matter density &amp;Omega;_m h^2 at higher redshifts. Through standard frequentist profile likelihoods, we identify corroborating quasar (QSO) and gamma-ray burst (GRB) data sets where &amp;Omega;_m increases with effective redshift z_rmeff and remains anomalously large at higher redshifts. We relax the traditional priors by allowing for &amp;Omega;_m &amp;gt; 1, consistent with negative dark energy density, to locate profile likelihood peaks where possible. While the variation of &amp;Omega;_m with z_rmeff is at odds with the &amp;Lambda;CDM model, demarcating frequentist confidence intervals through differences in &amp;chi;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; in profile likelihoods, the prevailing technique in the literature, points to 3.9 &amp;sigma; and 7.9 &amp;sigma; tensions between GRBs and QSOs, respectively, and Planck-&amp;Lambda;CDM. We explain the approximations inherent in the existing profile likelihood literature, and highlight fresh methodology that generalises the prescription. We show that alternative methods, including Bayesian approaches, lead to similar tensions. Finally, in the large sample limit, we show that Feldman-Cousins prescription for frequentist confidence intervals in the presence of a boundary (prior) leads to confidence intervals that are bounded above by Wilks' theorem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2024-05-30T11:18:17Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-30T15:38:15Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; v2 comments on frequentist confidence intervals added; v3 to appear   in Physics of the Dark Universe &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2405.19953v3"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2405.19953v3 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Eoin Ó Colgáin</author><pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2024 11:18:17 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19953v3</guid></item><item><title>The impact of mass-dependent stochasticity at cosmic dawn</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2405.13108v3</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Viola Gelli, Charlotte Mason, Christopher C. Hayward &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
JWST is unveiling a surprising lack of evolution in the number densities of ultraviolet-selected (UV) galaxies at redshift z≳ 10. At the same time, observations and simulations are providing evidence for highly bursty star formation in high-z galaxies, resulting in significant scatter in their UV luminosities. Galaxies in low-mass dark matter halos are expected to experience most stochasticity due to their shallow potential wells. Here, we explore the impact of a mass-dependent stochasticity using a simple analytical model. We assume that scatter in the M_UV-M_h relation increases towards lower halo masses, following the decrease in halo escape velocity, &amp;sigma;_UV ~ M_h^-1/3, independent of redshift. Since low-mass halos are more dominant in the early universe, this model naturally predicts an increase in UV luminosity functions (LFs) at high redshifts compared to models without scatter. We make predictions for additional observables which would be affected by stochasticity and could be used to constrain its amplitude, finding: (i) galaxies are less clustered compared to the no-scatter scenario, with the difference increasing at higher-z; (ii) assuming star-bursting galaxies dominate the ionizing photon budget implies reionization starts earlier and is more gradual compared to the no-scatter case, (iii) at fixed UV magnitude galaxies should exhibit wide ranges of UV slopes, nebular emission line strengths and Balmer breaks. Comparing to observations, the mass-dependent stochasticity model successfully reproduces the observed LFs up to z~12. However, the model cannot match the observed z~14 LFs, implying additional physical processes enhance star formation efficiency in the earliest galaxies.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2024-05-21T18:00:01Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-20T15:16:51Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 11 pages, 7 figures &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2405.13108v3"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2405.13108v3 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Viola Gelli</author><pubDate>Tue, 21 May 2024 18:00:01 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2405.13108v3</guid></item><item><title>GA-NIFS: Witnessing the complex assembly of a star-forming system at z=5.7</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12955v2</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Gareth C. Jones, Andrew J. Bunker, Kseniia Telikova, Santiago Arribas, Stefano Carniani, Stephane Charlot, Francesco D'Eugenio, Roberto Maiolino, Michele Perna, Bruno Rodríguez Del Pino, Hannah Übler, Chris Willott, Manuel Aravena, Torsten Böker, Giovanni Cresci, Mirko Curti, Jorge González-López, Rodrigo Herrera-Camus, Isabella Lamperti, Eleonora Parlanti, Pablo G. Perez-Gonzalez, Vicente Villanueva &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We present observations of the z~5.7 Lyman-break galaxy HZ10 with the JWST/NIRSpec IFU in high and low spectral resolution (G395H, spectral resolving power R~2700 and PRISM, R~100, respectively), as part of the GA-NIFS program. By spatially resolving the source (spatial resolution ~0.15'' or ~0.9kpc), we find three spatially and spectrally distinct regions of line emission along with one region of strong continuum emission, all within a projected distance of &amp;lt;10kpc. The R2700 data features strong detections in H&amp;beta;, [OIII]&amp;lambda;&amp;lambda;4959,5007, [NII]&amp;lambda;&amp;lambda;6548,6584, H&amp;alpha;, and [SII]&amp;lambda;&amp;lambda;6716,6731. The R100 data additionally contains a strong detection of the Ly&amp;alpha; break, rest-frame UV and optical continuum, and [OII]&amp;lambda;&amp;lambda;3726,3729. None of the detected lines present strong evidence for AGN excitation from line diagnostic diagrams, and no high-ionisation lines are detected. Using the detected lines, we constrain the electron density ≤ft( log_10≤ft( n_e / cm^-3)~ 3) and metallicity (~0.5-0.7 solar) in each component. Spaxel-by-spaxel fits reveal a strong east-west velocity gradient and significant line asymmetries (possibly indicating tidal features or outflows). The western component features a very red UV slope (&amp;beta;_UV~-0.9) and significant H&amp;alpha; emission, suggesting an evolved population and active star formation. A comparison to high resolution (~0.3'' or ~1.8kpc) [CII]158&amp;mu;m imaging obtained with the Atacama Large Millimetre/submillimetre Array (ALMA) reveals areas of dust obscuration. Altogether, these data suggest that HZ10 represents an ongoing merger, with a complex distribution of stars, gas, and dust &amp;lt;1Gyr after the Big Bang.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2024-05-21T17:28:21Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-31T16:48:19Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 19 pages, 11 figures. Accepted for publication in MNRAS &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2405.12955v2"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2405.12955v2 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Gareth C. Jones</author><pubDate>Tue, 21 May 2024 17:28:21 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12955v2</guid></item><item><title>Direct Detection of Dark Photon Dark Matter with the James Webb Space Telescope</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2402.17140v2</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Haipeng An, Shuailiang Ge, Jia Liu, Zhiyao Lu &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In this study, we propose an investigation into dark photon dark matter (DPDM) within the infrared frequency band, utilizing highly sensitive infrared light detectors commonly integrated into space telescopes, such as the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST). The presence of DPDM induces electron oscillations in both the reflectors and the interior of the detectors. Consequently, these oscillating electrons can emit monochromatic electromagnetic waves with a frequency almost equivalent to the mass of DPDM. By estimating the signal generated by DPDM inside the detector and comparing with observation data, we establish constraints on the kinetic mixing between the photon and dark photon within the range [10, 500] THz. Despite JWST not being optimized for DPDM searches, our findings reveal constraints comparable to those obtained from the XENON1T experiment in the laboratory, as well as astrophysical constraints from solar emission. Additionally, we propose to modify the configuration of JWST optical elements to focus the DPDM induced signal onto the detector. By employing the stationary phase approximation, we can demonstrate that when the size of the reflector significantly exceeds the wavelength of the electromagnetic wave, the contribution to the electromagnetic wave field at a given position primarily stems from the surface unit perpendicular to the relative position vector. This simplification results in the reduction of electromagnetic wave calculations to ray optics. We show that by rearranging the position of reflectors, JWST can achieve a sensitivity stronger than the existing limits by 1 or 2 orders of magnitude.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2024-02-27T02:06:14Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-05-24T05:28:12Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2402.17140v2"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2402.17140v2 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Haipeng An</author><pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2024 02:06:14 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2402.17140v2</guid></item><item><title>Constraints on Bianchi-I type universe with SH0ES anchored Pantheon+ SNIa data</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2310.07661v3</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Anshul Verma, Sanjeet K. Patel, Pavan K. Aluri, Sukanta Panda, David F. Mota &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We study the Bianchi-I cosmological model motivated by signals of statistical isotropy violation seen in cosmic microwave background (CMB) observations and others. To that end, we consider various kinds of anisotropic matter that source anisotropy in our model, specifically Cosmic strings, Magnetic fields, Domain walls and Lorentz violation generated magnetic fields. These anisotropic matter sources, taking one at a time, are studied for their co-evolution with standard model (isotropic) sources viz., dust-like (dark/normal) matter, and dark energy modelled as cosmological constant. We constrain the Hubble parameter, density fractions of anisotropic matter, cold dark matter (CDM), and dark energy (&amp;Lambda;) in a Bianchi-I universe with planar symmetry i.e., which has a global ellipsoidal geometry, and try to find signatures of a cosmic preferred axis if any. The latest compilation of Type Ia Supernova (SNIa) data from Pantheon+SH0ES collaboration is used in our analysis to obtain constraints on cosmological parameters and any preferred axis for our universe. In our analysis, we found mild evidence for a cosmic preferred axis. It is interesting to note that this preferred axis lies broadly in the vicinity of other prominent cosmic anisotropy axes reported in the literature from diverse data sets. Also we find some evidence for non-zero (negative) cosmic shear and eccentricity that characterize different expansion rates in different directions and deviation from an isotropic scale factor respectively. The energy density fractions of two of the sources considered are found to be non-zero at a 2&amp;sigma; confidence level. To be more conclusive, we require more SNIa host galaxy data for tighter constraints on distance and absolute magnitude calibration which are expected to be available from the future JWST observations and others.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2023-10-11T17:02:26Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-06-01T19:03:39Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; 25 pages, 5 figures, 5 tables. Version accepted in JCAP &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2310.07661v3"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2310.07661v3 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Anshul Verma</author><pubDate>Wed, 11 Oct 2023 17:02:26 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2310.07661v3</guid></item></channel></rss>