<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>JWST arXiv Feed (feed)</title><link>https://github.com/gbrammer/arxiv-to-rss</link><description>Custom arXiv Query of JWST articles</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 05:06:28 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.1.1</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>A Study of Polycyclic Aromatic Hydrocarbon Emission in 30 Dor as seen by JWST</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18909v2</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Congcong Zhang, Joelene Hales, Els Peeters, Jan Cami, Ameek Sidhu, Junfeng Zhen &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) are responsible for strong mid-IR emission features near star-forming regions. It is well known that low-metallicity environments exhibit weaker PAH emission, but it is not clear how the metallicity affects the properties of the emitting PAH population. We present a detailed study of the PAH emission in the low-metallicity regime represented by 30 Dor in the Large Magellanic Cloud (LMC) and we compare it to the PAH emission in the Orion Bar to investigate the characteristics of the PAH population and how the environments affects the resulting IR emission. We analyze JWST observations of 30 Dor that include imaging (NIRCam, MIRI) and spectroscopy (NIRSpec/IFU, MIRI/MRS). We extracted NIRSpec/IFU and MIRI/MRS spectra from 18 apertures that cover the morphological structures of 30 Dor. We characterize the profiles and relative intensities of PAH emission in these apertures. The detailed profiles of the PAH emission bands in 30 Dor are all very similar, and compare well to those from one of the dissociation fronts (DF2) in the Orion Bar. The relative band ratios on the other hand show a much larger range than in the Orion Bar. The PAH emission in 30 Dor originates from a population with a higher ionization fraction than in the Orion Bar, and a size distribution that has more smaller PAHs. Since smaller PAHs typically photo-fragment before larger PAHs, our findings support the hypothesis that the lower PAH emission for lower metallicities is the result of inhibition of growth toward larger PAHs rather than photo-fragmentation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2024-10-24T16:59:41Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-06-06T12:37:23Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt; Due to JWST pipeline updated, the SNR of our data have been improved,   especially Nirspec, so we redo the data reduction, and find our conclusions   have changed accordingly, some sentences in this paper were even wrong.   Therefore, we decide to withdraw the arXiv article &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.18909v2"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.18909v2 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Congcong Zhang</author><pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 16:59:41 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18909v2</guid></item><item><title>A Low Metallicity Massive Contact Binary Star System Candidate in WLM identified by Hubble and James Webb Space Telescope imaging</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16393v2</link><description>
&lt;p&gt; Maude Gull, Daniel R. Weisz, Kareem El-Badry, Jan Henneco, Alessandro Savino, Meredith Durbin, Yumi Choi, Roger E. Cohen, Andrew A. Cole, Matteo Correnti, Julianne J. Dalcanton, Karoline M. Gilbert, Steven R. Goldman, Puragra Guhathakurta, Kristen B. W. McQuinn, Max J. B. Newman, Evan D. Skillman, Benjamin F. Williams &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We present archival HST and JWST ultraviolet through near infrared time series photometric observations of a massive minimal-contact binary candidate in the metal-poor galaxy WLM (Z = 0.14 Z&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;). This discovery marks the lowest metallicity contact binary candidate observed to date. We determine the nature of the two stars in the binary by using the eclipsing binary modeling software (PHysics Of Eclipsing BinariEs; PHOEBE) to train a neural network to fit our observed panchromatic multi-epoch photometry. The best fit model consists of two hot MS stars (T_1=29800^+2300_-1700 K, M_1=16^+2_-3~M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;, and T_2=18000^+5000_-5000 K, M_2=7^+5_-3~M&lt;sub&gt;&amp;odot;&lt;/sub&gt;). We discuss plausible evolutionary paths for the system, and suggest the system is likely to be currently in a contact phase before ultimately ending in a merger. Future spectroscopy will help to further narrow down evolutionary pathways. This work showcases a novel use of data of JWST and HST imaging originally taken to characterize RR Lyrae. We expect time series imaging from LSST, BlackGEM, etc. to uncover similar types of objects in nearby galaxies.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Published: &lt;/b&gt; 2024-10-21T18:07:10Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Updated: &lt;/b&gt; 2025-06-05T20:11:58Z &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; Comments: &lt;/b&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt; PDF: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.16393v2"&gt; http://arxiv.org/pdf/2410.16393v2 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

</description><author>Maude Gull</author><pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 18:07:10 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16393v2</guid></item></channel></rss>